Proverbs 14

1 The wisdom of women buildeth their house; but folly plucketh it down with her hands.

2 He that walketh in his uprightness feareth Jehovah; but he that is perverted in his ways despiseth him.

3 In the fool's mouth is a rod of pride; but the lips of the wise shall preserve them.

4 Where no oxen are, the crib is clean; but much increase is by the strength of the ox.

5 A faithful witness will not lie; but a false witness uttereth lies.

6 A scorner seeketh wisdom, and there is none for him; but knowledge is easy unto the intelligent.

7 Go from the presence of a foolish man, in whom thou perceivest not the lips of knowledge.

8 The wisdom of the prudent is to discern his way; but the folly of the foolish is deceit.

9 Fools make a mock at trespass; but for the upright there is favour.

10 The heart knoweth its own bitterness, and a stranger doth not intermeddle with its joy.

11 The house of the wicked shall be overthrown; but the tent of the upright shall flourish.

12 There is a way that seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof is the ways of death.

13 Even in laughter the heart is sorrowful, and the end of mirth is sadness.

14 The backslider in heart shall be filled with his own ways, and the good man from what is in himself.

15 The simple believeth every word; but the prudent man heedeth his going.

16 A wise man feareth and departeth from evil; but the foolish is overbearing and confident.

17 He that is soon angry dealeth foolishly, and a man of mischievous devices is hated.

18 The simple inherit folly; but the prudent are crowned with knowledge.

19 The evil bow before the good, and the wicked at the gates of the righteous man.

20 He that is poor is hated even of his own neighbour; but the rich hath many friends.

21 He that despiseth his neighbour sinneth; but he that is gracious to the afflicted, happy is he.

22 Do they not err that devise evil? but loving-kindness and truth are for those that devise good.

23 In all labour there is profit; but the talk of the lips tendeth only to want.

24 The crown of the wise is their riches; the folly of the foolish is folly.

25 A true witness delivereth souls; but deceit uttereth lies.

26 In the fear of Jehovah is strong confidence, and his children shall have a place of refuge. 27 The fear of Jehovah is a fountain of life, to turn away from the snares of death.

28 In the multitude of people is the king's glory; but in the lack of people is the ruin of a prince.

29 He that is slow to anger is of great understanding; but he that is hasty of spirit exalteth folly.

30 A sound heart is the life of the flesh; but envy the rottenness of the bones.

31 He that oppresseth the poor reproacheth his Maker; but he that honoureth Him is gracious to the needy.

32 The wicked is driven away by his evil-doing; but the righteous trusteth, even in his death.

33 Wisdom resteth in the heart of the intelligent man; but that which is in the foolish maketh itself known.

34 Righteousness exalteth a nation; but sin is a reproach to peoples.

35 The king's favour is toward a wise servant; but his wrath is against him that causeth shame.

Proverbs 15

1 A soft answer turneth away fury; but a grievous word stirreth up anger.

2 The tongue of the wise useth knowledge aright; but the mouth of the foolish poureth out folly.

3 The eyes of Jehovah are in every place, beholding the evil and the good.

4 Gentleness of tongue is a tree of life; but crookedness therein is a breaking of the spirit.

5 A fool despiseth his father's instruction; but he that regardeth reproof becometh prudent.

6 In the house of a righteous man is much treasure; but in the revenue of a wicked man is disturbance.

7 The lips of the wise disperse knowledge, but not so the heart of the foolish.

8 The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to Jehovah; but the prayer of the upright is his delight.

9 The way of a wicked man is an abomination to Jehovah; but him that pursueth righteousness he loveth.

10 Grievous correction is for him that forsaketh the path; he that hateth reproof shall die.

11 Sheol and destruction are before Jehovah; how much more then the hearts of the children of men!

12 A scorner loveth not one that reproveth him; he will not go unto the wise.

13 A joyful heart maketh a cheerful countenance; but by sorrow of heart the spirit is broken.

14 The heart of an intelligent man seeketh knowledge; but the mouth of the foolish feedeth on folly.

15 All the days of the afflicted are evil; but a cheerful heart is a continual feast.

16 Better is little with the fear of Jehovah than great store and disquietude therewith. 17 Better is a meal of herbs where love is, than a fatted ox and hatred therewith.

18 A furious man stirreth up contention; but he that is slow to anger appeaseth strife.

19 The way of the sluggard is as a hedge of thorns; but the path of the upright is made plain.

20 A wise son maketh a glad father; but a foolish man despiseth his mother.

21 Folly is joy to him that is void of sense; but a man of understanding regulateth his walk.

22 Without counsel purposes are disappointed; but in the multitude of counsellors they are established.

23 A man hath joy by the answer of his mouth; and a word in its season, how good is it!

24 The path of life is upwards for the wise, that he may depart from Sheol beneath.

25 Jehovah plucketh up the house of the proud; but he establisheth the boundary of the widow.

26 The thoughts of the evil man are an abomination to Jehovah; but pure words are pleasant.

27 He that is greedy of gain troubleth his own house; but he that hateth gifts shall live.

28 The heart of a righteous man studieth to answer; but the mouth of the wicked poureth out evil things.

29 Jehovah is far from the wicked; but he heareth the prayer of the righteous.

30 That which enlighteneth the eyes rejoiceth the heart; good tidings make the bones fat.

31 The ear that heareth the reproof of life shall abide among the wise.

32 He that refuseth instruction despiseth his own soul; but he that heareth reproof getteth sense.

33 The fear of Jehovah is the discipline of wisdom, and before honour goeth humility.

Proverbs 17

1 Better is a dry morsel, and quietness therewith, than a house full of feasting with strife.

2 A wise servant shall rule over a son that causeth shame, and shall have part in the inheritance among the brethren.

3 The fining-pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold; but Jehovah trieth the hearts.

4 The evil-doer giveth heed to iniquitous lips; the liar giveth ear to a mischievous tongue.

5 Whoso mocketh a poor man reproacheth his Maker; he that is glad at calamity shall not be held innocent.

6 Children's children are the crown of old men; and the glory of children are their fathers.

7 Excellent speech becometh not a vile man; how much less do lying lips a noble!

8 A gift is a precious stone in the eyes of the possessor: whithersoever it turneth it prospereth.

9 He that covereth transgression seeketh love; but he that bringeth a matter up again separateth very friends.

10 A reproof entereth more deeply into him that hath understanding than a hundred stripes into a fool.

11 An evil man seeketh only rebellion; but a cruel messenger shall be sent against him.

12 Let a bear robbed of her whelps meet a man rather than a fool in his folly.

13 Whoso rewardeth evil for good, evil shall not depart from his house.

14 The beginning of contention is as when one letteth out water; therefore leave off strife before it become vehement.

15 He that justifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the righteous, even they both are abomination to Jehovah.

16 To what purpose is there a price in the hand of a fool to get wisdom, seeing he hath no sense?

17 The friend loveth at all times, and a brother is born for adversity.

18 A senseless man striketh hands, becoming surety for his neighbour.

19 He loveth transgression that loveth a quarrel; he that maketh high his gate seeketh destruction.

20 He that hath a perverse heart findeth no good; and he that shifteth about with his tongue falleth into evil.

21 He that begetteth a fool doeth it to his sorrow, and the father of a vile man hath no joy.

22 A joyful heart promoteth healing; but a broken spirit drieth up the bones.

23 A wicked man taketh a gift out of the bosom, to pervert the paths of judgment.

24 Wisdom is before him that hath understanding; but the eyes of a fool are in the ends of the earth.

25 A foolish son is a grief to his father, and bitterness to her that bore him.

26 To punish a righteous man is not good, nor to strike nobles because of their uprightness.

27 He that hath knowledge spareth his words; and a man of understanding is of a cool spirit. 28 Even a fool when he holdeth his peace is reckoned wise, and he that shutteth his lips, intelligent.

Proverbs 18

1 He that separateth himself seeketh his pleasure, he is vehement against all sound wisdom.

2 A fool hath no delight in understanding, but only that his heart may reveal itself.

3 When the wicked cometh, there cometh also contempt, and with ignominy reproach.

4 The words of a man's mouth are deep waters, and the fountain of wisdom is a gushing brook.

5 It is not good to accept the person of the wicked, to wrong the righteous in judgment.

6 A fool's lips enter into contention, and his mouth calleth for stripes. 7 A fool's mouth is destruction to him, and his lips are a snare to his soul.

8 The words of a talebearer are as dainty morsels, and they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.

9 He also who is indolent in his work is brother of the destroyer.

10 The name of Jehovah is a strong tower: the righteous runneth into it, and is safe.

11 The rich man's wealth is his strong city, and as a high wall in his own imagination.

12 Before destruction the heart of man is haughty; and before honour goeth humility.

13 He that giveth answer before he heareth, it is folly and shame unto him.

14 The spirit of a man sustaineth his infirmity; but a broken spirit who can bear?

15 The heart of an intelligent man getteth knowledge, and the ear of the wise seeketh knowledge.

16 A man's gift maketh room for him, and bringeth him before great men.

17 He that is first in his own cause seemeth just; but his neighbour cometh and searcheth him.

18 The lot causeth contentions to cease, and parteth between the mighty.

19 A brother offended is harder to be won than a strong city; and contentions are as the bars of a palace.

20 A man's belly is satisfied with the fruit of his mouth; with the increase of his lips is he satisfied.

21 Death and life are in the power of the tongue, and they that love it shall eat the fruit thereof.

22 Whoso hath found a wife hath found a good thing, and hath obtained favour from Jehovah.

23 He that is poor speaketh with supplications, but the rich answereth roughly.

24 A man of many friends will come to ruin but there is a friend that sticketh closer than a brother.

Proverbs 19

1 Better is a poor man that walketh in his integrity, than he that is perverse in his lips, and is a fool.

2 Also that a person be without knowledge is not good; and he that hasteth with his feet maketh false steps.

3 The folly of man distorteth his way, and his heart is irritated against Jehovah.

4 Wealth addeth many friends; but the poor is separated from his friend.

5 A false witness shall not be held innocent, and he that uttereth lies shall not escape.

6 Many court the favour of a noble; and every one is friend to a man that giveth. 7 All the brethren of a poor man hate him; how much more do his friends go far from him: he pursueth them with words, --they are not to be found.

8 He that getteth sense loveth his own soul; he that keepeth understanding shall find good.

9 A false witness shall not be held innocent, and he that uttereth lies shall perish.

10 Good living beseemeth not a fool; how much less for a servant to have rule over princes.

11 The discretion of a man maketh him slow to anger, and it is his glory to pass over a transgression.

12 The king's displeasure is as the roaring of a lion; but his favour is as dew upon the grass.

13 A foolish son is the calamity of his father; and the contentions of a wife are a continual dropping.

14 House and wealth are an inheritance from fathers; but a prudent wife is from Jehovah.

15 Slothfulness casteth into a deep sleep, and the idle soul shall suffer hunger.

16 He that keepeth the commandment keepeth his soul; he that is careless of his ways shall die.

17 He that is gracious to the poor lendeth unto Jehovah; and what he hath bestowed will he repay unto him.

18 Chasten thy son, seeing there is hope; but set not thy soul upon killing him.

19 A man of great wrath shall suffer punishment; for if thou deliver him, yet thou must do it again.

20 Hear counsel, and receive instruction, that thou mayest be wise in thy latter end.

21 Many are the thoughts in a man's heart, but the counsel of Jehovah, that doth stand.

22 The charm of a man is his kindness; and a poor man is better than a liar.

23 The fear of Jehovah tendeth to life, and he that hath it shall rest satisfied without being visited with evil.

24 A sluggard burieth his hand in the dish, and will not even bring it to his mouth again.

25 Smite a scorner, and the simple will beware; reprove the intelligent, and he will understand knowledge.

26 He that ruineth his father and chaseth away his mother is a son that causeth shame and bringeth reproach.

27 Cease, my son, to hear the instruction which causeth to stray from the words of knowledge.

28 A witness of Belial scorneth judgment, and the mouth of the wicked swalloweth down iniquity.

29 Judgments are prepared for scorners, and stripes for the back of the foolish.

Proverbs 20

1 Wine is a scorner, strong drink is raging; and whoso erreth thereby is not wise.

2 The terror of a king is as the roaring of a lion: he that provoketh him to anger sinneth against his own soul.

3 It is an honour for a man to cease from strife; but every fool rusheth into it.

4 The sluggard will not plough by reason of the winter; he shall beg in harvest, and have nothing.

5 Counsel in the heart of man is deep water, and a man of understanding draweth it out.

6 Most men will proclaim every one his own kindness; but a faithful man who shall find?

7 The righteous walketh in his integrity: blessed are his children after him!

8 A king sitting on the throne of judgment scattereth away all evil with his eyes.

9 Who can say, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my sin?

10 Divers weights, divers measures, even both of them are abomination to Jehovah.

11 Even a child is known by his doings, whether his work be pure, and whether it be right.

12 The hearing ear, and the seeing eye, Jehovah hath made even both of them.

13 Love not sleep, lest thou come to poverty; open thine eyes, and thou shalt be satisfied with bread.

14 Bad! bad! saith the buyer; but when he is gone his way, then he boasteth.

15 There is gold, and a multitude of rubies; but the lips of knowledge are a precious Jewel.

16 Take his garment that is become surety for another, and hold him in pledge for strangers.

17 Bread of falsehood is sweet to a man, but afterwards his mouth shall be filled with gravel.

18 Plans are established by counsel; and with good advice make war.

19 He that goeth about talebearing revealeth secrets; therefore meddle not with him that openeth his lips.

20 Whoso curseth his father or his mother, his lamp shall be put out in the blackest darkness.

21 An inheritance obtained hastily at the beginning will not be blessed in the end.

22 Say not, I will recompense evil: wait on Jehovah, and he shall save thee.

23 Divers weights are an abomination unto Jehovah; and a false balance is not good.

24 The steps of a man are from Jehovah; and how can a man understand his own way?

25 It is a snare to a man rashly to say, It is hallowed, and after vows to make inquiry.

26 A wise king scattereth the wicked, and bringeth the wheel over them.

27 Man's spirit is the lamp of Jehovah, searching all the inner parts of the belly.

28 Mercy and truth preserve the king; and he upholdeth his throne by mercy.

29 The glory of young men is their strength; and the beauty of old men is the grey head.

30 Wounding stripes purge away evil, and strokes purge the inner parts of the belly.

Proverbs 21

1 The king's heart in the hand of Jehovah is as brooks of water: he turneth it whithersoever he will.

2 Every way of a man is right in his own eyes; but Jehovah weigheth the hearts.

3 To exercise justice and judgment is more acceptable to Jehovah than sacrifice.

4 Lofty eyes, and a proud heart, the lamp of the wicked, is sin.

5 The thoughts of the diligent tend only to plenteousness; but of every one that is hasty, only to want.

6 The getting of treasures by a lying tongue is a fleeting breath of them that seek death.

7 The devastation of the wicked sweepeth them away, because they refuse to do what is right.

8 Very crooked is the way of a guilty man; but as for the pure, his work is upright.

9 It is better to dwell in a corner of the housetop, than with a contentious woman, and a house in common.

10 The soul of the wicked desireth evil: his neighbour findeth no favour in his eyes.

11 When the scorner is punished, the simple becometh wise; and when the wise is instructed, he receiveth knowledge.

12 One that is righteous wisely considereth the house of the wicked: he overthroweth the wicked to their ruin.

13 Whoso stoppeth his ears at the cry of the poor, he also himself shall cry, and shall not be heard.

14 A gift in secret pacifieth anger; and a present in the bosom, vehement fury.

15 It is joy to a righteous man to do what is right; but it is ruin for the workers of iniquity.

16 The man that wandereth out of the way of wisdom shall abide in the congregation of the dead.

17 He that loveth mirth shall be a poor man; he that loveth wine and oil shall not be rich.

18 The wicked is a ransom for the righteous, and a treacherous man in the stead of the upright.

19 It is better to dwell in a desert land. than with a contentious and irritable woman.

20 There is costly store and oil in the dwelling of a wise man; but a foolish man swalloweth it up.

21 He that followeth after righteousness and mercy findeth life, righteousness, and honour.

22 A wise man scaleth the city of the mighty, and casteth down the strength of the confidence thereof.

23 Whoso keepeth his mouth and his tongue keepeth his soul from troubles.

24 Proud, arrogant, scorner is his name who dealeth in proud wrath.

25 The desire of the sluggard killeth him; for his hands refuse to work: 26 He coveteth greedily all the day long; but the righteous giveth and spareth not.

27 The sacrifice of the wicked is abomination: how much more when they bring it with a wicked purpose!

28 A lying witness shall perish; and a man that heareth shall speak constantly.

29 A wicked man hardeneth his face; but as for the upright, he establisheth his way.

30 There is no wisdom, nor understanding, nor counsel against Jehovah. 31 The horse is prepared for the day of battle; but safety is of Jehovah.

Proverbs 22

1 A good name is rather to be chosen than great riches; loving favour rather than silver and gold.

2 The rich and poor meet together; Jehovah is the maker of them all.

3 A prudent man seeth the evil, and hideth himself; but the simple pass on, and are punished.

4 The reward of humility and the fear of Jehovah is riches, and honour, and life.

5 Thorns and snares are in the way of the perverse: he that keepeth his soul holdeth himself far from them.

6 Train up the child according to the tenor of his way, and when he is old he will not depart from it.

7 The rich ruleth over the poor; and the borrower is servant to the lender.

8 He that soweth unrighteousness shall reap iniquity, and the rod of his wrath shall have an end.

9 He that hath a bountiful eye shall be blessed, for he giveth of his bread to the poor.

10 Cast out the scorner, and contention will depart, and strife and ignominy shall cease.

11 He that loveth pureness of heart, upon whose lips is grace, the king is his friend.

12 The eyes of Jehovah preserve knowledge; but he overthroweth the words of the unfaithful.

13 The sluggard saith, There is a lion without, I shall be killed in the streets!

14 The mouth of strange women is a deep ditch: he with whom Jehovah is displeased shall fall therein.

15 Folly is bound in the heart of a child; the rod of correction shall drive it far from him.

16 He that oppresseth the poor, it is to enrich him; he that giveth to the rich, bringeth only to want.

17 Incline thine ear, and hear the words of the wise, and apply thy heart unto my knowledge. 18 For it is a pleasant thing if thou keep them within thee: they shall be together fitted on thy lips. 19 That thy confidence may be in Jehovah, I have made them known to thee this day, even to thee. 20 Have not I written to thee excellent things, in counsels and knowledge, 21 that I might make thee know the certainty of the words of truth; that thou mightest carry back words of truth to them that send thee?

22 Rob not the poor, because he is poor, neither oppress the afflicted in the gate; 23 for Jehovah will plead their cause, and despoil the soul of those that despoil them.

24 Make no friendship with an angry man, and go not with a furious man; 25 lest thou learn his paths, and get a snare to thy soul.

26 Be not of them that strike hands, of them that are sureties for debts: 27 if thou hast nothing to pay, why should he take away thy bed from under thee?

28 Remove not the ancient landmark which thy fathers have set.

29 Hast thou seen a man diligent in his work? He shall stand before kings; he shall not stand before the mean.

Proverbs 23

1 When thou sittest to eat with a ruler, consider well who is before thee; 2 and put a knife to thy throat, if thou be a man given to appetite. 3 Be not desirous of his dainties; for they are deceitful food.

4 Weary not thyself to become rich; cease from thine own intelligence: 5 wilt thou set thine eyes upon it, it is gone; for indeed it maketh itself wings and it flieth away as an eagle towards the heavens.

6 Eat thou not the food of him that hath an evil eye, neither desire thou his dainties. 7 For as he thinketh in his soul, so is he. Eat and drink! will he say unto thee; but his heart is not with thee. 8 Thy morsel which thou hast eaten must thou vomit up, and thou wilt have wasted thy sweet words.

9 Speak not in the ears of a foolish man, for he will despise the wisdom of thy words.

10 Remove not the ancient landmark; and enter not into the fields of the fatherless: 11 for their redeemer is mighty; he will plead their cause against thee.

12 Apply thy heart unto instruction, and thine ears to the words of knowledge. 13 Withhold not correction from the child; for if thou beatest him with the rod, he shall not die: 14 thou shalt beat him with the rod, and shalt deliver his soul from Sheol. 15 My son, if thy heart be wise, my heart shall rejoice, even mine; 16 and my reins shall exult, when thy lips speak right things.

17 Let not thy heart envy sinners, but be thou in the fear of Jehovah all the day; 18 for surely there is a result, and thine expectation shall not be cut off.

19 Thou, my son, hear and be wise, and direct thy heart in the way. 20 Be not among winebibbers, among riotous eaters of flesh. 21 For the drunkard and the glutton shall come to poverty; and drowsiness clotheth with rags. 22 Hearken unto thy father that begat thee, and despise not thy mother when she is old. 23 Buy the truth, and sell it not; wisdom, and instruction, and intelligence. 24 The father of a righteous man shall greatly rejoice, and he that begetteth a wise son shall have joy of him: 25 let thy father and thy mother have joy, and let her that bore thee rejoice. 26 My son, give me thy heart, and let thine eyes observe my ways. 27 For a whore is a deep ditch; and a strange woman is a narrow pit. 28 She also lieth in wait as a robber, and increaseth the treacherous among men.

29 Who hath woe? Who hath sorrow? Who contentions? Who complaining? Who wounds without cause? Who redness of eyes? 30 --They that tarry long at the wine; they that go to try mixed wine. 31 Look not upon the wine when it is red, when it sparkleth in the cup, and goeth down smoothly: 32 at the last it biteth like a serpent, and stingeth like an adder. 33 Thine eyes shall behold strange women, and thy heart shall speak froward things; 34 and thou shalt be as he that lieth down in the midst of the sea, and as he that lieth down upon the top of a mast: 35 --"They have smitten me, and I am not sore; they have beaten me, and I knew it not. When shall I awake? I will seek it yet again."

Proverbs 24

1 Be not thou envious of evil men, neither desire to be with them; 2 for their heart studieth destruction, and their lips talk of mischief.

3 Through wisdom is a house built, and by understanding it is established; 4 and by knowledge are the chambers filled with all precious and pleasant substance. 5 A wise man is strong, and a man of knowledge increaseth strength. 6 For with good advice shalt thou make thy war; and in the multitude of counsellors there is safety.

7 Wisdom is too high for a fool: he will not open his mouth in the gate. 8 He that deviseth to do evil shall be called a master of intrigues. 9 The purpose of folly is sin, and the scorner is an abomination to men.

10 If thou losest courage in the day of trouble, thy strength is small.

11 Deliver them that are taken forth unto death, and withdraw not from them that stagger to slaughter. 12 If thou sayest, Behold, we knew it not, will not he that weigheth the hearts consider it? And he that preserveth thy soul, he knoweth it; and he rendereth to man according to his work.

13 Eat honey, my son, for it is good; and a honeycomb is sweet to thy taste: 14 so consider wisdom for thy soul; if thou hast found it, there shall be a result, and thine expectation shall not be cut off.

15 Lay not wait, O wicked man, against the dwelling of the righteous; lay not waste his resting-place. 16 For the righteous falleth seven times, and riseth up again; but the wicked stumble into disaster.

17 Rejoice not when thine enemy falleth, and let not thy heart be glad when he stumbleth; 18 lest Jehovah see it, and it be evil in his sight, and he turn away his anger from him.

19 Fret not thyself because of evil-doers, and be not envious of the wicked: 20 for there shall be no future to the evil man; the lamp of the wicked shall be put out.

21 My son, fear Jehovah and the king: meddle not with them that are given to change. 22 For their calamity shall rise suddenly; and who knoweth the ruin of them both?

23 These things also come from the wise. It is not good to have respect of persons in judgment. 24 He that saith unto the wicked, Thou art righteous, peoples shall curse him, nations shall abhor him; 25 but to them that rebuke him shall be delight, and a good blessing cometh upon them. 26 He kisseth the lips who giveth a right answer.

27 Prepare thy work without, and put thy field in order, and afterwards build thy house.

28 Be not a witness against thy neighbour without cause; and wouldest thou deceive with thy lips? 29 Say not, I will do so to him as he hath done to me, I will render to the man according to his work.

30 I went by the field of a sluggard, and by the vineyard of a man void of understanding; 31 and lo, it was all grown over with thistles, and nettles had covered the face thereof, and its stone wall was broken down. 32 Then I looked, I took it to heart; I saw, I received instruction: 33 --A little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to rest! 34 So shall thy poverty come as a roving plunderer, and thy penury as an armed man.

Proverbs 25

1 These are also proverbs of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah king of Judah transcribed.

2 It is the glory of God[*] to conceal a thing; but the glory of kings is to search out a thing. 3 The heavens for height, and the earth for depth, and the heart of kings is unsearchable.

4 Take away the dross from the silver, and there cometh forth a vessel for the refiner: 5 take away the wicked from before the king, and his throne shall be established in righteousness.

6 Put not thyself forward in the presence of the king, and stand not in the place of the great; 7 for better it is that it be said unto thee, Come up hither, than that thou shouldest be put lower in the presence of the prince whom thine eyes see.

8 Go not forth hastily to strive, lest thou know not what to do in the end thereof, when thy neighbour hath put thee to shame. 9 Debate thy cause with thy neighbour, but reveal not the secret of another; 10 lest he that heareth it disgrace thee, and thine evil report turn not away.

11 As apples of gold in pictures of silver, is a word spoken in season. 12 An ear-ring of gold, and an ornament of fine gold, is a wise reprover upon an attentive ear.

13 As the cold of snow in the time of harvest, so is a faithful messenger to them that send him: for he refresheth the soul of his masters.

14 Clouds and wind without rain, so is a man that boasteth himself of a false gift.

15 By long forbearing is a ruler persuaded, and a soft tongue breaketh the bone.

16 Hast thou found honey? Eat so much as is sufficient for thee, lest thou be surfeited therewith, and vomit it.

17 Let thy foot be seldom in thy neighbour's house; lest he be weary of thee and hate thee.

18 A maul, and a sword, and a sharp arrow, is a man that beareth false witness against his neighbour.

19 A broken tooth, and a tottering foot, is confidence in an unfaithful man in the day of trouble.

20 As he that taketh off a garment in cold weather, and as vinegar upon nitre, so is he that singeth songs to a sad heart.

21 If thine enemy be hungry, give him bread to eat; and if he be thirsty, give him water to drink: 22 for thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head, and Jehovah shall reward thee.

23 The north wind bringeth forth rain, and the angry countenance a backbiting tongue.

24 It is better to dwell in a corner of the housetop, than with a contentious woman, and a house in common.

25 As cold waters to a thirsty soul, so is good news from a far country.

26 A troubled fountain, and a defiled well, is a righteous man that giveth way before the wicked.

27 It is not good to eat much honey; and to search into weighty matters is itself a weight.

28 He that hath no rule over his own spirit is as a city broken down, without walls.

Hebrew: Elohim

Proverbs 26

1 As snow in summer, and as rain in harvest, so honour beseemeth not a fool.

2 As the sparrow for flitting about, as the swallow for flying, so a curse undeserved shall not come.

3 A whip for the horse, a bridle for the ass, and a rod for the back of fools.

4 Answer not a fool according to his folly, lest thou also be like unto him. 5 Answer a fool according to his folly, lest he be wise in his own eyes.

6 He that sendeth a message by the hand of a fool cutteth off his own feet, and drinketh damage. 7 The legs of the lame hang loose; so is a proverb in the mouth of fools. 8 As a bag of gems in a stoneheap, so is he that giveth honour to a fool. 9 As a thorn goeth up into the hand of a drunkard, so is a proverb in the mouth of fools.

10 A master roughly worketh every one: he both hireth the fool and hireth passers-by.

11 As a dog turneth back to its vomit, so a fool repeateth his folly.

12 Hast thou seen a man wise in his own eyes? There is more hope of a fool than of him.

13 The sluggard saith, There is a fierce lion in the way; a lion is in the midst of the streets!

14 As the door turneth upon its hinges, so the sluggard upon his bed.

15 The sluggard burieth his hand in the dish: it wearieth him to bring it again to his mouth.

16 A sluggard is wiser in his own eyes than seven men that answer discreetly.

17 He that passing by vexeth himself with strife belonging not to him, is like one that taketh a dog by the ears.

18 As a madman who casteth firebrands, arrows, and death, 19 so is a man that deceiveth his neighbour, and saith, Am I not in sport?

20 Where no wood is, the fire goeth out; and where there is no talebearer, the contention ceaseth. 21 As coals for hot coals, and wood for fire, so is a contentious man to inflame strife. 22 The words of a talebearer are as dainty morsels, and they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.

23 Ardent lips, and a wicked heart, are as an earthen vessel overlaid with silver dross.

24 He that hateth dissembleth with his lips, but he layeth up deceit within him: 25 when his voice is gracious, believe him not, for there are seven abominations in his heart. 26 Though his hatred is covered by dissimulation, his wickedness shall be made manifest in the congregation.

27 Whoso diggeth a pit shall fall therein; and he that rolleth a stone, it shall return upon him.

28 A lying tongue hateth those that are injured by it, and a flattering mouth worketh ruin.

Proverbs 27

1 Boast not thyself of to-morrow, for thou knowest not what a day will bring forth.

2 Let another praise thee, and not thine own mouth; a stranger, and not thine own lips.

3 A stone is heavy, and the sand weighty; but a fool's vexation is heavier than them both. 4 Fury is cruel, and anger is outrageous; but who is able to stand before jealousy?

5 Open rebuke is better than hidden love. 6 Faithful are the wounds of a friend; but the kisses of an enemy are profuse.

7 The full soul trampleth on a honeycomb; but to the hungry soul every bitter thing is sweet.

8 As a bird that wandereth from her nest, so is a man that wandereth from his place.

9 Ointment and perfume rejoice the heart; and the sweetness of one's friend is the fruit of hearty counsel. 10 Thine own friend, and thy father's friend, forsake not; and go not into thy brother's house in the day of thy calamity: better is a neighbour that is near than a brother far off.

11 Be wise, my son, and make my heart glad, that I may have wherewith to answer him that reproacheth me.

12 A prudent man seeth the evil, and hideth himself; the simple pass on, and are punished.

13 Take his garment that is become surety for another, and hold him in pledge for a strange woman.

14 He that blesseth his friend with a loud voice, rising early in the morning, it shall be reckoned a curse to him.

15 A continual dropping on a very rainy day and a contentious woman are alike: 16 whosoever will restrain her restraineth the wind, and his right hand encountereth oil.

17 Iron is sharpened by iron; so a man sharpeneth the countenance of his friend.

18 Whoso keepeth the fig-tree shall eat the fruit thereof; and he that guardeth his master shall be honoured.

19 As in water face answereth to face, so the heart of man to man.

20 Sheol and destruction are insatiable; so the eyes of man are never satisfied.

21 The fining-pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold; so let a man be to the mouth that praiseth him.

22 If thou shouldest bray a fool in a mortar among wheat with a pestle, yet will not his folly depart from him.

23 Be well acquainted with the appearance of thy flocks; look well to thy herds: 24 for wealth is not for ever; and doth the crown endure from generation to generation? 25 The hay is removed, and the tender grass sheweth itself, and herbs of the mountains are gathered in. 26 The lambs are for thy clothing, and the goats are the price of a field; 27 and there is goats' milk enough for thy food, for the food of thy household, and sustenance for thy maidens.

Proverbs 28

1 The wicked flee when no man pursueth; but the righteous are bold as a lion.

2 By the transgression of a land many are the princes thereof; but by a man of understanding and of knowledge, its stability is prolonged.

3 A poor man who oppresseth the helpless is a sweeping rain which leaveth no food.

4 They that forsake the law praise the wicked; but such as keep the law contend with them.

5 Evil men understand not judgment; but they that seek Jehovah understand everything.

6 Better is the poor that walketh in his integrity, than he that is perverse, double in ways, though he be rich.

7 Whoso observeth the law is a son that hath understanding; but he that is a companion of profligates bringeth shame to his father.

8 He that by usury and unjust gain increaseth his substance gathereth it for him that is gracious to the poor.

9 He that turneth away his ear from hearing the law, even his prayer is an abomination.

10 Whoso causeth the upright to go astray in an evil way, shall himself fall into his own pit; but the perfect shall inherit good.

11 A rich man is wise in his own eyes; but the poor that hath understanding searcheth him out.

12 When the righteous triumph, there is great glory; but when the wicked rise, men conceal themselves.

13 He that covereth his transgressions shall not prosper; but whoso confesseth and forsaketh them shall obtain mercy.

14 Happy is the man that feareth always; but he that hardeneth his heart shall fall into evil.

15 A roaring lion, and a ranging bear, is a wicked ruler over a poor people.

16 The prince void of intelligence is also a great oppressor: he that hateth covetousness shall prolong his days.

17 A man laden with the blood of any person, fleeth to the pit: let no man stay him.

18 Whoso walketh in integrity shall be saved; but he that is perverted in his double ways, shall fall in one of them.

19 He that tilleth his land shall be satisfied with bread; but he that followeth the worthless shall have poverty enough.

20 A faithful man aboundeth with blessings; but he that maketh haste to be rich shall not be innocent.

21 To have respect of persons is not good; but for a piece of bread will a man transgress.

22 He that hath an evil eye hasteth after wealth, and knoweth not that poverty shall come upon him.

23 He that rebuketh a man shall afterwards find more favour than he that flattereth with the tongue.

24 Whoso robbeth his father and his mother, and saith, It is no transgression, the same is the companion of a destroyer.

25 He that is puffed up in soul exciteth contention; but he that relieth upon Jehovah shall be made fat.

26 He that confideth in his own heart is a fool; but whoso walketh wisely, he shall be delivered.

27 He that giveth unto the poor shall not lack; but he that withdraweth his eyes shall have many a curse.

28 When the wicked rise, men hide themselves; but when they perish, the righteous increase.

Proverbs 29

1 He that being often reproved hardeneth his neck, shall suddenly be destroyed, and without remedy.

2 When the righteous increase, the people rejoice; but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourn.

3 Whoso loveth wisdom rejoiceth his father; but he that is a companion of harlots destroyeth his substance.

4 A king by just judgment establisheth the land; but he that taketh gifts overthroweth it.

5 A man that flattereth his neighbour spreadeth a net for his steps.

6 In the transgression of an evil man there is a snare; but the righteous shall sing and rejoice.

7 The righteous taketh knowledge of the cause of the poor; the wicked understandeth not knowledge.

8 Scornful men set the city in a flame; but the wise turn away anger.

9 If a wise man contendeth with a fool, whether he rage or laugh, he hath no rest.

10 The bloodthirsty hate the perfect, but the upright care for his soul.

11 A fool uttereth all his mind; but a wise man keepeth it back.

12 If a ruler hearken to lying words, all his servants are wicked.

13 The indigent and the oppressor meet together; Jehovah lighteneth the eyes of them both.

14 A king that faithfully judgeth the poor, his throne shall be established for ever.

15 The rod and reproof give wisdom; but a child left to himself bringeth his mother to shame.

16 When the wicked increase, transgression increaseth; but the righteous shall see their fall.

17 Chasten thy son, and he shall give thee rest, and shall give delight unto thy soul.

18 Where there is no vision the people cast off restraint; but happy is he that keepeth the law.

19 A servant is not corrected by words: he understandeth indeed, but he will not answer.

20 Hast thou seen a man hasty in his words? there is more hope of a fool than of him.

21 He that delicately bringeth up his servant from a child, shall in the end have him as a son.

22 An angry man exciteth contention; and a furious man aboundeth in transgression.

23 A man's pride bringeth him low; but the humble in spirit shall obtain honour.

24 Whoso shareth with a thief hateth his own soul: he heareth the adjuration, and declareth not.

25 The fear of man bringeth a snare; but whoso putteth his confidence in Jehovah is protected.

26 Many seek the ruler's face; but a man's right judgment is from Jehovah.

27 An unjust man is an abomination to the righteous; and he that is of upright way is an abomination to the wicked man.

Proverbs 30

1 The words of Agur the son of Jakeh; the prophecy uttered by the man unto Ithiel, even unto Ithiel and Ucal: 2 Truly I am more stupid than any one; and I have not a man's intelligence. 3 I have neither learned wisdom, nor have I the knowledge of the Holy. 4 Who hath ascended up into the heavens, and descended? Who hath gathered the wind in his fists? Who hath bound the waters in a mantle? Who hath established all the ends of the earth? What is his name, and what is his son's name, if thou knowest? 5 Every word of +God[*] is pure: he is a shield unto them that put their trust in him. 6 Add thou not unto his words, lest he reprove thee, and thou be found a liar.

7 Two things do I ask of thee; deny me them not before I die: 8 Remove far from me vanity and lies; give me neither poverty nor riches; feed me with the bread of my daily need: 9 lest I be full and deny thee, and say, Who is Jehovah? or lest I be poor and steal, and outrage the name of my God[*]

10 Speak not too much about a servant to his master, lest he curse thee, and thou be held guilty. 11 There is a generation that curseth their father, and doth not bless their mother; 12 there is a generation that are pure in their own eyes, yet are not washed from their filthiness; 13 there is a generation, --how lofty are their eyes, how their eyelids are lifted up! 14 --a generation whose teeth are swords, and their jaw-teeth knives, to devour the afflicted from off the earth, and the needy from among men.

15 The leech hath two daughters: Give, give. There are three things never satisfied; four which say not, It is enough: 16 --Sheol, and the barren womb; the earth which is not filled with water, and the fire which saith not, It is enough. 17 The eye that mocketh at a father, and despiseth to obey a mother, the ravens of the valley shall pick it out, and the young eagles shall eat it.

18 There are three things too wonderful for me, and four that I know not: 19 The way of an eagle in the heavens, the way of a serpent upon a rock, the way of a ship in the midst of the sea, and the way of a man with a maid. 20 Such is the way of an adulterous woman: she eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and saith, I have done no wickedness. 21 Under three things the earth is disquieted, and under four it cannot bear up: 22 Under a servant when he reigneth, and a churl when he is filled with meat; 23 under an odious woman when she is married, and a handmaid when she is heir to her mistress.

24 There are four things little upon the earth, and they are exceeding wise: 25 The ants, a people not strong, yet they provide their food in the summer; 26 the rock-badgers are but a feeble folk, yet they make their house in the cliff; 27 the locusts have no king, yet they go forth all of them by bands; 28 thou takest hold of the lizard with the hands, yet is she in kings' palaces.

29 There are three things which have a stately step, and four are comely in going: 30 The lion, mighty among beasts, which turneth not away for any; 31 a horse girt in the loins; or the he-goat; and a king, against whom none can rise up. 32 If thou hast done foolishly in lifting up thyself, or if thou hast thought evil, lay the hand upon thy mouth. 33 For the pressing of milk bringeth forth butter, and the pressing of the nose bringeth forth blood; and the pressing of anger bringeth forth strife.

Hebrew: Eloah

Hebrew: Elohim

Ecclesiastes 1

1 The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem. 2 Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher, vanity of vanities! all is vanity. 3 What profit hath man of all his labour wherewith he laboureth under the sun?

4 One generation passeth away, and another generation cometh, but the earth standeth for ever. 5 The sun also riseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to its place where it ariseth. 6 The wind goeth towards the south, and turneth about towards the north: it turneth about continually, and the wind returneth again to its circuits. 7 All the rivers run into the sea, yet the sea is not full: unto the place whither the rivers go, thither they go again. 8 All things are full of toil; none can express it. The eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.

9 That which hath been is that which shall be; and that which hath been done is that which will be done: and there is nothing new under the sun. 10 Is there a thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new? It hath been already in the ages which were before us. 11 There is no remembrance of former things; neither shall there be remembrance of things that are to come with those who shall live afterwards.

12 I, the Preacher, was king over Israel in Jerusalem. 13 And I applied my heart to seek and search out by wisdom concerning all that is done under the heavens: this grievous occupation hath God[*] given to the children of men to weary themselves therewith. 14 I have seen all the works that are done under the sun, and behold, all is vanity and pursuit of the wind. 15 That which is crooked cannot be made straight; and that which is wanting cannot be numbered. 16 I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I have become great and have acquired wisdom more than all they that have been before me over Jerusalem; and my heart hath seen much of wisdom and knowledge. 17 And I applied my heart to the knowledge of wisdom, and to the knowledge of madness and folly: I perceived that this also is a striving after the wind. 18 For in much wisdom is much vexation, and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow.

Hebrew: Elohim

Ecclesiastes 4

1 And I returned and saw all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and behold, the tears of the oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors was power, and they had no comforter. 2 Then I praised the dead who are already dead more than the living who are yet alive; 3 and more fortunate than both is he who hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.

4 And I saw all labour, and all success of work, that it is man's jealousy of his neighbour. This also is vanity and pursuit of the wind. 5 The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh. 6 Better is a handful with quietness, than both hands full with labour and pursuit of the wind.

7 And I returned and saw vanity under the sun. 8 There is one alone and without a second; also he hath neither son nor brother: yet is there no end of all his labour, neither is his eye satisfied with riches, and he saith not, For whom then am I labouring, and depriving my soul of good? This also is vanity and a grievous occupation. 9 Two are better than one; because they have a good reward for their labour. 10 For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow; but woe to him that is alone when he falleth, and who hath not another to lift him up! 11 Again, if two lie together, then they have warmth; but how can one alone be warm? 12 And if a man overpower the one, the two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.

13 Better is a poor but wise youth than an old and foolish king, who knoweth no more how to be admonished. 14 For out of the prison-house he came forth to reign, although he was born poor in his kingdom. 15 I saw all the living that walk under the sun, with the child, the second, that should stand up in his stead. 16 There is no end of all the people, of all that stood before them; those however that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and a striving after the wind.

Ecclesiastes 10

1 Dead flies cause the ointment of the apothecary to stink and ferment; so a little folly is weightier than wisdom and honour. 2 The heart of a wise man is at his right hand; but a fool's heart at his left. 3 Yea also, when he that is a fool walketh by the way, his sense faileth him, and he saith to every one that he is a fool.

4 If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for quietness pacifieth great offences. 5 There is an evil that I have seen under the sun, as an error that proceedeth from the ruler: 6 folly is set in great dignities, but the rich sit in a low place. 7 I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking as servants upon the earth. 8 He that diggeth a pit falleth into it; and whoso breaketh down a hedge, a serpent biteth him. 9 Whoso removeth stones is hurt therewith; he that cleaveth wood is endangered thereby. 10 If the iron be blunt, and one do not whet the edge, then must he apply more strength; but wisdom is profitable to give success. 11 If the serpent bite before enchantment, then the charmer hath no advantage.

12 The words of a wise man's mouth are gracious; but the lips of a fool swallow up himself. 13 The beginning of the words of his mouth is folly; and the end of his talk is mischievous madness. 14 And the fool multiplieth words: yet man knoweth not what shall be; and what shall be after him, who will tell him? 15 The labour of fools wearieth them, because they know not how to go to the city.

16 Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy princes eat in the morning! 17 Happy art thou, O land, when thy king is a son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness! 18 By much sloth fulness the framework falleth in; and through idleness of the hands the house drippeth. 19 A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh life merry; but money answereth everything. 20 Curse not the king, no, not in thy thought; and curse not the rich in thy bedchamber: for the bird of the air will carry the voice, and that which hath wings will tell the matter.

Song of Solomon 1

1 The song of songs, which is Solomon's.

2 Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth; For thy love is better than wine. 3 Thine ointments savour sweetly; Thy name is an ointment poured forth: Therefore do the virgins love thee. 4 Draw me, we will run after thee! --The king hath brought me into his chambers--We will be glad and rejoice in thee, We will remember thy love more than wine. They love thee uprightly. 5 I am black, but comely, daughters of Jerusalem, As the tents of Kedar, As the curtains of Solomon. 6 Look not upon me, because I am black; Because the sun hath looked upon me. My mother's children were angry with me: They made me keeper of the vineyards; Mine own vineyard have I not kept.

7 Tell me, thou whom my soul loveth, Where thou feedest thy flock, Where thou makest it to rest at noon; For why should I be as one veiled Beside the flocks of thy companions? 8 If thou know not, thou fairest among women, Go thy way forth by the footsteps of the flock, And feed thy kids beside the shepherds' booths. 9 I compare thee, my love, To a steed in Pharaoh's chariots. 10 Thy cheeks are comely with bead-rows, Thy neck with ornamental chains. 11 We will make thee bead-rows of gold With studs of silver.

12 While the king is at his table, My spikenard sendeth forth its fragrance. 13 A bundle of myrrh is my beloved unto me; He shall pass the night between my breasts. 14 My beloved is unto me a cluster of henna-flowers In the vineyards of Engedi. 15 Behold, thou art fair, my love; Behold, thou art fair: thine eyes are doves. 16 Behold, thou art fair, my beloved, yea, pleasant; Also our bed is green. 17 The beams of our houses are cedars, Our rafters are cypresses.

Song of Solomon 2

1 I am a narcissus of Sharon, A lily of the valleys. 2 As the lily among thorns, So is my love among the daughters.

3 As the apple-tree among the trees of the wood, So is my beloved among the sons: In his shadow have I rapture and sit down; And his fruit is sweet to my taste. 4 He hath brought me to the house of wine, And his banner over me is love. 5 Sustain ye me with raisin-cakes, Refresh me with apples; For I am sick of love. 6 His left hand is under my head, And his right hand doth embrace me. 7 I charge you, daughters of Jerusalem, By the gazelles, or by the hinds of the field, That ye stir not up, nor awake my love, till he please.

8 The voice of my beloved! Behold, he cometh Leaping upon the mountains, Skipping upon the hills. 9 My beloved is like a gazelle or a young hart. Behold, he standeth behind our wall, He looketh in through the windows, Glancing through the lattice. 10 My beloved spake and said unto me, Rise up, my love, my fair one, and come away. 11 For behold, the winter is past, The rain is over, it is gone: 12 The flowers appear on the earth; The time of singing is come, And the voice of the turtle-dove is heard in our land; 13 The fig-tree melloweth her winter figs, And the vines in bloom give forth their fragrance. Arise, my love, my fair one, and come away!

14 My dove, in the clefts of the rock, In the covert of the precipice, Let me see thy countenance, let me hear thy voice; For sweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely. 15 Take us the foxes, The little foxes, that spoil the vineyards; For our vineyards are in bloom. 16 My beloved is mine, and I am his; He feedeth his flock among the lilies, 17 Until the day dawn, and the shadows flee away. Turn, my beloved: be thou like a gazelle or a young hart, Upon the mountains of Bether.

Song of Solomon 3

1 On my bed, in the nights, I sought him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not. 2 I will rise now, and go about the city; In the streets and in the broadways Will I seek him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not. 3 The watchmen that go about the city found me: --Have ye seen him whom my soul loveth? 4 --Scarcely had I passed from them, When I found him whom my soul loveth: I held him, and would not let him go, Until I had brought him into my mother's house, And into the chamber of her that conceived me. 5 I charge you, daughters of Jerusalem, By the gazelles, or by the hinds of the field, That ye stir not up, nor awake my love, till he please.

6 Who is this, she that cometh up from the wilderness Like pillars of smoke, Perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, With all powders of the merchant? ...

7 Behold his couch, Solomon's own: Threescore mighty men are about it, Of the mighty of Israel. 8 They all hold the sword, Experts in war; Each hath his sword upon his thigh Because of alarm in the nights. 9 King Solomon made himself a palanquin Of the wood of Lebanon. 10 Its pillars he made of silver, Its support of gold, Its seat of purple; The midst thereof was paved with love By the daughters of Jerusalem. 11 Go forth, daughters of Zion, And behold king Solomon With the crown wherewith his mother crowned him In the day of his espousals, And in the day of the gladness of his heart.

Song of Solomon 4

1 Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair; Thine eyes are doves behind thy veil; Thy hair is as a flock of goats, On the slopes of mount Gilead. 2 Thy teeth are like a flock of shorn sheep, Which go up from the washing; Which have all borne twins, And none is barren among them. 3 Thy lips are like a thread of scarlet, And thy speech is comely; As a piece of a pomegranate are thy temples Behind thy veil. 4 Thy neck is like the tower of David, Built for an armoury: A thousand bucklers hang thereon, All shields of mighty men. 5 Thy two breasts are like two fawns, twins of a gazelle, Which feed among the lilies. 6 Until the day dawn, and the shadows flee away, I will get me to the mountain of myrrh, And to the hill of frankincense. 7 Thou art all fair, my love; And there is no spot in thee.

8 Come with me, from Lebanon, my spouse, With me from Lebanon, --Come, look from the top of Amanah, From the top of Senir and Hermon, From the lions' dens, From the mountains of the leopards. 9 Thou hast ravished my heart, my sister, my spouse; Thou hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes, With one chain of thy neck. 10 How fair is thy love, my sister, my spouse! How much better is thy love than wine! And the fragrance of thine ointments than all spices! 11 Thy lips, my spouse, drop as the honeycomb; Honey and milk are under thy tongue; And the smell of thy garments is like the smell of Lebanon. 12 A garden enclosed is my sister, my spouse; A spring shut up, a fountain sealed. 13 Thy shoots are a paradise of pomegranates, with precious fruits; Henna with spikenard plants; 14 Spikenard and saffron; Calamus and cinnamon, with all trees of frankincense; Myrrh and aloes, with all the chief spices:

15 A fountain in the gardens, A well of living waters, Which stream from Lebanon. 16 Awake, north wind, and come, thou south; Blow upon my garden, that the spices thereof may flow forth. Let my beloved come into his garden, And eat its precious fruits.

Song of Solomon 5

1 I am come into my garden, my sister, my spouse; I have gathered my myrrh with my spice; I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey; I have drunk my wine with my milk. Eat, O friends; drink, yea, drink abundantly, beloved ones!

2 I slept, but my heart was awake. The voice of my beloved! he knocketh: Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, mine undefiled; For my head is filled with dew, My locks with the drops of the night. 3 --I have put off my tunic, how should I put it on? I have washed my feet, how should I pollute them? -- 4 My beloved put in his hand by the hole of the door; And my bowels yearned for him. 5 I rose up to open to my beloved; And my hands dropped with myrrh, And my fingers with liquid myrrh, Upon the handles of the lock. 6 I opened to my beloved; But my beloved had withdrawn himself; he was gone: My soul went forth when he spoke. I sought him, but I found him not; I called him, but he gave me no answer. 7 The watchmen that went about the city found me; They smote me, they wounded me; The keepers of the walls took away my veil from me. 8 I charge you, daughters of Jerusalem, If ye find my beloved, ...What will ye tell him? --That I am sick of love.

9 What is thy beloved more than another beloved, Thou fairest among women? What is thy beloved more than another beloved, That thou dost so charge us? 10 My beloved is white and ruddy, The chiefest among ten thousand. 11 His head is as the finest gold; His locks are flowing, black as the raven; 12 His eyes are like doves by the water-brooks, Washed with milk, fitly set; 13 His cheeks are as a bed of spices, raised beds of sweet plants; His lips lilies, dropping liquid myrrh. 14 His hands gold rings, set with the chrysolite; His belly is bright ivory, overlaid with sapphires; 15 His legs, pillars of marble, set upon bases of fine gold: His bearing as Lebanon, excellent as the cedars; 16 His mouth is most sweet: Yea, he is altogether lovely. This is my beloved, yea, this is my friend, O daughters of Jerusalem.

Song of Solomon 6

1 Whither is thy beloved gone, Thou fairest among women? Whither is thy beloved turned aside? And we will seek him with thee. 2 My beloved is gone down into his garden, to the beds of spices, To feed in the gardens and to gather lilies. 3 I am my beloved's, and my beloved is mine: He feedeth his flock among the lilies.

4 Thou art fair, my love, as Tirzah, Comely as Jerusalem, Terrible as troops with banners: 5 Turn away thine eyes from me, For they overcome me. Thy hair is as a flock of goats On the slopes of Gilead. 6 Thy teeth are like a flock of sheep Which go up from the washing; Which have all borne twins, And none is barren among them. 7 As a piece of a pomegranate are thy temples Behind thy veil. 8 There are threescore queens, and fourscore concubines, And virgins without number: 9 My dove, mine undefiled, is but one; She is the only one of her mother, She is the choice one of her that bore her. The daughters saw her, and they called her blessed; The queens and the concubines, and they praised her. 10 Who is she that looketh forth as the dawn, Fair as the moon, clear as the sun, Terrible as troops with banners?

11 I went down into the garden of nuts, To see the verdure of the valley, To see whether the vine budded, Whether the pomegranates blossomed. 12 Before I was aware, My soul set me upon the chariots of my willing people. 13 Return, return, O Shulamite; Return, return, that we may look upon thee. --What would ye look upon in the Shulamite? --As it were the dance of two camps.

Song of Solomon 8

1 Oh that thou wert as my brother, That sucked the breasts of my mother! Should I find thee without, I would kiss thee; And they would not despise me. 2 I would lead thee, bring thee into my mother's house; Thou wouldest instruct me: I would cause thee to drink of spiced wine, Of the juice of my pomegranate. 3 His left hand would be under my head, And his right hand embrace me. 4 I charge you, daughters of Jerusalem, ...Why should ye stir up, why awake my love, till he please?

5 Who is this that cometh up from the wilderness, Leaning upon her beloved? I awoke thee under the apple-tree: There thy mother brought thee forth; There she brought thee forth that bore thee. 6 Set me as a seal upon thy heart, As a seal upon thine arm: For love is strong as death; Jealousy is cruel as Sheol: The flashes thereof are flashes of fire, Flames of Jah. 7 Many waters cannot quench love, Neither do the floods drown it: Even if a man gave all the substance of his house for love, It would utterly be contemned.

8 We have a little sister, And she hath no breasts: What shall we do for our sister In the day when she shall be spoken for? -- 9 If she be a wall, We will build upon her a turret of silver; And if she be a door, We will enclose her with boards of cedar. 10 I am a wall, and my breasts like towers; Then was I in his eyes as one that findeth peace. 11 Solomon had a vineyard at Baal-hamon: He let out the vineyard unto keepers; Every one for the fruit thereof was to bring a thousand silver-pieces. 12 My vineyard, which is mine, is before me: The thousand silver-pieces be to thee, Solomon; And to the keepers of its fruit, two hundred.

13 Thou that dwellest in the gardens, The companions hearken to thy voice: Let me hear it. 14 Haste, my beloved, And be thou like a gazelle or a young hart Upon the mountains of spices.

Isaiah 1

1 The vision of Isaiah the son of Amos, which he saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, kings of Judah.

2 Hear, ye heavens, and give ear, thou earth! for Jehovah hath spoken: I have nourished and brought up children; and they have rebelled against me. 3 The ox knoweth his owner, and the ass his master's crib; Israel doth not know, my people hath no intelligence. 4 Ah sinful nation, a people laden with iniquity, a seed of evildoers, children that corrupt themselves! They have forsaken Jehovah; they have despised the Holy One of Israel; they are turned away backward. 5 Why should ye be smitten any more? ye will revolt more and more: the whole head is sick, and the whole heart faint. 6 From the sole of the foot even unto the head there is no soundness in him; wounds, and weals, and open sores: they have not been dressed, nor bound up, nor mollified with oil. 7 Your country is desolate; your cities are burned with fire; your land, strangers eat it up in your presence, and it is desolate, as overthrown by strangers. 8 And the daughter of Zion is left, as a booth in a vineyard, as a night-lodge in a cucumber-garden, as a besieged city. 9 Unless Jehovah of hosts had left us a very small residue, we should have been as Sodom, we should have been like unto Gomorrah.

10 Hear the word of Jehovah, rulers of Sodom; give ear unto the law of our God[*] people of Gomorrah! 11 To what purpose is the multitude of your sacrifices unto me? saith Jehovah. I am sated with burnt-offerings of rams, and the fat of fed beasts; and in the blood of bullocks, and of lambs, and of he-goats I take no pleasure. 12 When ye come to appear before me, who hath required this from your hand--to tread my courts? 13 Bring no more vain oblations! Incense is an abomination unto me, --new moon and sabbath, the calling of convocations--wickedness and the solemn meeting I cannot bear. 14 Your new moons and your set feasts my soul hateth: they are a burden to me; I am wearied of bearing them. 15 And when ye spread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you; yea, when ye make many prayers, I will not hear: your hands are full of blood.

16 Wash you, make you clean; put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes; --cease to do evil, 17 learn to do well: seek judgment, gladden the oppressed, do justice to the fatherless, plead for the widow. 18 Come now, let us reason together, saith Jehovah: though your sins be as scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they be red like crimson, they shall be as wool. 19 If ye be willing and hearken, ye shall eat the good of the land; 20 but if ye refuse and rebel, ye shall be devoured with the sword: for the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken.

21 How is the faithful city become a harlot! It was full of judgment; righteousness used to lodge in it, but now murderers. 22 Thy silver is become dross, thy wine is mixed with water: 23 thy princes are rebellious, and companions of thieves; every one loveth presents, and hunteth after rewards; they judge not the fatherless, and the cause of the widow cometh not unto them. 24 Therefore saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, the Mighty One of Israel: Ah! I will ease me of mine adversaries, and avenge me of mine enemies. 25 And I will turn my hand upon thee, and will thoroughly purge away thy dross, and take away all thine alloy; 26 and I will restore thy judges as at the first, and thy counsellors as at the beginning. Afterwards thou shalt be called, Town of righteousness, Faithful city. 27 Zion shall be redeemed with judgment, and they that return of her with righteousness. 28 But the ruin of the transgressors and of the sinners shall be together; and they that forsake Jehovah shall be consumed. 29 For they shall be ashamed of the terebinths that ye have desired, and ye shall blush for the gardens that ye have chosen. 30 For ye shall be as a terebinth whose leaf fadeth, and as a garden that hath no water. 31 And the strong shall be for tow, and his work a spark; and they shall both burn together, and there shall be none to quench them.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 2

1 The word that Isaiah the son of Amoz saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem. 2 And it shall come to pass in the end of days, that the mountain of Jehovah's house shall be established on the top of the mountains, and shall be lifted up above the hills; and all the nations shall flow unto it. 3 And many peoples shall go and say, Come, and let us go up to the mountain of Jehovah, to the house of the God[*] of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths. For out of Zion shall go forth the law, and Jehovah's word from Jerusalem. 4 And he shall judge among the nations, and shall reprove many peoples; and they shall forge their swords into ploughshares, and their spears into pruning-knives: nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more. 5 House of Jacob, come ye, and let us walk in the light of Jehovah.

6 For thou hast cast off thy people, the house of Jacob, because they are filled with what comes from the east, and use auguries like the Philistines, and ally themselves with the children of foreigners. 7 And their land is full of silver and gold, and there is no end of their treasures: their land also is full of horses, and there is no end of their chariots. 8 And their land is full of idols; they bow themselves down to the work of their own hands, to that which their fingers have made. 9 And the mean man shall be bowed down, and the great man shall be brought low: and do not thou forgive them!

10 Enter into the rock, and hide thee in the dust, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty. 11 The lofty eyes of man shall be brought low, and the haughtiness of men shall be bowed down, and Jehovah alone shall be exalted in that day. 12 For there shall be a day of Jehovah of hosts upon everything proud and lofty, and upon everything lifted up, and it shall be brought low; 13 and upon all the cedars of Lebanon, high and lifted up, and upon all the oaks of Bashan; 14 and upon all the lofty mountains, and upon all the hills that are lifted up; 15 and upon every high tower, and upon every fenced wall; 16 and upon all the ships of Tarshish, and upon all pleasant works of art. 17 And the loftiness of man shall be bowed down, and the haughtiness of men shall be brought low; and Jehovah alone shall be exalted in that day: 18 and the idols shall utterly pass away. 19 And they shall go into the caves of the rocks, and into the holes of the earth, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty, when he shall arise to terrify the earth. 20 In that day men shall cast away their idols of silver and their idols of gold, which they made each for himself to worship, to the moles and to the bats; 21 to go into the clefts of the rocks, and into the fissures of the cliffs, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty, when he shall arise to terrify the earth. 22 Cease ye from man, whose breath is in his nostrils; for what account is to be made of him?

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 3

1 For behold, the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, will take away from Jerusalem and from Judah stay and staff, the whole stay of bread, and the whole stay of water, 2 the mighty man and the man of war, the judge and the prophet, and the diviner and the elder, 3 the captain of fifty, and the honourable man, and the counsellor, and the clever among artificers, and the one versed in enchantments. 4 And I will appoint youths as their princes, and children shall rule over them. 5 And the people shall be oppressed one by the other, and each by his neighbour; the child will be insolent against the elder, and the base against the honourable. 6 When a man shall take hold of his brother, in his father's house, and shall say: Thou hast clothing; be our chief, and let this ruin be under thy hand; 7 he will lift up his hand in that day, saying, I cannot be a healer, and in my house there is neither bread nor clothing; ye shall not make me a chief of the people. 8 For Jerusalem stumbleth and Judah falleth, because their tongue and their doings are against Jehovah, to provoke the eyes of his glory.

9 The look of their face doth witness against them, and they declare their sin as Sodom: they hide it not. Woe unto their soul! for they have brought evil upon themselves. 10 Say ye of the righteous that it shall be well with him, for they shall eat the fruit of their doings. 11 Woe unto the wicked! it shall be ill with him, because the desert of his hands shall be rendered unto him. 12 As for my people, children are their oppressors, and women rule over them. My people! they that guide thee mislead thee, and destroy the way of thy paths. 13 Jehovah setteth himself to plead, and standeth to judge the peoples. 14 Jehovah will enter into judgment with the elders of his people and their princes, saying: It is ye that have eaten up the vineyard: the spoil of the poor is in your houses. 15 What mean ye that ye crush my people, and grind the faces of the afflicted? saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts.

16 And Jehovah said, Because the daughters of Zion are haughty, and walk with stretched-out neck and wanton eyes, and go along mincing, and making a tinkling with their feet; 17 therefore the Lord will make bald the crown of the head of the daughters of Zion, and Jehovah will lay bare their secret parts. 18 In that day the Lord will take away the ornament of anklets, and the little suns and crescents, 19 the pearl-drops, and the bracelets, and the veils, 20 the head-dresses, and the stepping chains, and the girdles, and the scent-boxes, and the amulets; 21 the finger-rings, and the nose-rings; 22 the festival-robes, and the tunics, and the mantles, and the wallets; 23 the mirrors, and the fine linen bodices, and the turbans, and the flowing veils. 24 And it shall come to pass, instead of perfume there shall be rottenness; and instead of a girdle, a rope; and instead of well-set hair, baldness; and instead of a robe of display, a girding of sackcloth; brand instead of beauty. 25 Thy men shall fall by the sword, and thy mighty in the fight; 26 and her gates shall lament and mourn; and, stripped, she shall sit upon the ground.

Isaiah 6

1 In the year of the death of king Uzziah, I saw the Lord sitting upon a throne, high and lifted up; and his train filled the temple. 2 Seraphim were standing above him: each had six wings; with twain he covered his face, and with twain he covered his feet, and with twain he flew. 3 And one called to the other and said, Holy, holy, holy is Jehovah of hosts; the whole earth is full of his glory! 4 And the foundations of the thresholds shook at the voice of him that cried, and the house was filled with smoke.

5 And I said, Woe unto me! for I am undone; for I am a man of unclean lips, and I dwell in the midst of a people of unclean lips: for mine eyes have seen the King, Jehovah of hosts. 6 And one of the seraphim flew unto me, and he had in his hand a glowing coal, which he had taken with the tongs from off the altar; 7 and he made it touch my mouth, and said, Behold, this hath touched thy lips; and thine iniquity is taken away, and thy sin expiated. 8 And I heard the voice of the Lord saying, Whom shall I send, and who will go for us? And I said, Here am I; send me.

9 And he said, Go; and thou shalt say unto this people, Hearing ye shall hear and shall not understand, and seeing ye shall see and shall not perceive. 10 Make the heart of this people fat, and make their ears heavy, and blind their eyes; lest they see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and be converted, and healed. 11 And I said, Lord, how long? And he said, Until the cities be wasted, without inhabitant, and the houses without man, and the land become an utter desolation, 12 and Jehovah have removed men far away, and the solitude be great in the midst of the land. 13 But a tenth part shall still be therein, and it shall return and be eaten; as the terebinth and as the oak whose trunk remaineth after the felling: the holy seed shall be the trunk thereof.

Isaiah 7

1 And it came to pass in the days of Ahaz, the son of Jotham, the son of Uzziah, king of Judah, that Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, came up to Jerusalem to make war against it, but they were not able to fight against it. 2 And it was told the house of David saying, Syria is allied with Ephraim. Then his heart and the heart of his people shook, as the trees of the forest are shaken with the wind. 3 And Jehovah said to Isaiah, Go out now to meet Ahaz, thou and thy son Shear-jashub, at the end of the aqueduct of the upper pool, on the highway of the fuller's field; 4 and thou shalt say unto him, Take heed and be quiet; fear not, and let not thy heart faint before these two ends of smoking firebrands, because of the fierce anger of Rezin and Syria, and of the son of Remaliah. 5 Inasmuch as Syria hath taken evil counsel against thee, Ephraim also and the son of Remaliah, saying, 6 Let us go up against Judah, and harass it, and make a breach therein for us, and set up a king therein--the son of Tabeal; 7 thus saith the Lord Jehovah: It shall not stand, nor come to pass; 8 for the head of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Rezin; and within sixty-five years shall Ephraim be broken, so as to be no more a people; 9 and the head of Ephraim is Samaria, and the head of Samaria is Remaliah's son. If ye believe not, surely ye shall not be established.

10 And Jehovah spoke again to Ahaz, saying, 11 Ask for thee a sign from Jehovah thy God[*] ask for it in the deep, or in the height above. 12 And Ahaz said, I will not ask, and will not tempt Jehovah. 13 And he said, Hear then, house of David: Is it a small matter for you to weary men, that ye weary also my God[*] 14 Therefore will the Lord himself give you a sign: Behold, the virgin shall conceive and shall bring forth a son, and call his name Immanuel. 15 Butter and honey shall he eat, that he may know to refuse the evil, and to choose the good. 16 For before the child knoweth to refuse the evil and to choose the good, the land whose two kings thou fearest shall be forsaken.

17 Jehovah will bring upon thee, and upon thy people, and upon thy father's house, days which have not come since the day when Ephraim turned away from Judah-- even the king of Assyria. 18 And it shall come to pass in that day, that Jehovah will hiss for the fly which is at the extremity of the streams of Egypt, and for the bee which is in the land of Assyria; 19 and they shall come and settle all of them in the desolate valleys, and in the holes of the rocks, and on all thorn-bushes, and on all the pastures. 20 In that day will the Lord, with a razor which is hired beyond the river, with the king of Assyria, shave the head and the hair of the feet, yea, the beard also will it take away. 21 And it shall come to pass in that day, that a man shall nourish a young cow and two sheep, 22 and it shall come to pass, from the abundance of milk they shall give, that he shall eat butter; for every one that remaineth in the midst of the land shall eat butter and honey. 23 And it shall come to pass in that day, that every place, where there were a thousand vines at a thousand silver pieces, shall become briars and thorns: 24 with arrows and with the bow shall they come thither, for the whole land shall become briars and thorns. 25 And all mountains that have been dug up with the hoe--thither will they not come, from fear of briars and thorns; and they shall be for the sending forth of oxen, and for the treading of small cattle.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 8

1 And Jehovah said to me, Take thee a great tablet, and write thereon with a man's style, concerning Maher-shalal-hash-baz. 2 And I took unto me to witness, sure witnesses, Urijah the priest, and Zechariah the son of Jeberechiah. 3 And I came near to the prophetess, and she conceived and bore a son; and Jehovah said unto me, Call his name, Maher-shalal-hash-baz. 4 For before the lad knoweth to cry, My father! and, My mother! the riches of Damascus and the spoil of Samaria shall be taken away before the king of Assyria. 5 And Jehovah spoke again to me, saying, 6 Forasmuch as this people refuseth the waters of Shiloah which flow softly, and rejoiceth in Rezin and in the son of Remaliah, 7 therefore behold, the Lord will bring up upon them the waters of the river, strong and many, the king of Assyria and all his glory; and he shall mount up over all his channels, and go over all his banks: 8 and he shall pass through Judah; he shall overflow it and go further, he shall reach even to the neck; and the stretching out of his wings shall fill the breadth of thy land, O Immanuel!

9 Rage, ye peoples, and be broken in pieces! And give ear, all ye distant parts of the earth: Gird yourselves, and be broken in pieces; gird yourselves, and be broken in pieces! 10 Settle a plan, and it shall come to nought; speak a word, and it shall not stand: for ·God[*] is with us. 11 For Jehovah spoke thus to me with a strong hand, and he instructed me not to walk in the way of this people, saying, 12 Ye shall not say, Conspiracy, of everything of which this people saith, Conspiracy; and fear ye not their fear, and be not in dread. 13 Jehovah of hosts, him shall ye sanctify; and let him be your fear, and let him be your dread. 14 And he will be for a sanctuary; and for a stone of stumbling, and for a rock of offence to both the houses of Israel, for a gin and for a snare to the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 15 And many among them shall stumble, and fall, and be broken, and snared, and taken.

16 Bind up the testimony, seal the law among my disciples. 17 And I will wait for Jehovah, who hideth his face from the house of Jacob; and I will look for him. 18 Behold, I and the children that Jehovah hath given me are for signs and for wonders in Israel, from Jehovah of hosts, who dwelleth in mount Zion. 19 And when they shall say unto you, Seek unto the necromancers and unto the soothsayers, who chirp and who mutter, say, Shall not a people seek unto their God[*] Will they go for the living unto the dead? 20 To the law and the testimony! If they speak not according to this word, for them there is no daybreak. 21 And they shall pass through it, hard pressed and hungry; and it shall come to pass when they are hungry, they will fret themselves, and curse their king and their God[*] and will gaze upward: 22 and they will look to the earth; and behold, trouble and darkness, gloom of anguish; and they shall be driven into thick darkness.

Hebrew: El

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 9

1 Nevertheless the darkness shall not be as when the distress was in the land, at the time he at first lightly, and afterwards heavily, visited the land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali, --the way of the sea, beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the nations: 2 the people that walked in darkness have seen a great light; they that dwelt in the land of the shadow of death, upon them light hath shone. 3 Thou hast multiplied the nation, hast increased its joy: they joy before thee like to the joy in harvest; as men rejoice when they divide the spoil. 4 For thou hast broken the yoke of his burden and the staff of his shoulder, the rod of his oppressor, as in the day of Midian. 5 For every boot of him that is shod for the tumult, and the garment rolled in blood, shall be for burning, fuel for fire. 6 For unto us a child is born, unto us a son is given; and the government shall be upon his shoulder; and his name is called Wonderful, Counsellor, Mighty ·God[*] Father of Eternity, Prince of Peace. 7 Of the increase of his government and of peace there shall be no end, upon the throne of David and over his kingdom, to establish it, and to uphold it with judgment and with righteousness, from henceforth even for ever. The zeal of Jehovah of hosts will perform this.

8 The Lord sent a word unto Jacob, and it lighteth upon Israel. 9 And all the people shall know it, Ephraim and the inhabitant of Samaria, that say in pride and stoutness of heart, 10 The bricks are fallen down, but we will build with hewn stones; the sycamore trees are cut down, but we will replace them with cedars. 11 And Jehovah will set up the adversaries of Rezin against him, and arm his enemies, 12 the Syrians on the east, and the Philistines on the west; and they shall devour Israel with open mouth. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still. 13 But the people turneth not unto him that smiteth them, and they do not seek Jehovah of hosts. 14 And Jehovah will cut off from Israel head and tail, palm-branch and rush, in one day: 15 the ancient and honourable, he is the head; and the prophet that teacheth lies, he is the tail. 16 For the guides of this people mislead them; and they that are guided by them are swallowed up. 17 Therefore the Lord will not rejoice in their young men, neither will he have mercy on their fatherless and on their widows; for every one is a hypocrite and an evildoer, and every mouth speaketh folly. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still. 18 For wickedness burneth as a fire: it devoureth briars and thorns, and kindleth in the thickets of the forest, and they go rolling up like a pillar of smoke. 19 Through the wrath of Jehovah of hosts is the land burned up, and the people is as fuel for fire: a man spareth not his brother; 20 and he snatcheth on the right hand, and is hungry, and eateth on the left hand; and they are not satisfied. They eat every man the flesh of his own arm: 21 Manasseh, Ephraim, and Ephraim, Manasseh; and they together are against Judah. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still.

Hebrew: El

Isaiah 10

1 Woe unto them that decree iniquitous decrees, and to the writers that prescribe oppression, 2 to turn away the poor from judgment, and to take away the right from the afflicted of my people; that widows may be their prey, and that they may rob the fatherless! 3 And what will ye do in the day of visitation, and in the sudden destruction which shall come from far? To whom will ye flee for help, and where will ye leave your glory? 4 They can but crouch under the prisoners, and they shall fall under the slain. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still.

5 Ah! the Assyrian! the rod of mine anger! and the staff in their hand is mine indignation. 6 I will send him against a hypocritical nation, and against the people of my wrath will I give him a charge; to take the spoil, and to seize the prey, and to tread them down like the mire of the streets. 7 But he meaneth not so, neither doth his heart think so; for it is in his heart to extirpate and cut off nations not a few. 8 For he saith, Are not my princes all kings? 9 Is not Calno as Karkemish? Is not Hamath as Arpad? Is not Samaria as Damascus? 10 As my hand hath found the kingdoms of the idols, --and their graven images exceeded those of Jerusalem and Samaria, 11 --shall I not, as I have done unto Samaria and her idols, so do to Jerusalem and her images? 12 And it shall come to pass, when the Lord hath performed his whole work upon mount Zion and upon Jerusalem, I will punish the fruit of the stoutness of heart of the king of Assyria, and the glory of his high looks. 13 For he saith, By the strength of my hand I have done it, and by my wisdom, for I am intelligent; and I have removed the bounds of the peoples, and have robbed their treasures, and, like a valiant man, I have brought down them that sit on thrones; 14 and my hand hath found as a nest the riches of the peoples, and as one gathereth forsaken eggs, have I gathered all the earth; and there was none that moved the wing, or opened the mouth, or chirped. 15 --Shall the axe boast itself against him that heweth therewith? shall the saw magnify itself against him that wieldeth it? As if the rod should wield them that lift it up; as if the staff should lift up him who is not wood! 16 Therefore shall the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, send among his fat ones leanness, and under his glory he shall kindle a burning, like the burning of a fire: 17 and the light of Israel shall be for a fire, and his Holy One for a flame; and it shall burn and devour his thorns and his briars in one day, 18 and it shall consume the glory of his forest, and of his fruitful field, both soul and body; and they shall be as when a sick man fainteth. 19 And the remainder of the trees of his forest shall be few: yea, a child might write them.

20 And it shall come to pass in that day, that the remnant of Israel and such as are escaped of the house of Jacob shall no more again rely upon him that smote them; but they shall rely upon Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel, in truth. 21 The remnant shall return, the remnant of Jacob, unto the mighty ·God[*] 22 For though thy people Israel be as the sand of the sea, only a remnant of them shall return: the consumption determined shall overflow in righteousness. 23 For a consumption, and one determined, will the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, accomplish in the midst of all the land.

24 Therefore thus saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts: O my people that dwellest in Zion, be not afraid of the Assyrian; he shall smite thee with a rod, and shall lift up his staff against thee, after the manner of Egypt: 25 for yet a very little while, and the indignation shall be accomplished, and mine anger, in their destruction. 26 And Jehovah of hosts will stir up a scourge against him, according to the slaughter of Midian at the rock of Oreb; and his rod shall be upon the sea, and he will lift it up after the manner of Egypt. 27 And it shall come to pass in that day, that his burden shall be taken away from off thy shoulder, and his yoke from off thy neck; and the yoke shall be destroyed because of the anointing. ... 28 He is come to Aiath, he hath passed through Migron; at Michmash he layeth up his baggage. 29 They are gone through the pass; they make their lodging at Geba: Ramah trembleth, Gibeah of Saul is fled. 30 Lift up thy voice, daughter of Gallim! Hearken, O Laish! --Poor Anathoth! 31 Madmenah is fugitive; the inhabitants of Gebim take to flight. 32 Still a day of halting at Nob; he shaketh his hand against the mount of the daughter of Zion, the hill of Jerusalem. ... 33 Behold the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, shall lop the boughs with violence; and the high ones of stature shall be hewn down, and the haughty shall be brought low; 34 and he shall make clearings in the thickets of the forest with iron; and Lebanon shall fall by a mighty one.

Hebrew: El

Isaiah 11

1 And there shall come forth a shoot out of the stock of Jesse, and a branch out of his roots shall be fruitful; 2 and the Spirit of Jehovah shall rest upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of Jehovah. 3 And his delight will be in the fear of Jehovah; and he shall not judge after the sight of his eyes, neither reprove after the hearing of his ears; 4 but with righteousness shall he judge the poor, and reprove with equity the meek of the earth: and he shall smite the earth with the rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips shall he slay the wicked. 5 And righteousness shall be the girdle of his reins, and faithfulness the girdle of his loins. 6 The wolf also shall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid, and the calf and the young lion and the fatted beast together, and a little child shall lead them. 7 And the cow and the she-bear shall feed; their young ones shall lie down together; and the lion shall eat straw like the ox. 8 And the sucking child shall play on the hole of the adder, and the weaned child shall put forth its hand to the viper's den. 9 They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain; for the earth shall be full of the knowledge of Jehovah, as the waters cover the sea.

10 And in that day there shall be a root of Jesse, standing as a banner of the peoples: the nations shall seek it; and his resting-place shall be glory. 11 And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord shall set his hand again the second time to acquire the remnant of his people which shall be left, from Assyria, and from Egypt, and from Pathros, and from Cush, and from Elam, and from Shinar, and from Hamath, and from the islands of the sea. 12 And he shall lift up a banner to the nations, and shall assemble the outcasts of Israel, and gather together the dispersed of Judah from the four corners of the earth. 13 And the envy of Ephraim shall depart, and the troublers of Judah shall be cut off; Ephraim will not envy Judah, and Judah will not trouble Ephraim: 14 but they shall fly upon the shoulder of the Philistines towards the west; together shall they spoil the sons of the east; they shall lay their hand upon Edom and Moab, and the children of Ammon shall obey them. 15 And Jehovah will utterly destroy the tongue of the Egyptian sea; and with his mighty wind will he shake his hand over the river, and will smite it into seven streams, and make men go over dryshod. 16 And there shall be a highway for the remnant of his people which will be left, from Assyria; like as it was to Israel in the day when he went up out of the land of Egypt.

Isaiah 13

1 The burden of Babylon, which Isaiah the son of Amoz saw. 2 Lift up a banner upon a bare mountain, raise the voice unto them, shake the hand, that they may enter the gates of the nobles. 3 I have commanded my hallowed ones, I have also called my mighty men for mine anger, them that rejoice in my highness. 4 The noise of a multitude on the mountains, as of a great people; a tumultuous noise of the kingdoms of nations assembled together: Jehovah of hosts mustereth the host of the battle. 5 They come from a far country, from the end of the heavens--Jehovah, and the weapons of his indignation--to destroy the whole land.

6 Howl, for the day of Jehovah is at hand; it cometh as destruction from the Almighty. 7 Therefore shall all hands be feeble, and every heart of man shall melt, 8 and they shall be terrified: pangs and sorrows shall take hold of them, they shall writhe as a woman that travaileth; they shall be amazed one at another, their faces shall be as flames. 9 Behold, the day of Jehovah cometh, cruel both with wrath and fierce anger, to lay the earth desolate; and he will destroy the sinners thereof out of it. 10 For the stars of the heavens and the constellations thereof shall not give their light; the sun shall be darkened in his going forth, and the moon shall not cause her light to shine. 11 And I will punish the world for evil, and the wicked for their iniquity; and I will make the arrogance of the proud to cease, and will bring low the haughtiness of the violent. 12 I will make a man more precious than fine gold, even man than the gold of Ophir. 13 Therefore I will make the heavens to shake, and the earth shall be removed out of her place, at the wrath of Jehovah of hosts, and in the day of his fierce anger. 14 And it shall be as with a chased roe, and as with a flock that no man gathereth together; every one shall turn to his own people, and every one flee into his own land. 15 All that are found shall be thrust through; and every one that is in league with them shall fall by the sword. 16 And their infants shall be dashed in pieces before their eyes, their houses shall be rifled, and their women ravished. 17 Behold, I will stir up the Medes against them, who do not regard silver, and as for gold, they have no delight in it. 18 And their bows shall dash the young men to pieces, and they shall have no pity on the fruit of the womb: their eye shall not spare children.

19 And Babylon, the glory of kingdoms, the beauty of the Chaldeans' pride, shall be as when God[*] overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah. 20 It shall never be inhabited, neither shall it be dwelt in, even to generation and generation; nor shall Arabian pitch tent there, nor shepherds make fold there. 21 But beasts of the desert shall lie there, and their houses shall be full of owls; and ostriches shall dwell there, and wild goats shall dance there. 22 And jackals shall cry to one another in their palaces, and wild dogs in the pleasant castles. And her time is near to come, and her days shall not be prolonged.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 14

1 For Jehovah will have mercy on Jacob, and will yet choose Israel, and set them in rest in their own land; and the stranger shall be united to them, and they shall be joined to the house of Jacob. 2 And the peoples shall take them and bring them to their place; and the house of Israel shall possess them in the land of Jehovah for servants and handmaids; and they shall take them captive whose captives they were, and they shall rule over their oppressors. 3 And it shall come to pass in the day that Jehovah shall give thee rest from thy sorrow and from thy trouble and from the hard bondage wherein thou wast made to serve,

4 that thou shalt take up this proverb against the king of Babylon, and say, How hath the oppressor ceased, --the exactress of gold ceased! 5 Jehovah hath broken the staff of the wicked, the sceptre of the rulers. 6 He that smote the peoples in wrath with a relentless stroke, he that ruled the nations in anger, is persecuted unsparingly. 7 The whole earth is at rest, is quiet: they break forth into singing. 8 Even the cypresses rejoice at thee, the cedars of Lebanon, saying, Since thou art laid down, no feller is come up against us. 9 Sheol from beneath is moved for thee to meet thee at thy coming, stirring up the dead for thee, all the he-goats of the earth; making to rise from their thrones all the kings of the nations. 10 All of them shall answer and say unto thee, Art thou also become powerless as we; art thou become like unto us! 11 --Thy pomp is brought down to Sheol, the noise of thy lyres: the maggot is spread under thee, and worms cover thee. 12 How art thou fallen from heaven, Lucifer, son of the morning! Thou art cut down to the ground, that didst prostrate the nations! 13 And thou that didst say in thy heart, I will ascend into the heavens, I will exalt my throne above the stars of ·God[*] and I will sit upon the mount of assembly, in the recesses of the north; 14 I will ascend above the heights of the clouds, I will be like the Most High: 15 none the less art thou brought down to Sheol, to the recesses of the pit. 16 They that see thee shall narrowly look upon thee; they shall consider thee, saying, Is this the man that made the earth to tremble, that shook kingdoms; 17 that made the world as a wilderness, and overthrew the cities thereof; that dismissed not his prisoners homewards? 18 --All the kings of the nations, all of them, lie in glory, every one in his own house; 19 but thou art cast out of thy grave like an abominable branch, covered with the slain--those thrust through with the sword, that go down to the stones of the pit: like a carcase trodden under foot. 20 Thou shalt not be joined with them in burial; for thou hast destroyed thy land, hast slain thy people. Of the seed of evildoers no mention shall be made for ever. 21 Prepare ye slaughter for his children, because of the iniquity of their fathers; that they may not rise up and possess the earth, nor fill the face of the world with cities. 22 For I will rise up against them, saith Jehovah of hosts, and cut off from Babylon name and remnant, and scion and descendant, saith Jehovah. 23 And I will make it a possession for the bittern, and pools of water; and I will sweep it with the besom of destruction, saith Jehovah of hosts.

24 Jehovah of hosts hath sworn saying, Assuredly as I have thought, so shall it come to pass; and as I have purposed, it shall stand: 25 to break the Assyrian in my land; and upon my mountains will I tread him under foot; and his yoke shall depart from off them, and his burden depart from off their shoulders. 26 This is the counsel which is purposed concerning the whole earth; and this is the hand which is stretched out upon all the nations. 27 For Jehovah of hosts hath purposed, and who shall frustrate it? And his hand is stretched out, and who shall turn it back? 28 In the year of the death of king Ahaz was this burden: 29 Rejoice not thou, Philistia, all of thee, because the rod that smote thee is broken; for out of the serpent's root shall come forth a viper, and his fruit shall be a fiery flying serpent. 30 And the firstborn of the poor shall feed, and the needy shall lie down in safety; but I will kill thy root with famine, and thy remnant shall be slain. 31 Howl, O gate! cry, O city! thou, Philistia, art wholly dissolved; for there cometh from the north a smoke, and none remaineth apart in his gatherings of troops. 32 And what shall be answered to the messengers of the nation? That Jehovah hath founded Zion, and the afflicted of his people find refuge in it.

Hebrew: El

Isaiah 15

1 The burden of Moab: For in the night of being laid waste, Ar of Moab is destroyed; for in the night of being laid waste, Kir of Moab is destroyed! 2 He is gone up to Bajith, and to Dibon, to the high places, to weep; Moab howleth over Nebo, and over Medeba; on all their heads is baldness, every beard is cut off. 3 In their streets they are girded with sackcloth; on their roofs, and in their broadways, every one howleth, melted into tears. 4 And Heshbon crieth, and Elealeh: their voice is heard unto Jahaz. Therefore the armed men of Moab cry out: his soul trembleth in him. 5 My heart crieth out for Moab; their fugitives have fled unto Zoar, unto Eglath-Sheli-shijah: for by the ascent of Luhith, with weeping they go up by it; for in the way of Horonaim they raise up a cry of destruction.

6 For the waters of Nimrim shall be desolate; for the herbage is withered away, the grass hath failed, there is no green thing. 7 Therefore the abundance they have gotten, and that which they have laid up, do they carry away to the torrent of the willows. 8 For the cry goeth round about the borders of Moab; the howling thereof unto Eglaim, and the howling thereof unto Beer-elim. 9 For the waters of Dimon are full of blood, for I will lay yet more upon Dimon: a lion upon them that are escaped of Moab, and upon that which remaineth of the land.

Isaiah 16

1 Send the lamb of the ruler of the land from the rock to the wilderness, --unto the mount of the daughter of Zion. 2 And it shall be that as a wandering bird, as a scattered nest, so shall the daughters of Moab be at the fords of the Arnon. 3 Bring in counsel, execute justice; make thy shadow as the night in the midst of noonday; hide the outcasts, discover not the fugitive. 4 Let mine outcasts dwell with thee, Moab; be thou a covert to them from the face of the waster. For the extortioner is at an end, the wasting hath ceased, the oppressors are consumed out of the land. 5 And a throne shall be established in mercy: and in the tent of David there shall sit upon it, in truth, one judging and seeking justice and hastening righteousness.

6 We have heard of the arrogance of Moab, -- he is very proud, --of his pride, and his arrogance, and his wrath: his pratings are vain. 7 Therefore shall Moab howl for Moab; every one of them shall howl. For the foundations of Kirhareseth shall ye mourn, verily afflicted. 8 For the fields of Heshbon languish, the vine of Sibmah; the lords of the nations have broken down its choice plants: they reached unto Jaazer, they wandered through the wilderness; its shoots stretched out, they went beyond the sea. 9 Therefore I will weep with the weeping of Jaazer for the vine of Sibmah; with my tears will I water thee, Heshbon, and Elealeh, for a cry is fallen upon thy summer fruits and upon thy harvest. 10 And joy and gladness is taken away out of the fruitful field; and in the vineyards there is no singing, neither is there shouting: the treaders tread out no wine in the presses, I have made the cry of the winepress to cease. 11 Therefore my bowels sound like a harp for Moab, and mine inward parts for Kirheres. 12 And it shall come to pass, when Moab shall appear, shall weary himself on the high place, and enter into his sanctuary to pray, that he shall not prevail. 13 This is the word which Jehovah hath spoken from of old concerning Moab. 14 And now Jehovah speaketh saying, Within three years, as the years of a hired servant, and the glory of Moab shall be brought to nothing, with all that great multitude; and the remnant shall be small, few, of no account.

Isaiah 17

1 The burden of Damascus. Behold, Damascus is taken away from being a city, and it shall be a ruinous heap. 2 The cities of Aroer are forsaken: they shall be for flocks; and they shall lie down and there shall be none to make them afraid. 3 The fortress also shall cease from Ephraim, and the kingdom from Damascus, and the remnant of Syria: they shall be as the glory of the children of Israel, saith Jehovah of hosts. 4 And in that day it shall come to pass, that the glory of Jacob shall be made thin, and the fatness of his flesh shall become lean. 5 And it shall be as when the reaper gathereth the corn, and reapeth the ears with his arm; yea, it shall be as he that gathereth ears in the valley of Rephaim.

6 And a gleaning shall be left in it, as at the shaking of an olive-tree: two, three berries above, in the tree-top; four, five in its fruitful boughs, saith Jehovah, the God[*] of Israel. 7 In that day shall man look to his Maker, and his eyes shall have regard to the Holy One of Israel. 8 And he will not look to the altars, the work of his hands, nor have regard to what his fingers have made, neither the Asherahs nor the sun-images.

9 In that day shall his strong cities be as the forsaken tract in the woodland, and the mountain-top which they forsook before the children of Israel; and there shall be desolation. 10 For thou hast forgotten the God[*] of thy salvation, and hast not been mindful of the rock of thy strength; therefore shalt thou plant pleasant plantations, and shalt set them with foreign slips: 11 in the day of thy planting wilt thou make them to grow, and on the morrow wilt thou make thy seed to flourish; but the harvest will flee in the day of taking possession, and the sorrow will be incurable.

12 Ha! a tumult of many peoples! they make a noise as the noise of the seas; --and the rushing of nations! they rush as the rushing of mighty waters. 13 The nations rush as the rushing of many waters; but he will rebuke them, and they shall flee far away, and shall be chased as the chaff of the mountains before the wind, and like a whirling of dust before the whirlwind: 14 behold, at eventide, trouble; before the morning they are not. This is the portion of them that spoil us, and the lot of them that rob us.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 19

1 The burden of Egypt. Behold, Jehovah rideth upon a swift cloud, and cometh to Egypt; and the idols of Egypt are moved at his presence, and the heart of Egypt melteth in the midst of it. 2 And I will incite the Egyptians against the Egyptians; and they shall fight every one against his brother, and every one against his neighbour; city against city, kingdom against kingdom. 3 And the spirit of Egypt shall fail in the midst of it, and I will destroy the counsel thereof; and they shall seek unto the idols and unto the conjurers, and unto the necromancers, and unto the soothsayers. 4 And the Egyptians will I give over into the hand of a cruel lord, and a fierce king shall rule over them, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts. 5 And the waters shall fail from the sea, and the river shall be wasted and dried up; 6 and the rivers shall stink, and the streams of Egypt shall be diminished and drain away: the reeds and sedges shall wither. 7 The meadows by the Nile, on the banks of the Nile, and everything sown by the Nile, shall be dried up, be driven away, and be no more. 8 And the fishers shall mourn, and all they that cast fish-hook into the Nile shall lament, and they that spread net upon the waters shall languish. 9 And they that work in fine flax, and they that weave white stuffs shall be ashamed. 10 And her pillars shall be broken in pieces, and all workers for hire shall be sad of soul. 11 They are but fools, the princes of Zoan, the wise counsellors of Pharaoh: their counsel is become senseless. How say ye unto Pharaoh, I am the son of the wise, the son of ancient kings? 12 Where are they then, thy wise men? Let them now tell thee, and let them make known what Jehovah of hosts hath purposed upon Egypt. 13 The princes of Zoan are become foolish, the princes of Noph are deceived; and the corner-stones of its tribes have caused Egypt to err. 14 Jehovah hath mingled a spirit of perverseness in the midst thereof; and they have caused Egypt to err in every work thereof, as a drunkard staggereth in his vomit. 15 Neither shall there be any work for Egypt, which the head or tail, palm-branch or rush, may do. 16 In that day shall Egypt be like unto women; and it shall tremble and fear because of the shaking of the hand of Jehovah of hosts, which he shaketh over it. 17 And the land of Judah shall be a dismay unto Egypt: every one that thinketh of it shall be afraid for himself, because of the counsel of Jehovah of hosts, which he hath purposed against it.

18 In that day shall there be five cities in the land of Egypt speaking the language of Canaan, and swearing by Jehovah of hosts: one shall be called, The city of Heres. 19 In that day shall there be an altar to Jehovah in the midst of the land of Egypt, and a pillar at the border thereof to Jehovah: 20 and it shall be for a sign and for a witness to Jehovah of hosts in the land of Egypt; for they shall cry unto Jehovah because of the oppressors, and he will send them a saviour and defender, who shall deliver them. 21 And Jehovah shall be known to the Egyptians, and the Egyptians shall know Jehovah in that day, and shall serve with sacrifice and oblation; and they shall vow a vow unto Jehovah, and perform it. 22 And Jehovah will smite Egypt; he will smite and heal: and they shall return to Jehovah, and he will be entreated of them, and will heal them. 23 In that day shall there be a highway out of Egypt to Assyria; and the Assyrian shall come into Egypt, and the Egyptian into Assyria; and Egypt shall serve with Assyria. 24 In that day shall Israel be the third with Egypt and with Assyria, a blessing in the midst of the earth; 25 whom Jehovah of hosts will bless, saying, Blessed be Egypt my people, and Assyria the work of my hands, and Israel mine inheritance!

Isaiah 21

1 The burden of the desert of the sea. As whirlwinds in the south pass through, so it cometh from the desert, from a terrible land. 2 A grievous vision is declared unto me: the treacherous dealeth treacherously, and the spoiler spoileth. Go up, Elam! besiege, Media! All the sighing thereof have I made to cease. 3 Therefore are my loins filled with pain; anguish hath taken hold upon me, as the anguish of a woman in travail: I am bowed down so as not to hear, I am dismayed so as not to see. 4 My heart panteth, horror affrighteth me: the night of my pleasure hath he turned into trembling unto me. 5 Prepare the table, appoint the watch; eat, drink: arise, ye princes, anoint the shield. 6 For thus hath the Lord said unto me: Go, set a watchman, let him declare what he seeth. 7 And he saw chariots, horsemen by pairs, a chariot with asses, a chariot with camels; and he hearkened diligently with much heed. 8 And he cried as a lion, Lord, I stand continually upon the watchtower in the daytime, and I am set in my ward whole nights. 9 --And behold, there cometh a chariot of men; horsemen by pairs. And he answered and said, Babylon is fallen, is fallen; and all the graven images of her gods he hath broken unto the ground. 10 O my threshing, and the corn of my floor! What I have heard of Jehovah of hosts, the God[*] of Israel, have I declared unto you.

11 The burden of Dumah. He calleth to me out of Seir, Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night? 12 The watchman said, The morning cometh, and also the night: if ye will inquire, inquire; return, come.

13 The burden against Arabia. In the forest of Arabia shall ye lodge, ye caravans of Dedanites. 14 Bring ye water to meet the thirsty! The inhabitants of the land of Tema come forth with their bread for him that fleeth. 15 For they flee from the swords, from the drawn sword, and from the bent bow, and from the grievousness of war. 16 For thus hath the Lord said unto me: Within a year, according to the years of a hired servant, and all the glory of Kedar shall fail; 17 and the residue of the number of the archers, the mighty men of the sons of Kedar, shall be diminished: for Jehovah, the God[*] of Israel, hath spoken.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 22

1 The burden of the valley of vision. What aileth thee now, that thou art wholly gone up to the housetops? 2 Thou that wast full of stir, a town of tumult, a joyous city: thy slain men are not slain with the sword, nor dead in battle. 3 All thy rulers have fled together, they are taken prisoners without the bow: all that are found of thee are made prisoners together; they were fleeing far off. 4 Therefore said I, Look away from me; let me weep bitterly: labour not to comfort me, because of the spoiling of the daughter of my people. 5 For it is a day of trouble, and of treading down, and of perplexity, from the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, in the valley of vision; a day of breaking down the wall, and of crying to the mountain: 6 --Elam beareth the quiver with chariots of men and horsemen; and Kir uncovereth the shield. 7 And it shall come to pass that thy choicest valleys shall be full of chariots, and the horsemen shall set themselves in array at the gate.

8 And he uncovereth the covering of Judah: and thou didst look in that day to the armour in the house of the forest; 9 and ye have seen the breaches of the city of David, that they are many; and ye have gathered together the waters of the lower pool; 10 and ye have numbered the houses of Jerusalem, and have broken down the houses to fortify the wall; 11 and ye have made a reservoir between the two walls for the water of the old pool: but ye have not had regard unto the maker thereof, neither have ye looked unto him that fashioned it long ago. 12 And in that day did the Lord Jehovah of hosts call to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldness, and to girding with sackcloth; 13 and behold joy and rejoicing, slaying oxen, and killing sheep, eating flesh, and drinking wine: --Let us eat and drink, for to-morrow we die. 14 And it was revealed in mine ears by Jehovah of hosts: Assuredly this iniquity shall not be purged from you till ye die, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts.

15 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah of hosts: Go, get thee in unto this steward, unto Shebna, who is over the house, and say, 16 What hast thou here? and whom hast thou here, that thou hast hewn thee out a sepulchre here, as he that heweth out his sepulchre on high, cutting out in the rock a habitation for himself? 17 Behold, Jehovah will hurl thee with the force of a mighty man, and will cover thee entirely. 18 Rolling thee up completely, he will roll thee as a ball into a wide country: there shalt thou die, and there shall be the chariots of thy glory, O shame of thy lord's house! 19 And I will drive thee from thine office, and from thy station will I pull thee down. 20 And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will call my servant Eliakim the son of Hilkijah; 21 and I will clothe him with thy robe, and strengthen him with thy girdle, and I will commit thy government into his hand; and he shall be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to the house of Judah. 22 And the key of the house of David will I lay upon his shoulder; and he shall open, and none shall shut; and he shall shut, and none shall open. 23 And I will fasten him as a nail in a sure place; and he shall be for a throne of glory to his father's house: 24 and they shall hang upon him all the glory of his father's house, the offspring and the issue, all the small vessels, as well the vessels of cups as all the vessels of flagons. 25 In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, shall the nail that is fastened in a sure place be removed, and be cut down, and fall; and the burden that was upon it shall be cut off: for Jehovah hath spoken.

Isaiah 23

1 The burden of Tyre. Howl, ye ships of Tarshish! for it is laid waste, so that there is no house, none entering in. From the land of Chittim it is revealed to them. 2 Be still, ye inhabitants of the isle! The merchants of Sidon, that pass over the sea, have replenished thee. 3 And on great waters, the seed of Shihor, the harvest of the Nile, was her revenue; and she was the market of the nations. 4 Be thou ashamed, Sidon, for the sea hath spoken, the strength of the sea, saying, I have not travailed nor brought forth, neither have I nourished young men nor brought up virgins. 5 --When the report came into Egypt, they were sorely pained at the news of Tyre. 6 Pass over to Tarshish; howl, ye inhabitants of the coast! 7 Is this your joyous city, whose antiquity is of ancient days? Her feet shall carry her afar off to sojourn. 8 Who hath purposed this against Tyre, the distributor of crowns, whose merchants were princes, whose dealers were the honourable of the earth? 9 Jehovah of hosts hath purposed it, to profane the pride of all glory, to bring to nought all the honourable of the earth. 10 Overflow thy land like the Nile, daughter of Tarshish: there is no more restraint. 11 He hath stretched out his hand over the sea, he shaketh the kingdoms. Jehovah hath given a commandment concerning Canaan, to destroy the strongholds thereof, 12 and hath said, Thou shalt no more exult, thou oppressed virgin, daughter of Sidon: get thee up, pass over to Chittim; even there shalt thou have no rest. 13 Behold the land of the Chaldeans: this people did not exist; the Assyrian founded it for the dwellers in the desert: they set up their towers, they destroyed the palaces thereof; he brought it to ruin. 14 Howl, ships of Tarshish! for your fortress is laid waste.

15 And it shall come to pass in that day, that Tyre shall be forgotten seventy years, according to the days of one king. At the end of seventy years it shall be for Tyre as the harlot's song. 16 Take a harp, go about the city, thou forgotten harlot! Make sweet melody, sing many songs, that thou mayest be remembered. 17 And it shall come to pass at the end of seventy years, that Jehovah will visit Tyre; and she will return to her hire, and will commit fornication with all the kingdoms of the earth upon the face of the ground. 18 And her merchandise and her hire shall be holy to Jehovah: it shall not be treasured nor laid up; for her merchandise shall be for them that dwell before Jehovah, to eat and be sufficed, and for excellent clothing.

Isaiah 24

1 Behold, Jehovah maketh the land empty, and maketh it waste, and turneth it upside down, and scattereth abroad its inhabitants. 2 And it shall be, as with the people, so with the priest; as with the servant, so with his master; as with the maid, so with her mistress; as with the buyer, so with the seller; as with the lender, so with the borrower; as with the taker of usury, so with him from whom usury is taken. 3 The land shall be utterly emptied, and utterly spoiled; for Jehovah hath spoken this word. 4 The land mourneth, it fadeth away; the world languisheth, it fadeth away: the haughty people of the land do languish. 5 And the land is polluted under the inhabitants thereof; for they have violated the laws, changed the statute, broken the everlasting covenant. 6 Therefore doth the curse devour the earth, and they that dwell therein are held guilty; therefore the inhabitants of the earth are consumed, and few men are left. 7 The new wine mourneth, the vine languisheth, all that were merry-hearted do sigh; 8 the mirth of tambours ceaseth, the noise of them that rejoice endeth, the joy of the harp ceaseth. 9 They do not drink wine with a song; strong drink is bitter to them that drink it. 10 The city of solitude is broken down; every house is shut up, so that none entereth in. 11 There is a crying for wine in the streets; all joy is darkened, the mirth of the land is gone; 12 desolation remaineth in the city, and the gate is smitten, --a ruin.

13 For so will it be in the midst of the land among the peoples, as the shaking of an olive-tree, as the grape-gleanings when the vintage is done. 14 These shall lift up their voice, they shall shout for the majesty of Jehovah, they shall cry aloud from the sea. 15 Therefore glorify Jehovah in the east, the name of Jehovah, the God[*] of Israel, in the isles of the west.

16 From the end of the earth have we heard songs: Glory to the righteous! And I said, My leanness, my leanness, woe unto me! The treacherous have dealt treacherously; yea, the treacherous have dealt very treacherously. 17 Fear, and the pit, and the snare are upon thee, inhabitant of the land. 18 And it shall come to pass, that he who fleeth from the sound of the fear shall fall into the pit; and he that cometh up out of the midst of the pit shall be taken in the snare; for the windows on high are open, and the foundations of the earth shake. 19 The earth is utterly broken down, the earth is completely dissolved, the earth is violently moved. 20 The earth reeleth to and fro like a drunkard, and is shaken like a night hut; and its transgression is heavy upon it; and it falleth and shall not rise again. 21 And it shall come to pass in that day, that Jehovah will punish the host of the high ones on high, and the kings of the earth upon the earth. 22 And they shall be brought together, as an assemblage of prisoners for the pit, and shall be shut up in prison, and after many days shall they be visited. 23 And the moon shall be confounded, and the sun ashamed; for Jehovah of hosts shall reign on mount Zion, and in Jerusalem, and before his ancients in glory.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 25

1 Jehovah, thou art my God[*] I will exalt thee; I will celebrate thy name, for thou hast done wonderful things; counsels of old which are faithfulness and truth. 2 For thou hast made of the city a heap, of the fortified town a ruin, the palace of strangers to be no city; it shall never be built up. 3 Therefore shall the mighty people glorify thee, the city of terrible nations shall fear thee. 4 For thou hast been a fortress to the poor, a fortress for the needy in his distress, a refuge from the storm, a shadow from the heat: for the blast of the terrible ones has been as the storm against a wall. 5 Thou hast subdued the tumult of strangers, as the heat in a dry place; as the heat, by the shadow of a cloud, so the song of the terrible ones is brought low.

6 And in this mountain will Jehovah of hosts make unto all peoples a feast of fat things, a feast of wines on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of wines on the lees well refined. 7 And he will destroy in this mountain the face of the veil which veileth all the peoples, and the covering that is spread over all the nations. 8 He will swallow up death in victory. And the Lord Jehovah will wipe away tears from off all faces; and the reproach of his people will he take away from off all the earth: for Jehovah hath spoken.

9 And it shall be said in that day, Behold, this is our God[*] we have waited for him, and he will save us: this is Jehovah, we have waited for him; we will be glad and rejoice in his salvation. 10 For in this mountain shall the hand of Jehovah rest, and Moab shall be trodden down under him, as straw is trodden down in the dunghill; 11 and he shall spread forth his hands in the midst of them, as he that swimmeth spreadeth them forth to swim; and he shall bring down their pride together with the plots of their hands. 12 And the fortress of the high defences of thy walls will he bring down, lay low, bring to the ground, into the dust.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 26

1 In that day shall this song be sung in the land of Judah: We have a strong city; salvation doth he appoint for walls and bulwarks. 2 Open ye the gates, and the righteous nation which keepeth faithfulness shall enter in. 3 Thou wilt keep in perfect peace the mind stayed on thee, for he confideth in thee. 4 Confide ye in Jehovah for ever; for in Jah, Jehovah, is the rock of ages.

5 For he bringeth down them that dwell on high; the lofty city, he layeth it low, he layeth it low to the ground, he bringeth it even to the dust. 6 The foot shall tread it down, --the feet of the afflicted, the steps of the poor. 7 The way of the just is uprightness: thou, the Upright, dost make the path of the just even. 8 Yea, in the way of thy judgments, O Jehovah, have we waited for thee; the desire of our soul is to thy name, and to thy memorial. 9 With my soul have I desired thee in the night; yea, with my spirit within me I seek thee early: for when thy judgments are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world learn righteousness. 10 If favour be shewn to the wicked, he doth not learn righteousness: in the land of uprightness he dealeth unjustly, and beholdeth not the majesty of Jehovah. 11 Jehovah, thy hand is lifted up, but they do not see: yet they shall see thy jealousy for the people, and be ashamed; yea, the fire which is for thine adversaries shall devour them.

12 Jehovah, thou wilt ordain peace for us; for thou also hast wrought all our works for us. 13 Jehovah our God[*] other lords than thee have had dominion over us; by thee only will we make mention of thy name. 14 They are dead, they shall not live; deceased, they shall not rise: for thou hast visited and destroyed them, and made all memory of them to perish. 15 Thou hast increased the nation, Jehovah, thou hast increased the nation: thou art glorified. Thou hadst removed it far unto all the ends of the earth. 16 Jehovah, in trouble they sought thee; they poured out their whispered prayer when thy chastening was upon them. 17 As a woman with child, that draweth near her delivery, is in travail, and crieth out in her pangs; so have we been before thee, Jehovah. 18 We have been with child, we have been in travail, we have as it were brought forth wind; we have not wrought the deliverance of the land, neither have the inhabitants of the world fallen. 19 Thy dead shall live, my dead bodies shall arise. Awake and sing in triumph, ye that dwell in dust; for thy dew is the dew of the morning, and the earth shall cast forth the dead.

20 Come, my people, enter into thy chambers, and shut thy doors about thee; hide thyself just for a little moment, until the indignation be past. 21 For behold, Jehovah cometh out of his place to visit the iniquity of the inhabitants of the earth upon them; and the earth shall disclose her blood, and shall no more cover her slain.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 27

1 In that day Jehovah, with his sore and great and strong sword, will visit leviathan the fleeing serpent, and leviathan the crooked serpent; and he will slay the monster that is in the sea. 2 In that day there shall be a vineyard of pure wine; sing concerning it: 3 I Jehovah keep it, I will water it every moment; lest any harm it, I will keep it night and day. 4 Fury is not in me. Oh that I had briars and thorns in battle against me! I would march against them, I would burn them together. 5 Or let him take hold of my strength; let him make peace with me: yea, let him make peace with me. 6 In the future Jacob shall take root; Israel shall blossom and bud, and they shall fill the face of the world with fruit.

7 Hath he smitten him according to the smiting of those that smote him? Is he slain according to the slaughter of those slain by him? 8 In measure, when sending her away, didst thou contend with her: he hath taken her away with his rough wind in the day of the east wind. 9 By this, therefore, shall the iniquity of Jacob be purged; and this is all the fruit of the taking away of his sin: when he shall make all the stones of the altar as chalkstones that are crumbled in pieces, --the Asherahs and the sun-images shall not stand. 10 For the fortified city is solitary, a habitation abandoned and forsaken like a wilderness; there shall the calf feed, and there shall he lie down, and consume its boughs. 11 When its branches are withered they shall be broken off; women shall come and set them on fire. For it is a people of no intelligence; therefore he that made them will not have mercy on them, and he who formed them will shew them no favour. 12 And it shall come to pass in that day, that Jehovah shall beat out from the flood of the river unto the torrent of Egypt, and ye shall be gathered one by one, ye children of Israel. 13 And it shall come to pass in that day, that the great trumpet shall be blown; and they shall come that were perishing in the land of Assyria, and the outcasts in the land of Egypt, and they shall worship Jehovah in the holy mountain at Jerusalem.

Isaiah 28

1 Woe to the crown of pride of the drunkards of Ephraim, and to the fading flower of his glorious adornment, which is on the head of the fat valley of them that are overcome with wine. 2 Behold, the Lord hath a mighty and strong one, as a storm of hail and a destroying tempest; as a storm of mighty waters overflowing, shall he cast down to the earth with might. 3 The crown of pride of the drunkards of Ephraim shall be trodden under feet; 4 and the fading flower of his glorious adornment which is on the head of the fat valley shall be like an early fig before the summer: as soon as he that seeth it perceiveth it, scarcely is it in his hand, he swalloweth it down. 5 In that day will Jehovah of hosts be for a crown of glory, and for a diadem of beauty, unto the remnant of his people; 6 and for a spirit of judgment to him that sitteth in judgment, and for strength to them that turn the battle to the gate. 7 But these also have erred through wine, and through strong drink are they gone astray. The priest and the prophet have erred through strong drink; they are overpowered by wine, they are gone astray through strong drink; they have erred in vision, they have stumbled in judgment. 8 For all tables are full of filthy vomit, so that there is no more place.

9 Whom shall he teach knowledge? and whom shall he make to understand the report? Them that are weaned from the milk, withdrawn from the breasts? 10 For it is precept upon precept, precept upon precept; line upon line, line upon line; here a little, there a little. ... 11 For with stammering lips and a strange tongue will he speak to this people; 12 to whom he said, This is the rest: cause the weary to rest; and this is the refreshing. But they would not hear. 13 And the word of Jehovah was unto them precept upon precept, precept upon precept, line upon line, line upon line, here a little, there a little: that they might go, and fall backward, and be broken, and snared, and taken.

14 Therefore hear the word of Jehovah, ye scornful men, that rule this people which is in Jerusalem. 15 For ye have said, We have made a covenant with death, and with Sheol have we made an agreement; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, it shall not come unto us; for we have made lies our refuge, and under falsehood have we hid ourselves. 16 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I lay for foundation in Zion a stone, a tried stone, a precious corner-stone, a sure foundation: he that trusteth shall not make haste. 17 And I will appoint judgment for a line, and righteousness for a plummet; and the hail shall sweep away the refuge of lies, and the waters shall overflow the hiding-place. 18 And your covenant with death shall be annulled, and your agreement with Sheol shall not stand; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, ye shall be trodden down by it. 19 As it passeth through it shall take you; for morning by morning shall it pass through, by day and by night; and it shall be terror only to understand the report. 20 For the bed is too short to stretch oneself on, and the covering too narrow when he would wrap himself in it. 21 For Jehovah will rise up as on mount Perazim, he will be moved with anger as in the valley of Gibeon; that he may do his work, his strange work, and perform his act, his unwonted act. 22 Now therefore be ye not scorners, lest your bonds be made strong; for I have heard from the Lord Jehovah of hosts a consumption, and one determined, upon the whole land.

23 Give ear, and hear my voice; hearken, and hear my speech. 24 Doth the ploughman plough all day to sow? Is he all day opening and breaking the clods of his land? 25 Doth he not, when he hath levelled the face thereof, cast abroad dill, and scatter cummin, and set the wheat in rows, and the barley in an appointed place, and the rye in its border? 26 His God[*] doth instruct him in his judgment, he doth teach him. 27 For the dill is not threshed with a threshing instrument, neither is a cart-wheel turned about upon the cummin; but dill is beaten out with a staff, and cummin with a rod. 28 Bread corn is crushed, because he will not ever be threshing it; and if he drove the wheels of his cart and his horses over it, he would not crush it. 29 This also cometh forth from Jehovah of hosts; he is wonderful in counsel, great in wisdom.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 29

1 Woe to Ariel, to Ariel, the city of David's encampment! Add ye year to year; let the feasts come round. 2 But I will distress Ariel, and there shall be sorrow and sadness; and it shall be unto me as an Ariel. 3 And I will camp against thee round about, and will lay siege against thee with watch-posts, and I will raise forts against thee. 4 And thou shalt be brought low, thou shalt speak out of the ground, and thy speech shall come low out of the dust, and thy voice shall be as of one that hath a familiar spirit, out of the ground, and thy speech shall whisper out of the dust. 5 And the multitude of thine enemies shall be like small dust, and the multitude of the terrible ones as chaff that passeth away; and it shall be in an instant, suddenly. 6 Thou shalt be visited by Jehovah of hosts with thunder and with earthquake and great noise, with whirlwind and tempest, and the flame of devouring fire. 7 And the multitude of all the nations that war against Ariel, even all that war against her and her fortifications, and that distress her, shall be as a dream of a night vision. 8 It shall even be as when the hungry dreameth, and, behold, he eateth; and he awaketh, and his soul is empty; or as when the thirsty dreameth, and, behold, he drinketh; and he awaketh, and, behold, he is faint, and his soul craveth: so shall the multitude of all the nations be that war against mount Zion.

9 Be astounded and astonished, blind yourselves and be blind! They are drunken, but not with wine; they stagger, but not with strong drink. 10 For Jehovah hath poured out upon you a spirit of deep sleep, and hath closed your eyes; the prophets and your chiefs, the seers, hath he covered. 11 And the whole vision is become unto you as the words of a book that is sealed, which they give to one that can read, saying, Read this, I pray thee; and he saith, I cannot, for it is sealed. 12 And they give the book to him that cannot read, saying, Read this, I pray thee; and he saith, I cannot read. 13 And the Lord saith, Forasmuch as this people draw near with their mouth, and honour me with their lips, but their heart is removed far from me, and their fear of me is a commandment taught of men; 14 therefore, behold, I will proceed to do marvellously with this people, to do marvellously, even with wonder, and the wisdom of their wise men shall perish, and the understanding of their intelligent ones shall be hid. 15 Woe unto them that hide deep, far from Jehovah, their counsel! And their works are in the dark, and they say, Who seeth us? and who knoweth us? 16 Oh your perverseness! --Shall the potter be esteemed as the clay, so that the work should say of him that made it, He made me not; or the thing formed say of him that formed it, He hath no understanding?

17 Is it not yet a very little while, and Lebanon shall be turned into a fruitful field, and the fruitful field shall be esteemed as a forest? 18 And in that day shall the deaf hear the words of the book, and, out of obscurity and out of darkness, the eyes of the blind shall see; 19 and the meek shall increase their joy in Jehovah, and the needy among men shall rejoice in the Holy One of Israel. 20 For the terrible one shall come to nought, and the scorner shall be no more, and all that watch for iniquity shall be cut off, 21 that make a man an offender for a word, and lay a snare for him that reproveth in the gate, and pervert the judgment of the righteous by futility. 22 Therefore thus saith Jehovah who redeemed Abraham, concerning the house of Jacob: Jacob shall not now be ashamed, neither shall his face now be pale; 23 for when he seeth his children, the work of my hands, in the midst of him, they shall hallow my name, and hallow the Holy One of Jacob, and shall fear the God[*] of Israel. 24 And they that are of erring spirit shall know understanding, and the disobedient shall learn doctrine.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 30

1 Woe to the rebellious children, saith Jehovah, who take counsel, but not of me, and who make leagues, but not by my Spirit, that they may heap sin upon sin; 2 who walk to go down into Egypt, and have not asked of my mouth, --to take refuge under the protection of Pharaoh, and trust in the shadow of Egypt! 3 For to you the protection of Pharaoh shall be a shame, and the trust in the shadow of Egypt a confusion. 4 For his princes were at Zoan, and his ambassadors came to Hanes. 5 They were all ashamed of a people that did not profit them, nor were a help or profit, but a shame, and also a reproach. 6 --The burden of the beasts of the south: Through a land of trouble and anguish, whence come the lioness and lion, the viper and fiery flying serpent, they carry their riches upon the shoulders of asses, and their treasures upon the bunches of camels, to the people that shall not profit them. 7 For Egypt shall help in vain, and to no purpose; therefore have I named her, Arrogance, that doeth nothing.

8 Now go, write it before them on a tablet, and record it in a book, that it may be for the time to come, as a witness for ever, 9 that this is a rebellious people, lying children, children that will not hear the law of Jehovah; 10 who say to the seers, See not; and to the prophets, Prophesy not unto us right things; speak unto us smooth things, prophesy deceits; 11 get you out of the way, turn aside out of the path, cause the Holy One of Israel to cease from before us! 12 Therefore thus saith the Holy One of Israel: Because ye reject this word, and confide in oppression and wilfulness, and depend thereon, 13 therefore this iniquity shall be to you as a breach ready to fall, swelling out in a towering wall, whose breaking shall come suddenly in an instant. 14 And he shall break it as the breaking of a potter's vessel, that is broken in pieces unsparingly; and in the pieces of it there shall not be found a sherd to take fire from the hearth, or to scoop water out of the cistern. 15 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel: In returning and rest shall ye be saved, in quietness and confidence shall be your strength; but ye would not. 16 And ye said, No, but we will flee upon horses, --therefore shall ye flee; and, We will ride upon the swift, --therefore shall they that pursue you be swift. 17 One thousand shall flee at the rebuke of one; at the rebuke of five shall ye flee: till ye be left as a beacon upon the top of a mountain, and as a banner on a hill.

18 And therefore will Jehovah wait, that he may be gracious unto you, and therefore will he lift himself up, that he may have mercy upon you; for Jehovah is a God[*] of judgment: blessed are all they that wait for him. 19 For the people shall dwell in Zion, at Jerusalem. Thou shalt weep no more; he will be very gracious unto thee at the voice of thy cry; as he heareth it, he will answer thee. 20 And the Lord will give you the bread of adversity, and the water of oppression; yet thy teachers shall not be hidden any more, but thine eyes shall see thy teachers. 21 And when ye turn to the right hand or when ye turn to the left, thine ears shall hear a word behind thee, saying, This is the way, walk ye in it. 22 And ye shall defile the silver covering of your graven images, and the gold overlaying of your molten images; thou shalt cast them away as a menstruous cloth: Out! shalt thou say unto it. 23 And he will give the rain of thy seed with which thou shalt sow the ground; and bread, the produce of the ground, and it shall be fat and rich. In that day shall thy cattle feed in large pastures; 24 and the oxen and the asses that till the ground shall eat salted provender, which hath been winnowed with the shovel and with the fan. 25 And there shall be upon every high mountain and upon every hill that is lifted up, brooks and water-courses, in the day of the great slaughter, when the towers fall. 26 And the light of the moon shall be as the light of the sun, and the light of the sun shall be sevenfold, as the light of seven days, in the day that Jehovah bindeth up the breach of his people, and healeth the wound of their stroke.

27 Behold, the name of Jehovah cometh from far, burning with his anger--a grievous conflagration; his lips are full of indignation, and his tongue as a consuming fire; 28 and his breath as an overflowing torrent, which reacheth even to the neck, to sift the nations with the sieve of destruction, and to put a bridle into the jaws of the peoples, that causeth them to go astray. 29 Ye shall have a song, as in the night when a feast is sanctified; and joy of heart, as of one who goeth with a pipe to come unto the mountain of Jehovah, to the Rock of Israel. 30 And Jehovah will cause the majesty of his voice to be heard, and will shew the lighting down of his arm with indignation of anger, and a flame of consuming fire, with waterflood and storm and hailstones. 31 For through the voice of Jehovah shall the Assyrian be broken down: he will smite him with the rod. 32 And wherever shall pass the appointed staff, which Jehovah shall lay upon him, it shall be with tambours and harps; and with tumultuous battles will he fight with it. 33 For Topheth is prepared of old; for the king also it is prepared: he hath made it deep and large; its pile is fire and much wood; the breath of Jehovah, like a stream of brimstone, doth kindle it.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 33

1 Woe to thee that spoilest, and thou wast not spoiled; and that dealest treacherously, and they dealt not treacherously with thee! When thou shalt cease to spoil, thou shalt be spoiled; when thou shalt make an end of dealing treacherously, they shall deal treacherously with thee. 2 Jehovah, be gracious unto us; we have waited for thee: be their arm every morning, yea, our salvation in the time of trouble. 3 At the noise of the tumult the peoples fled; at the lifting up of thyself the nations were scattered. 4 And your spoil shall be gathered like the gathering of the caterpillar: as the running of locusts shall they run upon it. 5 Jehovah is exalted; for he dwelleth on high: he hath filled Zion with justice and righteousness; 6 and he shall be the stability of thy times, the riches of salvation, wisdom and knowledge: the fear of Jehovah shall be your treasure. 7 Behold, their valiant ones cry without; the messengers of peace weep bitterly. 8 The highways are desolate, the wayfaring man ceaseth. He hath broken the covenant, he hath despised the cities, he regardeth no man. 9 The land mourneth, it languisheth; Lebanon is ashamed, is withered; the Sharon is become as a desert, and Bashan and Carmel are stripped. 10 Now will I arise, saith Jehovah; now will I be exalted, now will I lift up myself. 11 Ye shall conceive dry grass, ye shall bring forth stubble: your breath shall devour you as fire. 12 And the peoples shall be as burnings of lime, as thorns cut up shall they be burned in the fire.

13 Hear, ye that are far off, what I have done; and ye that are near, acknowledge my might. 14 The sinners in Zion are afraid; trembling hath surprised the hypocrites: Who among us shall dwell with the consuming fire? who among us shall dwell with everlasting flames? 15 --He that walketh righteously, and speaketh uprightly; he that despiseth the gain of oppressions, that shaketh his hands from taking hold of bribes, that stoppeth his ears from hearing of blood, and shutteth his eyes from seeing evil: 16 he shall dwell on high, the fortresses of the rocks shall be his high retreat; bread shall be given him, his water shall be sure. 17 Thine eyes shall see the King in his beauty; they shall behold the land that is far off. 18 Thy heart shall meditate on terror: Where is the scribe? where is the receiver? where is he that counted the towers? 19 Thou shalt no more see the fierce people, a people of a deeper speech than thou canst comprehend, of a stammering tongue that cannot be understood. 20 Look upon Zion, the city of our solemnities: thine eyes shall see Jerusalem a quiet habitation, a tent that shall not be removed, the stakes whereof shall never be pulled up, neither shall any of its cords be broken; 21 but there Jehovah is unto us glorious, --a place of rivers, of broad streams: no galley with oars shall go there, neither shall gallant ship pass thereby. 22 For Jehovah is our judge, Jehovah, our lawgiver, Jehovah, our king: he will save us. 23 Thy tacklings are loosed; they strengthen not the socket of their mast, they cannot spread the sail: then is the prey of a great spoil divided; the lame take the prey. 24 And the inhabitant shall not say, I am sick: the people that dwell therein shall be forgiven their iniquity.

Isaiah 34

1 Come near, ye nations, to hear; and hearken, ye peoples: let the earth hear, and all its fulness; the world, and all that cometh forth of it. 2 For the wrath of Jehovah is against all the nations, and his fury against all their armies: he hath devoted them to destruction, he hath delivered them to the slaughter. 3 And their slain shall be cast out, and their stink shall come up from their carcases, and the mountains shall be melted with their blood. 4 And all the host of the heavens shall be dissolved, and the heavens shall be rolled together as a scroll; and all their host shall fade away, as a leaf fadeth from off the vine, and as the withered fruit from the fig-tree. 5 For my sword is bathed in the heavens; behold, it shall come down upon Edom, and upon the people of my ban, to judgment. 6 The sword of Jehovah is filled with blood, it is made fat with fatness, with the blood of lambs and goats, with the fat of the kidneys of rams; for Jehovah hath a sacrifice in Bozrah, and a great slaughter in the land of Edom. 7 And the buffaloes shall come down with them, and the bullocks with the bulls; and their land shall be soaked with blood, and their dust made fat with fatness. 8 For it is the day of Jehovah's vengeance, the year of recompenses for the controversy of Zion.

9 And the torrents thereof shall be turned into pitch, and its dust into brimstone; yea, the land thereof shall become burning pitch: 10 it shall not be quenched night nor day; the smoke thereof shall go up for ever: from generation to generation it shall lie waste; none shall pass through it for ever and ever. 11 And the pelican and the bittern shall possess it, and the great owl and the raven shall dwell in it. And he shall stretch out upon it the line of waste, and the plummets of emptiness. 12 Of her nobles who should proclaim the kingdom, none are there; and all her princes shall be nought. 13 And thorns shall come up in her palaces, nettles and brambles in her fortresses; and it shall be a dwelling-place of wild dogs, a court for ostriches. 14 And there shall the beasts of the desert meet with the jackals, and the wild goat shall cry to his fellow; the lilith also shall settle there, and find for herself a place of rest. 15 There shall the arrow-snake make her nest, and lay, and hatch, and gather under her shadow; there also shall the vultures be gathered one with another. 16 Search ye in the book of Jehovah and read: not one of these shall fail, one shall not have to seek for the other; for my mouth, it hath commanded, and his Spirit, it hath gathered them. 17 For he himself hath cast the lot for them, and his hand hath divided it unto them with the line: they shall possess it for ever; from generation to generation shall they dwell therein.

Isaiah 36

1 And it came to pass in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, that Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all the fortified cities of Judah, and took them. 2 And the king of Assyria sent Rab-shakeh from Lachish to Jerusalem, to king Hezekiah, with a strong force. And he stood by the aqueduct of the upper pool, on the highway of the fuller's field. 3 Then came forth to him Eliakim the son of Hilkijah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph, the chronicler. 4 And Rab-shakeh said to them, Say now to Hezekiah, Thus says the great king, the king of Assyria: What confidence is this in which thou trustest? 5 Thou sayest, but it is a word of the lips, There is counsel and strength for war. Now on whom dost thou rely, that thou hast revolted against me? 6 Behold, thou reliest upon the staff of that broken reed, upon Egypt, on which if a man lean, it goes into his hand, and pierces it: so is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all that rely upon him. 7 And if thou say to me, We rely upon Jehovah our God[*] is it not he, whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah has removed, saying to Judah and Jerusalem, Ye shall worship before this altar? 8 And now engage, I pray thee, with my master the king of Assyria, and I will give thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to set riders upon them. 9 How then wilt thou turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master's servants? And thou reliest upon Egypt for chariots and for horsemen! 10 And now am I come up without Jehovah against this land to destroy it? Jehovah said to me, Go up against this land and destroy it.

11 And Eliakim and Shebna and Joah said to Rab-shakeh, Speak, we pray thee, to thy servants in Syriac, for we understand it; and speak not to us in the Jewish language in the ears of the people that are upon the wall. 12 And Rab-shakeh said, Is it to thy master and to thee that my master sent me to speak these words? Is it not to the men that sit on the wall, that they may eat their own dung, and drink their own urine with you? 13 And Rab-shakeh stood and cried with a loud voice in the Jewish language, and said, Hear the words of the great king, the king of Assyria! 14 Thus says the king: Let not Hezekiah deceive you; for he will not be able to deliver you. 15 Neither let Hezekiah make you rely upon Jehovah, saying, Jehovah will certainly deliver us; this city shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria. 16 Hearken not to Hezekiah; for thus says the king of Assyria: Make peace with me and come out to me; and eat every one of his vine, and every one of his fig-tree, and drink every one the waters of his own cistern; 17 until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of corn and wine, a land of bread and vineyards. 18 Let not Hezekiah persuade you, saying, Jehovah will deliver us. Has any of the gods of the nations delivered his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria? 19 Where are the gods of Hamath and of Arpad? where are the gods of Sepharvaim? and have they delivered Samaria out of my hand? 20 Who are they among all the gods of these countries that have delivered their country out of my hand, that Jehovah should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand? 21 And they were silent, and answered him not a word; for the king's command was, saying, Answer him not. 22 And Eliakim the son of Hilkijah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph, the chronicler, came to Hezekiah, with their garments rent, and told him the words of Rab-shakeh.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 38

1 In those days Hezekiah was sick unto death. And the prophet Isaiah the son of Amoz came to him, and said to him, Thus saith Jehovah: Set thy house in order; for thou shalt die, and not live. 2 And Hezekiah turned his face to the wall, and prayed to Jehovah, 3 and said, Ah, Jehovah, remember, I beseech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight. And Hezekiah wept much. 4 And the word of Jehovah came to Isaiah, saying, 5 Go and say to Hezekiah, Thus saith Jehovah, the God[*] of David thy father: I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears: behold, I will add to thy days fifteen years. 6 And I will deliver thee and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria, and I will defend this city. 7 And this shall be the sign to thee from Jehovah, that Jehovah will do this thing that he hath spoken: 8 behold, I will bring again the shadow of the degrees which hath gone down with the sun on the dial of Ahaz, ten degrees backward. So the sun returned on the dial ten degrees, by which it had gone down.

9 The writing of Hezekiah king of Judah, when he had been sick and had recovered from his sickness: 10 I said, In the meridian of my days I shall go to the gates of Sheol: I am deprived of the rest of my years. 11 I said, I shall not see Jah, Jah in the land of the living. With those who dwell where all has ceased to be, I shall behold man no more. 12 Mine age is departed, and is removed from me as a shepherd's tent. I have cut off like a weaver my life. He separateth me from the thrum: --from day to night thou wilt make an end of me. 13 I kept still until the morning; ...as a lion, so doth he break all my bones. From day to night thou wilt make an end of me. 14 Like a swallow or a crane, so did I chatter; I mourned as a dove; mine eyes failed with looking upward: Lord, I am oppressed; undertake for me. 15 What shall I say? He hath both spoken unto me, and himself hath done it. I shall go softly all my years in the bitterness of my soul. 16 Lord, by these things men live, and in all these things is the life of my spirit; and thou hast recovered me, and made me to live. 17 Behold, instead of peace I had bitterness upon bitterness; but thou hast in love delivered my soul from the pit of destruction; for thou hast cast all my sins behind thy back. 18 For not Sheol shall praise thee, nor death celebrate thee; they that go down into the pit do not hope for thy truth. 19 The living, the living, he shall praise thee, as I this day: the father to the children shall make known thy truth. 20 Jehovah was purposed to save me. --And we will play upon my stringed instruments all the days of our life, in the house of Jehovah. 21 Now Isaiah had said, Let them take a cake of figs, and lay it for a plaster upon the boil, and he shall recover. 22 And Hezekiah had said, What is the sign that I shall go up into the house of Jehovah?

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 39

1 At that time Merodach-Baladan, the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent a letter and a present to Hezekiah; for he had heard that he had been sick and had recovered. 2 And Hezekiah was glad of them, and shewed them the house of his precious things, the silver and the gold, and the spices and the fine oil, and all the house of his armour, and all that was found amongst his treasures: there was nothing in his house, nor in all his dominion, that Hezekiah did not shew them. 3 Then came the prophet Isaiah to king Hezekiah, and said to him, What said these men? and from whence came they to thee? And Hezekiah said, They came from a far country to me, from Babylon. 4 And he said, What have they seen in thy house? And Hezekiah said, All that is in my house have they seen: there is nothing among my treasures that I have not shewn them.

5 And Isaiah said to Hezekiah, Hear the word of Jehovah of hosts: 6 Behold, days come when all that is in thy house, and that which thy fathers have laid up until this day, shall be carried to Babylon: nothing shall be left, saith Jehovah. 7 And of thy sons that shall issue from thee, whom thou shalt beget, shall they take away; and they shall be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon. 8 And Hezekiah said to Isaiah, Good is the word of Jehovah which thou hast spoken. And he said, For there shall be peace and truth in my days.

Isaiah 42

1 Behold my servant whom I uphold, mine elect in whom my soul delighteth! I will put my Spirit upon him; he shall bring forth judgment to the nations. 2 He shall not cry, nor lift up, nor cause his voice to be heard in the street. 3 A bruised reed shall he not break, and smoking flax shall he not quench: he shall bring forth judgment according to truth. 4 He shall not faint nor be in haste, till he have set justice in the earth: and the isles shall wait for his law.

5 Thus saith ·God[*] Jehovah, he that created the heavens and stretched them out, he that spread forth the earth and its productions, he that giveth breath unto the people upon it, and spirit to them that walk therein: 6 I, Jehovah, have called thee in righteousness, and will take hold of thy hand; and I will preserve thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, for a light of the nations, 7 to open the blind eyes, to bring forth the prisoner from the prison, them that sit in darkness out of the house of restraint. 8 I am Jehovah, that is my name; and my glory will I not give to another, neither my praise to graven images. 9 Behold, the former things are come to pass, and new things do I declare: before they spring forth will I cause you to hear them. 10 Sing unto Jehovah a new song, his praise from the end of the earth, ye that go down to the sea, and all that is therein, the isles and their inhabitants. 11 Let the wilderness and the cities thereof lift up their voice, the villages that Kedar doth inhabit; let the inhabitants of the rock sing, let them shout from the top of the mountains: 12 let them give glory unto Jehovah, and declare his praise in the islands.

13 Jehovah will go forth as a mighty man, he will stir up jealousy like a man of war: he will cry, yea, he will shout; he will shew himself mighty against his enemies. 14 Long time have I holden my peace; I have been still, I have restrained myself: I will cry like a woman that travaileth; I will blow and pant at once. 15 I will lay waste mountains and hills, and dry up all their herbs; and I will make the rivers islands, and I will dry up the pools. 16 And I will bring the blind by a way that they know not, in paths that they know not will I lead them; I will make darkness light before them, and crooked things straight. These things will I do unto them, and not forsake them. 17 They shall be turned back, they shall be covered with shame, that confide in graven images, that say to the molten images, Ye are our gods.

18 --Hear, ye deaf; and look, ye blind, that ye may see. 19 Who is blind, but my servant? and deaf, as my messenger whom I sent? Who is blind as he in whom I have trusted, and blind as Jehovah's servant, 20 --seeing many things, and thou observest not? With opened ears, he heareth not. 21 Jehovah had delight in him for his righteousness' sake: he hath magnified the law, and made it honourable. 22 But this is a people robbed and spoiled; they are all of them snared in holes, and hidden in prison-houses; they are become a prey, and none delivereth, --a spoil, and none saith, Restore. 23 Who among you will give ear to this, who will hearken and hear what is to come? 24 Who gave Jacob for a spoil, and Israel to the robbers? Did not Jehovah, he against whom we have sinned? And they would not walk in his ways, neither did they hearken unto his law. 25 And he hath poured upon him the fury of his anger, and the strength of battle: and it set him on fire round about, yet he knew not; and it burned him, yet he took it not to heart.

Hebrew: El

Isaiah 43

1 But now thus saith Jehovah, that created thee, O Jacob, and he that formed thee, O Israel: Fear not, for I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy name; thou art mine. 2 When thou passest through the waters, I will be with thee; and through the rivers, they shall not overflow thee; when thou walkest through the fire, thou shalt not be burned, neither shall the flame kindle upon thee. 3 For I am Jehovah thy God[*] the Holy One of Israel, thy Saviour: I gave Egypt for thy ransom, Ethiopia and Seba for thee. 4 Since thou wast precious in my sight, thou hast been honourable, and I have loved thee; and I will give men for thee, and peoples for thy life. 5 Fear not, for I am with thee: I will bring thy seed from the east, and gather thee from the west; 6 I will say to the north, Give up; and to the south, Keep not back: bring my sons from afar, and my daughters from the end of the earth, 7 every one that is called by my name, and whom I have created for my glory: I have formed him, yea, I have made him.

8 Bring forth the blind people that have eyes, and the deaf that have ears. 9 Let all the nations be gathered together, and let the peoples be assembled: who among them declareth this, or causeth us to hear former things? let them bring forth their witnesses, that they may be justified; or let them hear, and say, It is truth. 10 Ye are my witnesses, saith Jehovah, and my servant whom I have chosen; that ye may know and believe me, and understand that I am HE: before me there was no ·God[*] formed, neither shall there be after me. 11 I, I am Jehovah; and besides me there is no saviour. 12 It is I that have declared, and have saved, and have shewed, when there was no strange god among you; and ye are my witnesses, saith Jehovah, that I am ·God[*] 13 Yea, since the day was, I am HE, and there is none that delivereth out of my hand: I will work, and who shall hinder it?

14 Thus saith Jehovah, your Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel: For your sake I have sent to Babylon, and have brought all of them down as fugitives, even the Chaldeans, whose cry is in the ships. 15 I am Jehovah, your Holy One, the Creator of Israel, your King. 16 Thus saith Jehovah, who maketh a way in the sea, and a path in the mighty waters, 17 who bringeth forth chariot and horse, army and power--they lie down together, they shall not rise; they are extinct, they are quenched as tow: 18 --Remember not the former things, neither consider the ancient things: 19 behold, I do a new thing; now it shall spring forth: shall ye not know it? I will even make a way in the wilderness, rivers in the waste. 20 The beast of the field shall glorify me, the jackals and the ostriches; for I will give waters in the wilderness, rivers in the waste, to give drink to my people, my chosen. 21 This people have I formed for myself: they shall shew forth my praise.

22 --But thou hast not called upon me, Jacob; for thou hast been weary of me, O Israel: 23 thou hast not brought me the small cattle of thy burnt-offerings, neither hast thou glorified me with thy sacrifices. I have not caused thee to toil with an oblation, nor wearied thee with incense. 24 Thou hast bought me no sweet cane with money, neither hast thou filled me with the fat of thy sacrifices; but thou hast made me to toil with thy sins, thou hast wearied me with thine iniquities. 25 --I, I am He that blotteth out thy transgressions for mine own sake, and I will not remember thy sins. 26 Put me in remembrance, let us plead together; rehearse thine own cause, that thou mayest be justified. 27 Thy first father hath sinned, and thy mediators have rebelled against me. 28 And I have profaned the princes of the sanctuary, and have given Jacob to the ban, and Israel to reproaches.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: El

Hebrew: El

Isaiah 44

1 And now hear, Jacob, my servant, and Israel, whom I have chosen: 2 thus saith Jehovah, that made thee, and formed thee from the womb, who helpeth thee, Fear not, Jacob, my servant, and thou, Jeshurun, whom I have chosen. 3 For I will pour water upon him that is thirsty, and floods upon the dry ground; I will pour my Spirit upon thy seed, and my blessing upon thine offspring. 4 And they shall spring up among the grass, as willows by the water-courses. 5 One shall say, I am Jehovah's; and another shall call himself by the name of Jacob; and another shall write with his hand: I am Jehovah's, and surname himself by the name of Israel. 6 Thus saith Jehovah, the King of Israel, and his Redeemer, Jehovah of hosts: I am the first, and I am the last, and beside me there is no God[*] 7 And who, as I, shall call, and shall declare it, and set it in order for me, since I appointed the ancient people? And the coming things, and those that shall happen, let them declare unto them. 8 Fear not, neither be afraid. Have I not caused thee to hear from that time, and have declared it? and ye are my witnesses. Is there a +God[*] beside me? yea, there is no Rock: I know not any.

9 They that form a graven image are all of them vanity, and their delectable things are of no profit; and they are their own witnesses: they see not, nor know; --that they may be ashamed. 10 Who hath formed a god[*] or molten a graven image that is profitable for nothing? 11 Behold, all his fellows shall be ashamed; and the workmen are but men. Let them all be gathered together, let them stand up: they shall fear, they shall be ashamed together. 12 The iron-smith hath a chisel, and he worketh in the coals, and he fashioneth it with hammers, and worketh it with his strong arm; --but he is hungry, and his strength faileth; he hath not drunk water, and he is faint. 13 The worker in wood stretcheth out a line; he marketh it out with red chalk; he formeth it with sharp tools, and he marketh it out with the compass, and maketh it after the figure of a man, according to the beauty of man: that it may remain in the house. 14 When he heweth him down cedars, he taketh also a holm-oak and a terebinth--he chooseth for himself among the trees of the forest: he planteth a pine, and the rain maketh it grow. 15 And it shall be for a man to burn, and he taketh thereof, and warmeth himself; he kindleth it also, and baketh bread; he maketh also a god[*] and worshippeth it; he maketh it a graven image, and falleth down thereto. 16 He burneth part thereof in the fire; with part thereof he eateth flesh, he roasteth roast, and is satisfied; yea, he is warm, and saith, Aha, I am become warm, I have seen the fire. 17 And with the remainder thereof he maketh a god[*] his graven image; he falleth down unto it, and worshippeth it, and prayeth unto it, and saith, Deliver me, for thou art my god[*] 18 They have no knowledge, and understand not; for he hath plastered their eyes, that they may not see; and their hearts, that they may not understand. 19 And none taketh it to heart, neither is there knowledge nor understanding to say, I have burned part of it in the fire, and have also baked bread upon the coals thereof, I have roasted flesh, and eaten it, and with the rest thereof shall I make an abomination? shall I bow down to a block of wood? 20 He feedeth on ashes; a deceived heart hath turned him aside, that he cannot deliver his soul, nor say, Is there not a lie in my right hand?

21 Remember these things, O Jacob, and Israel, for thou art my servant; I have formed thee: thou art my servant, Israel; thou shalt not be forgotten of me. 22 I have blotted out, as a thick cloud, thy transgressions, and, as a cloud, thy sins: return unto me; for I have redeemed thee. 23 Sing, ye heavens; for Jehovah hath done it: shout, ye lower parts of the earth; break forth into singing, ye mountains, the forest, and every tree therein! For Jehovah hath redeemed Jacob, and glorified himself in Israel. 24 Thus saith Jehovah, thy Redeemer, and he that formed thee from the womb: I am Jehovah, the maker of all things; who alone stretched out the heavens, who did spread forth the earth by myself; 25 --he that frustrateth the tokens of the liars, and maketh diviners mad; that turneth wise men backward, and maketh their knowledge foolish; 26 that confirmeth the word of his servant, and performeth the counsel of his messengers; that saith to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be inhabited; and to the cities of Judah, Ye shall be built up, and I will raise up their ruins; 27 that saith to the deep, Be dry, and I will dry up thy rivers; 28 that saith of Cyrus, He is my shepherd, and he shall perform all my pleasure; even saying to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be built; and to the temple, Thy foundation shall be laid.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Eloah

Hebrew: el

Hebrew: el

Hebrew: el

Hebrew: el

Isaiah 46

1 Bel is bowed down, Nebo bendeth; their idols are upon the beasts, and upon the cattle: the things ye carried are laid on, a burden to the weary beast. 2 They bend, they are bowed down together; they could not deliver the burden, and themselves are gone into captivity. 3 Hearken unto me, house of Jacob, and all the remnant of the house of Israel, ye who have been borne from the belly, who have been carried from the womb: 4 Even to old age, I am HE, and unto hoary hairs I will carry you: It is I that have made, and I will bear, and I will carry, and will deliver.

5 To whom will ye liken me and make me equal, or compare me, that we may be like? 6 --They lavish gold out of the bag, and weigh silver in the balance; they hire a goldsmith, and he maketh it a god[*] they fall down, yea, they worship. 7 They bear him on the shoulder, they carry him, and set him in his place; there he standeth, he doth not remove from his place: yea, one crieth unto him, and he answereth not; he saveth him not out of his trouble. 8 Remember this, and shew yourselves men; call it to mind, ye transgressors. 9 Remember the former things of old; for I am ·God[*] and there is none else; I am God[*] and there is none like me; 10 declaring the end from the beginning, and from ancient times the things that are not yet done, saying, My counsel shall stand, and I will do all my pleasure; 11 calling a bird of prey from the east, the man of my counsel from a far country. Yea, I have spoken, I will also bring it to pass; I have purposed it, I will also do it. 12 Hearken unto me, ye stout-hearted, that are far from righteousness: 13 I bring near my righteousness; it shall not be far off, and my salvation shall not delay; and I will give salvation in Zion, and unto Israel my glory.

Hebrew: el

Hebrew: El

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 47

1 Come down and sit in the dust, virgin-daughter of Babylon! Sit on the ground, -- there is no throne, O daughter of the Chaldeans; for thou shalt no more be called tender and delicate. 2 Take the millstones, and grind meal; remove thy veil, lift up the train, uncover the leg, pass over rivers: 3 thy nakedness shall be uncovered, yea, thy shame shall be seen. I will take vengeance, and I will meet none to stay me. ... 4 Our Redeemer, Jehovah of hosts is his name, the Holy One of Israel. ... 5 Sit silent, and get thee into darkness, daughter of the Chaldeans; for thou shalt no more be called, Mistress of kingdoms. 6 I was wroth with my people, I polluted mine inheritance, and gave them into thy hand: thou didst shew them no mercy; upon the aged didst thou very heavily lay thy yoke;

7 and thou saidst, I shall be a mistress for ever; so that thou didst not take these things to heart, thou didst not remember the end thereof. 8 And now hear this, thou voluptuous one, that dwellest carelessly, that sayest in thy heart, It is I, and there is none but me; I shall not sit as a widow, neither shall I know loss of children: 9 yet these two things shall come upon thee in a moment, in one day, loss of children and widowhood; they shall come upon thee in full measure for the multitude of thy sorceries, for the great abundance of thine enchantments. 10 For thou hast confided in thy wickedness: thou hast said, None seeth me. Thy wisdom and thy knowledge, it hath seduced thee; and thou hast said in thy heart, It is I, and there is none but me. 11 But evil shall come upon thee--thou shalt not know from whence it riseth; and mischief shall fall upon thee, which thou shalt not be able to ward off; and desolation that thou suspectest not shall come upon thee suddenly. 12 Stand now with thine enchantments and with the multitude of thy sorceries, wherein thou hast laboured from thy youth; if so be thou shalt be able to turn them to profit, if so be thou mayest cause terror. 13 Thou art wearied in the multitude of thy counsels. Let now the interpreters of the heavens, the observers of the stars, who predict according to the new moons what shall come upon thee, stand up, and save thee. 14 Behold, they shall be as stubble, the fire shall burn them; they shall not deliver themselves from the power of the flame: there shall not be a coal to warm at, nor fire to sit before it. 15 Thus shall they be unto thee with whom thou hast laboured, they that trafficked with thee from thy youth: they shall wander every one to his own quarter; there is none to save thee.

Isaiah 49

1 Listen, O isles, unto me; and hearken, ye peoples from afar. Jehovah hath called me from the womb; from the bowels of my mother hath he made mention of my name. 2 And he hath made my mouth like a sharp sword, he hath concealed me under the shadow of his hand, and he hath made me a polished shaft: in his quiver hath he hidden me. 3 And he said unto me, Thou art my servant, Israel, in whom I will glorify myself. 4 --And I said, I have laboured in vain, I have spent my strength for nought and in vain; nevertheless my judgment is with Jehovah, and my work with my God[*] 5 And now, saith Jehovah, that formed me from the womb to be his servant, that I should bring Jacob again to him; (though Israel be not gathered, yet shall I be glorified in the eyes of Jehovah, and my God[*] shall be my strength;) 6 --and he saith, It is a small thing that thou shouldest be my servant to raise up the tribes of Jacob, and to restore the preserved of Israel; I have even given thee for a light of the nations, that thou mayest be my salvation unto the end of the earth.

7 Thus saith Jehovah, the Redeemer of Israel, his Holy One, to him whom man despiseth, to him whom the nation abhorreth, to the servant of rulers: Kings shall see and arise, princes, and they shall worship, because of Jehovah who is faithful, the Holy One of Israel, who hath chosen thee. 8 Thus saith Jehovah: In a time of acceptance have I answered thee, and in the day of salvation have I helped thee; and I will preserve thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, to establish the land, to cause to inherit the desolate heritages; 9 saying to the prisoners, Go forth; to them that are in darkness, Shew yourselves. They shall feed in the ways, and their pasture shall be on all bare hills. 10 They shall not hunger nor thirst, neither shall the heat nor sun smite them; for he that hath mercy on them will lead them, and by the springs of water will he guide them. 11 And I will make all my mountains a way, and my highways shall be raised up. 12 Behold, these shall come from afar; and behold, these from the north and from the west; and these from the land of Sinim.

13 Shout, ye heavens; and be joyful, thou earth; and break forth into singing, ye mountains: for Jehovah hath comforted his people, and will have mercy upon his afflicted ones. 14 But Zion said, Jehovah hath forsaken me, and the Lord hath forgotten me. 15 Can a woman forget her sucking child, that she should not have compassion on the son of her womb? Even these forget, but I will not forget thee. 16 Lo, I have graven thee upon the palms of my hands; thy walls are continually before me. 17 Thy sons shall make haste; thy destroyers and they that laid thee waste shall go forth from thee.

18 Lift up thine eyes round about and behold: they all gather themselves together, they come to thee. As I live, saith Jehovah, thou shalt indeed clothe thee with them all as with an ornament, and bind them on as a bride doth. 19 For in thy waste and thy desolate places, and thy destroyed land, thou shalt even now be too straitened by reason of the inhabitants, and they that swallowed thee up shall be far away. 20 The children of thy bereavement shall yet say in thine ears, The place is too narrow for me: make room for me, that I may dwell. 21 And thou shalt say in thy heart, Who hath borne me these, seeing I had lost my children and was desolate, an exile, and driven about? and who hath brought up these? behold, I was left alone; these, where were they? 22 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will lift up my hand to the nations, and set up my banner to the peoples; and they shall bring thy sons in their bosom, and thy daughters shall be carried upon the shoulder. 23 And kings shall be thy nursing-fathers, and their princesses thy nursing-mothers: they shall bow down to thee with the face toward the earth, and lick up the dust of thy feet. And thou shalt know that I am Jehovah; for they shall not be ashamed who wait on me.

24 Shall the prey be taken from the mighty? and shall he that is rightfully captive be delivered? 25 For thus saith Jehovah: Even the captive of the mighty shall be taken away, and the prey of the terrible shall be delivered; and I will strive with him that striveth with thee, and I will save thy children. 26 And I will feed them that oppress thee with their own flesh; and they shall be drunken with their own blood, as with new wine. And all flesh shall know that I, Jehovah, am thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the Mighty One of Jacob.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 50

1 Thus saith Jehovah: Where is the bill of your mother's divorce, whom I have put away? or which of my creditors is it to whom I have sold you? Behold, through your iniquities have ye sold yourselves, and for your transgressions is your mother put away. 2 Wherefore did I come, and there was no man? I called, and there was none to answer? Is my hand at all shortened that I cannot redeem, or have I no power to deliver? behold, at my rebuke I dry up the sea, I make rivers a wilderness; their fish stink because there is no water, and die for thirst. 3 I clothe the heavens with blackness, and I make sackcloth their covering.

4 The Lord Jehovah hath given me the tongue of the instructed, that I should know how to succour by a word him that is weary. He wakeneth morning by morning, he wakeneth mine ear to hear as the instructed. 5 The Lord Jehovah hath opened mine ear, and I was not rebellious; I turned not away back. 6 I gave my back to smiters, and my cheeks to them that plucked off the hair; I hid not my face from shame and spitting. 7 But the Lord Jehovah will help me: therefore shall I not be confounded; therefore have I set my face like a flint, and I know that I shall not be ashamed. 8 He is near that justifieth me: who will contend with me? let us stand together; who is mine adverse party? let him draw near unto me. 9 Behold, the Lord Jehovah will help me; who is he that shall condemn me? Behold, they all shall grow old as a garment; the moth shall eat them up.

10 Who is among you that feareth Jehovah, that hearkeneth to the voice of his servant? he that walketh in darkness, and hath no light, --let him confide in the name of Jehovah, and stay himself upon his God[*] 11 Behold, all ye that kindle a fire, that compass yourselves about with sparks: walk in the light of your fire, and among the sparks that ye have kindled. This shall ye have of my hand: ye shall lie down in sorrow.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 53

1 Who hath believed our report? and to whom hath the arm of Jehovah been revealed? 2 For he shall grow up before him as a tender sapling, and as a root out of dry ground: he hath no form nor lordliness, and when we see him, there is no beauty that we should desire him. 3 He is despised and left alone of men; a man of sorrows, and acquainted with grief, and like one from whom men hide their faces; --despised, and we esteemed him not.

4 Surely he hath borne our griefs and carried our sorrows; and we, we did regard him stricken, smitten of God[*] and afflicted. 5 But he was wounded for our transgressions, he was bruised for our iniquities; the chastisement of our peace was upon him, and with his stripes we are healed. 6 All we like sheep have gone astray, we have turned every one to his own way; and Jehovah hath laid upon him the iniquity of us all. 7 He was oppressed, and he was afflicted, but he opened not his mouth; he was led as a lamb to the slaughter, and was as a sheep dumb before her shearers, and he opened not his mouth. 8 He was taken from oppression and from judgment; and who shall declare his generation? for he was cut off out of the land of the living; for the transgression of my people was he stricken. 9 And men appointed his grave with the wicked, but he was with the rich in his death, because he had done no violence, neither was there guile in his mouth.

10 Yet it pleased Jehovah to bruise him; he hath subjected him to suffering. When thou shalt make his soul an offering for sin, he shall see a seed, he shall prolong his days, and the pleasure of Jehovah shall prosper in his hand. 11 He shall see of the fruit of the travail of his soul, and shall be satisfied: by his knowledge shall my righteous servant instruct many in righteousness; and he shall bear their iniquities. 12 Therefore will I assign him a portion with the great, and he shall divide the spoil with the strong: because he hath poured out his soul unto death, and was reckoned with the transgressors; and he bore the sin of many, and made intercession for the transgressors.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 54

1 Exult, thou barren, that didst not bear; break forth into singing, and shout for joy, thou that didst not travail with child: for more are the children of the desolate than the children of the married wife, saith Jehovah. 2 Enlarge the place of thy tent, and let them stretch forth the curtains of thy habitations: spare not, lengthen thy cords, and strengthen thy stakes. 3 For thou shalt spread abroad on the right hand and on the left; and thy seed shall possess nations, and they shall make desolate cities to be inhabited. 4 Fear not, for thou shalt not be ashamed; neither be thou confounded, for thou shalt not be put to shame: for thou shalt forget the shame of thy youth, and shalt not remember the reproach of thy widowhood any more. 5 For thy Maker is thy husband: Jehovah of hosts is his name, and thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel: the God[*] of the whole earth shall he be called.

6 For Jehovah hath called thee as a woman forsaken and grieved in spirit, and as a wife of youth, that hath been refused, saith thy God[*] 7 For a small moment have I forsaken thee; but with great mercies will I gather thee. 8 In the outpouring of wrath have I hid my face from thee for a moment; but with everlasting loving-kindness will I have mercy on thee, saith Jehovah, thy Redeemer. 9 For this is as the waters of Noah unto me, since I have sworn that the waters of Noah should no more go over the earth: so have I sworn that I will no more be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee. 10 For the mountains shall depart, and the hills be removed; but my loving-kindness shall not depart from thee, neither shall my covenant of peace be removed, saith Jehovah, that hath mercy on thee.

11 Thou afflicted, tossed with tempest, not comforted! Behold, I will set thy stones in antimony, and lay thy foundations with sapphires; 12 and I will make thy battlements of rubies, and thy gates of carbuncles, and all thy borders of precious stones. 13 And all thy children shall be taught of Jehovah, and great shall be the peace of thy children. 14 In righteousness shalt thou be established: thou shalt be far from oppression, for thou shalt not fear; and from terror, for it shall not come near thee. 15 Behold, they shall surely gather together, but not by me: whosoever gathereth together against thee shall fall because of thee. 16 Behold, it is I who have created the smith that bloweth in the fire of coal, and that bringeth forth an instrument for his work; and I have created the destroyer to ravage. 17 No weapon that is prepared against thee shall prosper; and every tongue that riseth against thee in judgment, thou shalt condemn. This is the inheritance of the servants of Jehovah; and their righteousness is of me, saith Jehovah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 57

1 The righteous perisheth, and no man layeth it to heart; and merciful men are taken away, none considering that the righteous is taken away from before the evil. 2 He entereth into peace: they rest in their beds, each one that hath walked in his uprightness.

3 But draw near hither, ye sons of the sorceress, the seed of the adulterer and the harlot. 4 Against whom do ye sport yourselves? Against whom do ye make a wide mouth, and draw out the tongue? Are ye not children of transgression, a seed of falsehood, 5 inflaming yourselves with idols under every green tree, slaying the children in the valleys under the clefts of the rocks? 6 Among the smooth stones of the torrent is thy portion; they, they are thy lot: even to them hast thou poured out a drink-offering, thou hast offered an oblation. Shall I be comforted myself as to these things? 7 Upon a lofty and high mountain hast thou set thy bed: even thither didst thou go up to offer sacrifice. 8 Behind the doors also and the posts hast thou set up thy remembrance: for apart from me, thou hast uncovered thyself, and art gone up; thou hast enlarged thy bed, and hast made agreement with them; thou lovedst their bed, thou sawest their nakedness. 9 And thou wentest to the king with ointment, and didst multiply thy perfumes, and didst send thy messengers afar off, and didst debase thyself unto Sheol. 10 Thou wast wearied by the multitude of thy ways; but thou saidst not, It is of no avail. Thou didst find a quickening of thy strength; therefore thou wast not sick of it. 11 And of whom hast thou been afraid or feared, that thou hast lied, and hast not remembered me, nor taken it to heart? Have not I even of long time held my peace, and thou fearest me not? 12 I will declare thy righteousness, and thy works; and they shall not profit thee.

13 When thou criest, let them that are gathered by thee deliver thee! But a wind shall carry them all away, a breath shall take them; but he that putteth his trust in me shall inherit the land, and possess my holy mountain. 14 And it shall be said, Cast up, cast up, prepare the way, take up the stumbling-blocks out of the way of my people. 15 For thus saith the high and lofty One that inhabiteth eternity, and whose name is Holy: I dwell in the high and holy place, and with him that is of a contrite and humble spirit, to revive the spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones. 16 For I will not contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth; for the spirit would fail before me, and the souls which I have made.

17 For the iniquity of his covetousness was I wroth, and smote him; I hid me, and was wroth, and he went on backslidingly in the way of his heart. 18 I have seen his ways, and will heal him; and I will lead him, and will restore comforts unto him and to those of his that mourn. 19 I create the fruit of the lips: peace, peace to him that is afar off, and to him that is nigh, saith Jehovah; and I will heal him. 20 But the wicked are like the troubled sea, which cannot rest, and whose waters cast up mire and dirt. 21 There is no peace, saith my God[*] to the wicked.

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 58

1 Cry aloud, spare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet, and declare unto my people their transgression, and to the house of Jacob their sins. 2 Yet they seek me daily, and delight to know my ways, as a nation that doeth righteousness, and hath not forsaken the ordinance of their God[*] they ask of me the ordinances of righteousness, they take delight in approaching to God[*]

3 --Wherefore have we fasted, and thou seest not; have afflicted our soul, and thou takest no knowledge? Behold, in the day of your fast ye find what pleaseth you, and exact all your labours. 4 Behold, ye have fasted for strife and debate, and to smite with the fist of wickedness; ye do not at present fast, to cause your voice to be heard on high. 5 Is such the fast that I have chosen, a day for a man to afflict his soul, --that he should bow down his head as a bulrush, and spread sackcloth and ashes under him? Wilt thou call this a fast, and a day acceptable to Jehovah? 6 Is not this the fast which I have chosen: to loose the bands of wickedness, to undo the thongs of the yoke, and to send forth free the crushed, and that ye break every yoke? 7 Is it not to deal thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring to thy house the needy wanderers; when thou seest the naked, that thou cover him; and that thou hide not thyself from thine own flesh?

8 Then shall thy light break forth as the dawn, and thy health shall spring forth speedily; and thy righteousness shall go before thee, the glory of Jehovah shall be thy rearguard. 9 Then shalt thou call, and Jehovah will answer; thou shalt cry, and he will say, Here I am. If thou take away from the midst of thee the yoke, the putting forth of the finger and the unjust speech, 10 and thou proffer thy soul to the hungry, and satisfy the afflicted soul: then shall thy light rise in the darkness, and thine obscurity be as midday; 11 and Jehovah will guide thee continually, and satisfy thy soul in drought, and strengthen thy bones; and thou shalt be like a watered garden, and like a water-spring, whose waters deceive not. 12 And they that come of thee shall build the old waste places: thou shalt raise up the foundations that have remained from generation to generation; and thou shalt be called, Repairer of the breaches, restorer of frequented paths.

13 If thou turn back thy foot from the sabbath, from doing thy pleasure on my holy day, and call the sabbath a delight, the holy day of Jehovah, honourable; and thou honour him, not doing thine own ways, nor finding thine own pleasure, nor speaking idle words; 14 then shalt thou delight thyself in Jehovah, and I will cause thee to ride on the high places of the earth, and feed thee with the heritage of Jacob thy father: for the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 59

1 Behold, Jehovah's hand is not shortened that it cannot save, neither his ear heavy that it cannot hear; 2 but your iniquities have separated between you and your God[*] and your sins have hid his face from you, that he doth not hear. 3 For your hands are stained with blood, and your fingers with iniquity; your lips speak lies, your tongue muttereth unrighteousness: 4 none calleth for justice, none pleadeth in truthfulness. They trust in vanity, and speak falsehood; they conceive mischief, and bring forth iniquity. 5 They hatch serpents' eggs, and weave the spider's web: he that eateth of their eggs dieth, and that which is crushed breaketh out into a viper. 6 Their webs shall not become garments, neither shall they cover themselves with their works; their works are works of iniquity, and the act of violence is in their hands. 7 Their feet run to evil, and they make haste to shed innocent blood; their thoughts are thoughts of iniquity; wasting and destruction are in their paths; 8 the way of peace they know not, and there is no judgment in their goings; they have made their paths crooked: whoso goeth therein knoweth not peace.

9 Therefore is justice far from us, and righteousness overtaketh us not: we wait for light, and behold darkness; for brightness, but we walk in obscurity. 10 We grope for the wall like the blind, and we grope as if we had no eyes: we stumble at midday as in the twilight; amongst the flourishing we are as the dead. 11 We roar all like bears, and mourn grievously like doves: we look for judgment, and there is none; for salvation, but it is far from us. 12 For our transgressions are multiplied before thee, and our sins testify against us; for our transgressions are with us; and our iniquities, we know them: 13 in transgressing and lying against Jehovah, and departing away from our God[*] speaking oppression and revolt, conceiving and uttering from the heart words of falsehood. 14 And judgment is turned away backward, and righteousness standeth afar off; for truth stumbleth in the street, and uprightness cannot enter. 15 And truth faileth; and he that departeth from evil maketh himself a prey. And Jehovah saw it, and it was evil in his sight that there was no judgment.

16 And he saw that there was no man, and he wondered that there was no intercessor; and his arm brought him salvation, and his righteousness, it sustained him. 17 And he put on righteousness as a breastplate, and a helmet of salvation upon his head; and he put on garments of vengeance for clothing, and was clad with zeal as a cloak. 18 According to deeds, so will he repay: fury to his adversaries, recompence to his enemies; to the islands he will repay recompence. 19 And they shall fear the name of Jehovah from the west, and from the rising of the sun, his glory. When the adversary shall come in like a flood, the Spirit of Jehovah will lift up a banner against him. 20 And the Redeemer will come to Zion, and unto them that turn from transgression in Jacob, saith Jehovah. 21 And as for me, this is my covenant with them, saith Jehovah: My spirit that is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy seed, nor out of the mouth of thy seed's seed, saith Jehovah, from henceforth and for ever.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 60

1 Arise, shine! for thy light is come, and the glory of Jehovah is risen upon thee. 2 For behold, darkness shall cover the earth, and gross darkness the peoples; but Jehovah will arise upon thee, and his glory shall be seen on thee. 3 And the nations shall walk by thy light, and kings by the brightness of thy rising. 4 Lift up thine eyes round about, and see: all they gather themselves together, they come to thee: thy sons come from afar, and thy daughters are carried upon the side. 5 Then thou shalt see, and shalt be brightened, and thy heart shall throb, and be enlarged; for the abundance of the sea shall be turned unto thee, the wealth of the nations shall come unto thee. 6 A multitude of camels shall cover thee, young camels of Midian and Ephah; all they from Sheba shall come: they shall bring gold and incense; and they shall publish the praises of Jehovah. 7 All the flocks of Kedar shall be gathered unto thee, the rams of Nebaioth shall serve thee: they shall come up with acceptance on mine altar, and I will beautify the house of my magnificence. 8 Who are these that come flying as a cloud, and as doves to their dove-cotes?

9 For the isles shall await me, and the ships of Tarshish first, to bring thy sons from afar, their silver and their gold with them, unto the name of Jehovah thy God[*] and to the Holy One of Israel, for he hath glorified thee. 10 And the sons of the alien shall build up thy walls, and their kings shall minister unto thee. For in my wrath I smote thee, but in my favour have I had mercy on thee. 11 And thy gates shall stand open continually: (they shall not be shut day nor night,) that the wealth of the nations may be brought unto thee, and that their kings may be led to thee. 12 For the nation and the kingdom that will not serve thee shall perish; and those nations shall be utterly wasted. 13 The glory of Lebanon shall come unto thee, the cypress, pine, and box-tree together, to beautify the place of my sanctuary; and I will make the place of my feet glorious. 14 And the children of them that afflicted thee shall come bending unto thee; and all they that despised thee shall bow themselves down at the soles of thy feet; and they shall call thee The city of Jehovah, the Zion of the Holy One of Israel.

15 Instead of thy being forsaken and hated, so that no one went through thee, I will make thee an eternal excellency, a joy from generation to generation. 16 And thou shalt suck the milk of the nations, and shalt suck the breast of kings; and thou shalt know that I, Jehovah, am thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the Mighty One of Jacob. 17 For bronze I will bring gold, and for iron I will bring silver, and for wood bronze, and for stones iron; and I will make thine officers peace, and thy rulers righteousness. 18 Violence shall no more be heard in thy land, wasting nor destruction within thy borders; but thou shalt call thy walls Salvation, and thy gates Praise. 19 The sun shall be no more thy light by day, neither for brightness shall the moon give light unto thee; but Jehovah shall be thine everlasting light, and thy God[*] thy glory. 20 Thy sun shall no more go down, neither shall thy moon withdraw itself; for Jehovah shall be thine everlasting light, and the days of thy mourning shall be ended. 21 Thy people also shall be all righteous: they shall possess the land for ever--the branch of my planting, the work of my hands, that I may be glorified. 22 The little one shall become a thousand, and the smallest a mighty nation: I, Jehovah, will hasten it in its time.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 62

1 For Zion's sake will I not hold my peace, and for Jerusalem's sake I will not be still, until her righteousness go forth as brightness, and her salvation as a torch that burneth. 2 And the nations shall see thy righteousness, and all kings thy glory; and thou shalt be called by a new name, which the mouth of Jehovah will name. 3 And thou shalt be a crown of beauty in the hand of Jehovah, and a royal diadem in the hand of thy God[*] 4 Thou shalt no more be termed, Forsaken; neither shall thy land any more be termed, Desolate: but thou shalt be called, My delight is in her, and thy land, Married; for Jehovah delighteth in thee, and thy land shall be married. 5 For as a young man marrieth a virgin, shall thy sons marry thee; and with the joy of the bridegroom over the bride, shall thy God[*] rejoice over thee.

6 I have set watchmen upon thy walls, Jerusalem; all the day and all the night they shall never hold their peace: ye that put Jehovah in remembrance, keep not silence, 7 and give him no rest, till he establish, and till he make Jerusalem a praise in the earth. 8 Jehovah hath sworn by his right hand and by the arm of his strength, I will indeed no more give thy corn to be food for thine enemies; and the sons of the alien shall not drink thy new wine, for which thou hast laboured; 9 for they that have garnered it shall eat it, and praise Jehovah; and they that have gathered it shall drink it in the courts of my holiness.

10 Go through, go through the gates; prepare the way of the people; cast up, cast up the highway; gather out the stones; lift up a banner for the peoples. 11 Behold, Jehovah hath proclaimed unto the end of the earth, Say ye to the daughter of Zion, Behold, thy salvation cometh; behold, his reward is with him, and his recompence before him. 12 And they shall call them, The holy people, The redeemed of Jehovah; and thou shalt be called, The sought out, The city not forsaken.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 63

1 Who is this that cometh from Edom, with deep-red garments from Bozrah, this that is glorious in his apparel, travelling in the greatness of his strength? --I that speak in righteousness, mighty to save. 2 --Wherefore is redness in thine apparel, and thy garments like him that treadeth in the winevat? 3 I have trodden the winepress alone, and of the peoples not a man was with me; and I have trodden them in mine anger, and trampled them in my fury; and their blood is sprinkled upon my garments, and I have stained all mine apparel. 4 For the day of vengeance was in my heart, and the year of my redeemed had come. 5 And I looked, and there was none to help; and I wondered that there was none to uphold: and mine own arm brought salvation unto me; and my fury, it upheld me. 6 And I have trodden down the peoples in mine anger, and made them drunk in my fury; and their blood have I brought down to the earth.

7 I will record the loving-kindnesses of Jehovah, the praises of Jehovah, according to all that Jehovah hath bestowed upon us, and the great goodness toward the house of Israel which he hath bestowed upon them according to his mercies, and according to the multitude of his loving-kindnesses. 8 And he said, They are indeed my people, children that will not lie; and he became their Saviour. 9 In all their affliction he was afflicted, and the Angel of his presence saved them: in his love and in his pity he redeemed them; and he bore them and carried them all the days of old. 10 But they rebelled and grieved his holy Spirit: and he turned to be their enemy; himself, he fought against them. 11 But he remembered the days of old, Moses and his people: Where is he that brought them up out of the sea with the shepherds of his flock? Where is he that put his holy Spirit within him, 12 his glorious arm leading them by the right hand of Moses, dividing the waters before them, to make himself an everlasting name, 13 --who led them through the depths, like a horse in the wilderness, and they stumbled not? 14 As cattle go down into the valley, the Spirit of Jehovah gave them rest; so didst thou lead thy people, to make thyself a glorious name.

15 Look down from the heavens, and behold from the habitation of thy holiness and of thy glory! Where is thy zeal and thy strength, the sounding of thy bowels and of thy tender mercies? Are they restrained toward me? 16 For thou art our Father, though Abraham be ignorant of us, and Israel acknowledge us not: thou, Jehovah, art our Father; our Redeemer, from everlasting, is thy name. 17 Why, O Jehovah, hast thou made us to err from thy ways, hast hardened our heart from thy fear? Return for thy servants' sake, the tribes of thine inheritance. 18 Thy holy people have possessed it but a little while: our adversaries have trodden down thy sanctuary. 19 We have become like those over whom thou never barest rule, those not called by thy name.

Isaiah 64

1 Oh, that thou wouldest rend the heavens, that thou wouldest come down, --that the mountains might flow down at thy presence, 2 --as fire kindleth brushwood, as the fire causeth water to boil, to make thy name known to thine adversaries, that the nations might tremble at thy presence! 3 When thou didst terrible things which we looked not for, thou camest down, and the mountains flowed down at thy presence. 4 Never have men heard, nor perceived by the ear, nor hath eye seen a God[*] beside thee, who acteth for him that waiteth for him. 5 Thou meetest him that rejoiceth to do righteousness, those that remember thee in thy ways: (behold, thou wast wroth, and we have sinned:) in those is perpetuity, and we shall be saved.

6 And we are all become as an unclean thing, and all our righteousnesses are as filthy rags; and we all fade as a leaf, and our iniquities, like the wind, have carried us away; 7 and there is none that calleth upon thy name, that stirreth up himself to take hold of thee; for thou hast hidden thy face from us, and hast caused us to melt away through our iniquities. 8 And now, Jehovah, thou art our Father; we are the clay, and thou our potter; and we all are the work of thy hand. 9 Be not wroth very sore, O Jehovah, neither remember iniquity for ever. Behold, see, we beseech thee, we are all thy people. 10 Thy holy cities are become a wilderness, Zion is a wilderness, Jerusalem a desolation. 11 Our holy and our beautiful house, where our fathers praised thee, is burnt up with fire, and all our precious things are laid waste. 12 Wilt thou restrain thyself in presence of these things, Jehovah? Wilt thou hold thy peace, and afflict us very sore?

Hebrew: Elohim

Isaiah 66

1 Thus saith Jehovah: The heavens are my throne, and the earth is my footstool: what is the house that ye will build unto me? and what is the place of my rest? 2 Even all these things hath my hand made, and all these things have been, saith Jehovah. But to this man will I look: to the afflicted and contrite in spirit, and who trembleth at my word. 3 He that slaughtereth an ox, smiteth a man; he that sacrificeth a lamb, breaketh a dog's neck; he that offereth an oblation, it is as swine's blood; he that presenteth a memorial of incense, is as he that blesseth an idol. As they have chosen their own ways, and their soul delighteth in their abominations, 4 I also will choose their calamities, and will bring their fears upon them; because I called, and none answered, I spoke, and they did not hear, but did that which was evil in mine eyes, and chose that wherein I delight not.

5 Hear the word of Jehovah, ye that tremble at his word: Your brethren that hated you, that cast you out for my name's sake, said, Let Jehovah be glorified, and let us see your joy! but they shall be ashamed. 6 A voice of tumult from the city, a voice from the temple, a voice of Jehovah that rendereth recompence to his enemies! 7 Before she travailed, she brought forth; before her pain came, she was delivered of a man-child. 8 Who hath heard such a thing? who hath seen such things? Can a land be made to bring forth in one day? shall a nation be born at once? For as soon as Zion travailed, she brought forth her sons. 9 Shall I bring to the birth, and not cause to bring forth? saith Jehovah; I who cause to bring forth, shall I shut the womb? saith thy God[*] 10 Rejoice with Jerusalem, and be glad for her, all ye that love her; rejoice for joy with her, all ye that mourn over her: 11 because ye shall suck, and be satisfied with the breasts of her consolations; because ye shall drink out, and be delighted with the abundance of her glory. 12 For thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I will extend peace to her like a river, and the glory of the nations like an overflowing torrent; and ye shall suck, ye shall be carried upon the side, and be dandled upon the knees. 13 As one whom his mother comforteth, so will I comfort you; and ye shall be comforted in Jerusalem. 14 And ye shall see this, and your heart shall rejoice, and your bones shall flourish like the grass; and the hand of Jehovah shall be known toward his servants, and he will have indignation toward his enemies.

15 For behold, Jehovah will come with fire, and his chariots like a whirlwind, to render his anger with fury, and his rebuke with flames of fire. 16 For by fire and by his sword will Jehovah enter into judgment with all flesh: and the slain of Jehovah shall be many. 17 They that sanctify themselves, and purify themselves in the gardens behind one in the midst; that eat swine's flesh, and the abomination, and the mouse, shall perish together, saith Jehovah. 18 And I, --their works and their thoughts are before me. ... The time cometh for the gathering of all nations and tongues; and they shall come, and see my glory. 19 And I will set a sign among them, and I will send those that escape of them unto the nations, to Tarshish, Pul, and Lud, that draw the bow; to Tubal and Javan, to the isles afar off, that have not heard my fame, neither have seen my glory: and they shall declare my glory among the nations. 20 And they shall bring all your brethren out of all the nations as an oblation unto Jehovah, upon horses, and in chariots, and in covered waggons, and upon mules, and upon dromedaries, to my holy mountain, to Jerusalem, saith Jehovah, as the children of Israel bring an oblation in a clean vessel into the house of Jehovah. 21 And I will also take of them for priests and for Levites, saith Jehovah. 22 For as the new heavens and the new earth which I will make shall remain before me, saith Jehovah, so shall your seed and your name remain. 23 And it shall come to pass from new moon to new moon, and from sabbath to sabbath, all flesh shall come to worship before me, saith Jehovah. 24 And they shall go forth, and look upon the carcases of the men that have transgressed against me: for their worm shall not die, neither shall their fire be quenched; and they shall be an abhorrence unto all flesh.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 1

1 The words of Jeremiah the son of Hilkijah, of the priests that were in Anathoth in the land of Benjamin: 2 to whom the word of Jehovah came in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah, in the thirteenth year of his reign; 3 it came also in the days of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, unto the end of the eleventh year of Zedekiah the son of Josiah, king of Judah, unto the carrying away of Jerusalem captive, in the fifth month.

4 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 5 Before I formed thee in the belly I knew thee; and before thou camest forth out of the womb I hallowed thee, I appointed thee a prophet unto the nations. 6 And I said, Alas, Lord Jehovah! behold, I cannot speak; for I am a child. 7 But Jehovah said unto me, Say not, I am a child; for thou shalt go to whomsoever I shall send thee, and whatsoever I command thee thou shalt speak. 8 Be not afraid of them; for I am with thee to deliver thee, saith Jehovah. 9 And Jehovah put forth his hand and touched my mouth; and Jehovah said unto me, Behold, I have put my words in thy mouth. 10 See, I have this day set thee over the nations and over the kingdoms, to pluck up, and to break down, and to destroy, and to overthrow, to build and to plant.

11 And the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, Jeremiah, what seest thou? And I said, I see a rod of an almond-tree. 12 And Jehovah said unto me, Thou hast well seen; for I am watchful over my word to perform it. 13 And the word of Jehovah came to me the second time, saying, What seest thou? And I said, I see a seething-pot, and its face is from the north. 14 And Jehovah said unto me, Out of the north shall evil break forth upon all the inhabitants of the land. 15 For behold, I am calling all the families of the kingdoms of the north, saith Jehovah, and they shall come, and they shall set every one his throne at the entering of the gates of Jerusalem, and against all the walls thereof round about, and against all the cities of Judah: 16 and I will pronounce my judgments against them for all their wickedness, in that they have forsaken me, and have burned incense unto other gods, and worshipped the works of their own hands. 17 Thou, therefore, gird up thy loins, and arise, and speak unto them all that I shall command thee: be not dismayed at them, lest I cause thee to be dismayed before them. 18 And I, behold, I appoint thee this day as a strong city, and an iron pillar, and brazen walls, against the whole land; against the kings of Judah, against its princes, against its priests, and against the people of the land. 19 And they shall fight against thee, but they shall not prevail against thee: for I am with thee, saith Jehovah, to deliver thee.

Jeremiah 2

1 And the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, 2 Go and cry in the ears of Jerusalem, saying, Thus saith Jehovah: I remember for thee the kindness of thy youth, the love of thine espousals, when thou wentest after me in the wilderness, in a land not sown. 3 Israel was holiness unto Jehovah, the first-fruits of his increase: all that devour him are guilty; evil shall come upon them, saith Jehovah. 4 Hear the word of Jehovah, house of Jacob, and all the families of the house of Israel. 5 Thus saith Jehovah: What injustice have your fathers found in me, that they are gone far from me, and have walked after vanity, and become vain? 6 And they said not, Where is Jehovah, that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, that led us in the wilderness, in a land of deserts and of pits, in a land of drought and of the shadow of death, in a land that no one passeth through, and where no man dwelleth? 7 And I brought you into a fruitful land, to eat the fruit thereof and the good thereof; and ye entered and defiled my land, and made my heritage an abomination. 8 The priests said not, Where is Jehovah? and they that handled the law knew me not; and the shepherds transgressed against me; and the prophets prophesied by Baal, and walked after things that do not profit.

9 Therefore will I yet plead with you, saith Jehovah, and with your children's children will I plead. 10 For pass over to the isles of Chittim, and see; and send unto Kedar, and consider diligently, and see if there have been such a thing. 11 Hath a nation changed its gods? and they are no gods; --but my people have changed their glory for that which doth not profit. 12 Be astonished, ye heavens, at this, and shudder; be amazed very much, saith Jehovah. 13 For my people have committed two evils: they have forsaken me, the fountain of living waters, to hew them out cisterns, broken cisterns that hold no water.

14 Is Israel a bondman? Is he a home-born slave? Why is he become a spoil? 15 The young lions roared against him, they gave forth their voice, and they made his land desolate: his cities are burned, without inhabitant. 16 Even the children of Noph and Tahapanes have fed on the crown of thy head. 17 Hast thou not procured this unto thyself, in that thou hast forsaken Jehovah thy God[*] at the time he was leading thee in the way? 18 And now, what hast thou to do with the way of Egypt, to drink the waters of Shihor? And what hast thou to do with the way of Assyria, to drink the waters of the River? 19 Thine own wickedness chastiseth thee, and thy backslidings reprove thee: know then and see that it is an evil thing and bitter that thou hast forsaken Jehovah thy God[*] and that my fear is not in thee, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts.

20 For of old thou hast broken thy yoke, and burst thy bands; and thou saidst, I will not serve. For upon every high hill, and under every green tree, thou bowest down, playing the harlot. 21 And I, --I had planted thee a noble vine, wholly a right seed; how then art thou turned into the degenerate shoots of a strange vine unto me? 22 For though thou wash thee with nitre, and take thee much potash, thine iniquity is marked before me, saith the Lord Jehovah. 23 How sayest thou, I am not defiled, I have not gone after the Baals? See thy way in the valley, acknowledge what thou hast done--a swift dromedary traversing her ways! 24 --a wild ass, used to the wilderness, that snuffeth up the wind in her desire! In her ardour, who shall turn her away? All they that seek her will not weary themselves; in her month they shall find her. 25 Withhold thy foot from being unshod, and thy throat from thirst. But thou saidst, There is no hope; no, for I love strangers, and after them will I go. 26 As a thief is ashamed when he is found, so shall the house of Israel be ashamed--they, their kings, their princes, and their priests, and their prophets-- 27 saying to a stock, Thou art my father; and to a stone, Thou hast brought me forth; for they have turned the back unto me, and not the face; and in the time of their trouble they will say, Arise, and save us! 28 Where then are thy gods that thou hast made for thyself? let them arise, if they can save thee in the time of thy trouble: for as the number of thy cities, are thy gods, O Judah.

29 Wherefore would ye contend with me? Ye all have transgressed against me, saith Jehovah. 30 In vain have I smitten your children: they received no correction. Your own sword hath devoured your prophets, like a destroying lion. 31 O generation, mark ye the word of Jehovah. Have I been a wilderness unto Israel, or a land of thick darkness? Wherefore say my people, We have dominion; we will come no more unto thee? 32 Doth a virgin forget her ornaments, a bride her attire? But my people have forgotten me days without number. 33 How dost thou trim thy way to seek love! Therefore hast thou also accustomed thy ways to wickedness. 34 Yea, in thy skirts is found the blood of the souls of the innocent poor, whom thou didst not encounter breaking in, but it is found upon all these. 35 And thou sayest, Indeed I am innocent; his anger will turn from me. Behold, I will enter into judgment with thee because thou sayest, I have not sinned. 36 Why dost thou gad about so much, and change thy way? Thou shalt also be brought to shame by Egypt, as thou wast brought to shame by Assyria. 37 Thou shalt indeed go forth from her with thy hands upon thy head; for Jehovah hath rejected those thou confidest in, and thou shalt not prosper by them.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 4

1 If thou wilt return, O Israel, saith Jehovah, return unto me; and if thou wilt put away thine abominations out of my sight, then shalt thou not be a wanderer; 2 --and thou shalt in truth, in justice, and in righteousness swear, As Jehovah liveth! and the nations shall bless themselves in him, and in him shall they glory.

3 For thus saith Jehovah to the men of Judah and Jerusalem: Break up for you a fallow ground, and sow not among thorns. 4 Circumcise yourselves for Jehovah, and take away the foreskins of your heart, ye men of Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem; lest my fury come forth like fire and burn, and there be none to quench it, because of the evil of your doings.

5 Declare ye in Judah, and cause it to be heard in Jerusalem, and say, ...and blow the trumpet in the land, cry aloud and say, Assemble yourselves, and let us enter into the fenced cities. 6 Set up a banner toward Zion; take to flight, stay not! For I am bringing evil from the north, and a great destruction. 7 The lion is come up from his thicket, the destroyer of the nations is on his way; he is gone forth from his place, to make thy land desolate; thy cities shall be laid waste, without inhabitant. 8 For this, gird you with sackcloth, lament and howl! for the fierce anger of Jehovah is not turned away from us. 9 And it shall come to pass in that day, saith Jehovah, that the heart of the king shall perish, and the heart of the princes; and the priests shall be astonished, and the prophets shall be amazed. 10 And I said, Alas, Lord Jehovah! surely thou hast greatly deceived this people and Jerusalem, saying, Ye shall have peace; whereas the sword reacheth unto the soul. 11 At that time shall it be said to this people and to Jerusalem, A hot wind cometh from the heights in the wilderness, on the way of the daughter of my people, not for fanning, nor for cleansing. 12 A wind more vehement than that shall come from me: now will I also pronounce judgments against them. 13 Behold, he cometh up as clouds, and his chariots are as a whirlwind; his horses are swifter than eagles. Woe unto us! for we are destroyed. 14 Wash thy heart, Jerusalem, from wickedness, that thou mayest be saved. How long shall thy vain thoughts lodge within thee? 15 For a voice declareth from Dan, and publisheth affliction from mount Ephraim. 16 Inform the nations; behold, make Jerusalem to hear: Besiegers come from a far country, and raise their voice against the cities of Judah. 17 As keepers of a field are they against her round about; for she hath been rebellious against me, saith Jehovah. 18 Thy way and thy doings have procured these things unto thee; this is thy wickedness, yea, it is bitter, yea, it reacheth unto thy heart.

19 My bowels! my bowels! I am in travail! Oh, the walls of my heart! My heart maketh a noise in me; I cannot hold my peace: for thou hearest, my soul, the sound of the trumpet, the clamour of war. 20 Destruction upon destruction is proclaimed; for the whole land is wasted: suddenly are my tents laid waste, my curtains, in a moment. 21 How long shall I see the standard, and hear the sound of the trumpet? 22 For my people is foolish, they have not known me; they are sottish children, and they have no intelligence; they are wise to do evil, but to do good they have no knowledge. 23 I beheld the earth, and lo, it was waste and empty; and the heavens, and they had no light. 24 I beheld the mountains, and lo, they trembled, and all the hills shook violently. 25 I beheld, and lo, man was not, and all the fowl of the heavens were fled. 26 I beheld, and lo, the fruitful land was a wilderness, and all the cities thereof were broken down, before Jehovah, before his fierce anger. 27 For thus saith Jehovah: The whole land shall be a desolation; but I will not make a full end. 28 For this shall the earth mourn, and the heavens above be black; because I have spoken it, I have purposed it, and will not repent, neither will I turn back therefrom. 29 At the noise of the horsemen and bowmen, every city fleeth; they go into the thickets, and climb up upon the rocks: every city is forsaken and no man dwelleth therein. 30 --And thou, wasted one, what wilt thou do? Though thou clothest thyself with crimson, though thou deckest thee with ornaments of gold, though thou rendest thine eyes with paint, in vain dost thou make thyself fair: thy lovers despise thee, they seek thy life. 31 For I hear a voice, as of a woman in travail, anguish as of her that bringeth forth her first child, the voice of the daughter of Zion: she moaneth, she spreadeth forth her hands, saying, Woe unto me! for my soul faileth because of murderers.

Jeremiah 6

1 Flee for safety, ye children of Benjamin, out of the midst of Jerusalem, and blow the trumpet in Tekoa, and set up a signal in Beth-haccerem; for evil appeareth out of the north, and a great destruction. 2 The comely and delicate one do I cut off, the daughter of Zion. 3 Shepherds with their flocks shall come unto her; they shall pitch their tents against her round about; they shall feed every one in his place. 4 Prepare war against her. Arise, and let us go up at noon. Woe unto us! for the day hath declined, for the shadows of the evening are lengthening. 5 Arise, and let us go up by night, and let us destroy her palaces. 6 For thus hath Jehovah of hosts said: Hew ye down trees, and cast a mound against Jerusalem. She is the city to be visited; she is wholly oppression in the midst of her. 7 As a well poureth forth her waters, so she poureth forth her wickedness: violence and destruction are heard in her; before me continually are grief and wounds. 8 Be thou instructed, Jerusalem, lest my soul be alienated from thee; lest I make thee a desolation, a land not inhabited.

9 Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: They shall thoroughly glean like a vine the remnant of Israel: turn back thy hand, as a grape-gatherer unto the baskets. 10 To whom shall I speak and testify, that they may hear? Behold, their ear is uncircumcised, and they cannot hearken: behold, the word of Jehovah is unto them a reproach; they have no delight in it. 11 And I am full of the fury of Jehovah, I am weary with holding in. Pour it out upon the children in the street, and upon the assembly of young men together: for even the husband with the wife shall be taken; the aged with him that is full of days. 12 And their houses shall be turned unto others, their fields and wives together; for I will stretch out my hand upon the inhabitants of the land, saith Jehovah. 13 For from the least of them even unto the greatest of them, every one is given to covetousness; and from the prophet even unto the priest, every one dealeth falsely. 14 And they have healed the breach of the daughter of my people lightly, saying, Peace, peace! when there is no peace. 15 Are they ashamed that they have committed abomination? Nay, they are not at all ashamed, neither know they what it is to blush. Therefore they shall fall among them that fall; at the time that I visit them they shall stumble, saith Jehovah. 16 Thus saith Jehovah: Stand in the ways and see, and ask for the ancient paths, which is the good way, and walk therein, and ye shall find rest for your souls. But they said, We will not walk therein. 17 Also I have set watchmen over you: --Hearken ye to the sound of the trumpet. But they said, We will not hearken.

18 Therefore hear, ye nations, and know, O assembly, what is among them. 19 Hear, O earth: behold, I will bring evil upon this people, the fruit of their thoughts; for they have not hearkened unto my words, and as to my law, they have rejected it. 20 To what purpose should there come to me incense from Sheba, and the sweet cane from a far country? Your burnt-offerings are not acceptable, nor are your sacrifices pleasing unto me. 21 Therefore thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I will lay stumbling-blocks before this people, and the fathers and the sons together shall fall over them; the neighbour and his friend shall perish. 22 Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, a people cometh from the north country, and a great nation is stirred up from the uttermost parts of the earth. 23 They lay hold on bow and spear; they are cruel, and have no mercy; their voice roareth like the sea; and they ride upon horses, set in array as a man for the battle, against thee, daughter of Zion. 24 We have heard the report thereof: our hands are grown feeble; anguish hath taken hold of us, pain as of a woman that travaileth. 25 Go not forth into the field, nor walk by the way; for there is the sword of the enemy, terror is on every side. 26 Daughter of my people, gird thee with sackcloth, and roll thyself in ashes: make mourning, as for an only son--bitter lamentation; for the spoiler cometh suddenly upon us. 27 I have set thee among my people as an assayer, a fortress, that thou mayest know and try their way. 28 They are all the most rebellious of rebels, going about with slander: they are bronze and iron; they are all corrupters. 29 The bellows are burned, the lead is consumed by the fire; they have melted, and melted in vain; and the bad are not plucked away. 30 Reprobate silver shall they call them, for Jehovah hath rejected them.

Jeremiah 8

1 At that time, saith Jehovah, they shall bring forth the bones of the kings of Judah, and the bones of his princes, and the bones of the priests, and the bones of the prophets, and the bones of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, out of their graves; 2 and they shall spread them out to the sun and to the moon and to all the host of the heavens, which they have loved, and which they have served, and after which they have walked, and which they have sought, and which they have worshipped: they shall not be gathered, nor be buried; they shall be for dung upon the face of the ground. 3 And death shall be chosen rather than life by all the residue that remain of this evil family, in all the places whither I have driven those that remain, saith Jehovah of hosts.

4 And thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith Jehovah: Do men fall, and not rise up? Doth one turn away, and not return? 5 Why hath this people of Jerusalem slidden back with a perpetual backsliding? They hold fast deceit, they refuse to return. 6 I hearkened and heard: they speak not what is right; there is no man who repenteth him of his wickedness, saying, What have I done? Every one turneth to his course, like a horse rushing into the battle. 7 Even a stork in the heavens knoweth her appointed times, and the turtle-dove and the swallow and the crane observe the time of their coming; but my people know not the judgment of Jehovah. 8 How do ye say, We are wise, and the law of Jehovah is with us? Behold, certainly the lying pen of the scribes hath made it falsehood. 9 The wise men are ashamed, they are dismayed and taken: behold, they have rejected Jehovah's word; and what wisdom is in them? 10 Therefore will I give their wives unto others, their fields to those that shall possess them; for every one, from the least even unto the greatest, is given to covetousness; from the prophet even unto the priest, every one dealeth falsely. 11 And they have healed the breach of the daughter of my people lightly, saying, Peace, peace! when there is no peace. 12 Are they ashamed that they have committed abomination? Nay, they are not at all ashamed, and they know not how to blush. Therefore shall they fall among them that fall: in the time of their visitation they shall stumble, saith Jehovah.

13 I will utterly take them away, saith Jehovah: there are no grapes on the vine, nor figs on the fig-tree; and the leaf is faded: and I will give them up to those that shall pass over them. 14 Why do we sit still? Assemble yourselves, and let us enter into the fenced cities, and let us be silent there: for Jehovah our God[*] hath put us to silence, and given us water of gall to drink, because we have sinned against Jehovah. 15 Peace is looked for, and there is no good; a time of healing, and behold, terror. 16 The snorting of his horses is heard from Dan: the whole land trembleth at the sound of the neighing of his steeds, and they come, and devour the land, and all it contains, the city and those that dwell therein. 17 For behold, I send among you serpents, vipers against which there is no charm, and they shall bite you, saith Jehovah. 18 My comfort in my sadness! my heart is faint in me! 19 Behold the voice of the cry of the daughter of my people, from a very far country: Is not Jehovah in Zion? Is not her king in her? Why have they provoked me to anger with their graven images, with foreign vanities? 20 The harvest is past, the summer is ended, and we are not saved. 21 --For the breach of the daughter of my people am I crushed; I go mourning; astonishment hath taken hold of me. 22 Is there no balm in Gilead? is there no physician there? Why then is there no dressing applied for the healing of the daughter of my people?

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 9

1 Oh that my head were waters, and mine eye a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for the slain of the daughter of my people! 2 Oh that I had in the wilderness a traveller's lodging-place, that I might leave my people, and go away from them! For they are all adulterers, an assembly of treacherous men. 3 And they bend their tongue, their bow of falsehood, and not for fidelity are they valiant in the land; for they proceed from evil to evil, and they know not me, saith Jehovah. 4 Take ye heed every one of his friend, and confide not in any brother; for every brother only supplanteth, and every friend goeth about with slander. 5 And they act deceitfully every one with his neighbour, and speak not the truth: they teach their tongue to speak falsehood, they weary themselves with perverse dealing. 6 Thy habitation is in the midst of deceit; through deceit they refuse to know me, saith Jehovah. 7 Therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Behold, I will melt them, and try them; for how else could I do for the daughter of my people? 8 Their tongue is a murderous arrow; it speaketh deceit. A man speaketh peaceably to his neighbour with his mouth, but in his heart he layeth his ambush. 9 Shall I not visit them for these things? saith Jehovah; shall not my soul be avenged on such a nation as this? 10 For the mountains will I take up weeping and wailing, and for the pastures of the wilderness, a lamentation; for they are burnt up, so that none passeth through them; and the voice of the cattle is not heard. Both the fowl of the heavens and the beasts are fled; they are gone. 11 And I will make Jerusalem heaps, a dwelling-place of jackals; and I will make the cities of Judah a desolation, without inhabitant.

12 Who is a wise man, that he may understand this? and he to whom the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken, that he may declare it? Why is the land perished, burnt up like a wilderness, so that none passeth through? 13 And Jehovah saith, Because they have forsaken my law which I set before them, and have not hearkened unto my voice, nor walked in it, 14 but have walked after the stubbornness of their own heart, and after the Baals, as their fathers taught them; 15 therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God[*] of Israel, Behold, I will feed this people with wormwood, and give them water of gall to drink, 16 and will scatter them among the nations, whom neither they nor their fathers have known; and I will send the sword after them, till I have consumed them. 17 Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Consider, and call for the mourning women, that they may come, and send for the skilful women, that they may come; 18 and let them make haste, and take up a wailing for us, that our eyes may run down with tears, and our eyelids pour forth waters. 19 For a voice of wailing is heard out of Zion, How are we spoiled, sorely put to shame! For we have forsaken the land, for they have cast down our dwellings. 20 Hear then the word of Jehovah, ye women, and let your ear receive the word of his mouth, and teach your daughters wailing, and each one her companion lamentation. 21 For death is come up through our windows, is entered into our palaces, to cut off the children from the street, the young men from the broadways. 22 Speak, Thus saith Jehovah: Yea, the carcases of men shall fall as dung upon the open field, and as the handful after the reaper, and there shall be none to gather.

23 Thus saith Jehovah: Let not the wise glory in his wisdom, neither let the mighty glory in his might; let not the rich glory in his riches: 24 but let him that glorieth glory in this, that he understandeth and knoweth me, that I am Jehovah, who exercise loving-kindness, judgment, and righteousness in the earth; for in these things I delight, saith Jehovah. 25 Behold, days are coming, saith Jehovah, when I will visit all them that are circumcised with the uncircumcised; 26 Egypt, and Judah, and Edom, and the children of Ammon, and Moab, and all that have the corners of their beard cut off, that dwell in the wilderness: for all the nations are uncircumcised, and all the house of Israel are uncircumcised in heart.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 12

1 Righteous art thou, Jehovah, when I plead with thee; yet will I speak with thee of thy judgments. Wherefore doth the way of the wicked prosper? wherefore are all they at ease that deal very treacherously? 2 Thou hast planted them, they also have taken root: they advance, yea, they bring forth fruit: thou art near in their mouth, but far from their reins. 3 But thou, Jehovah, knowest me; thou hast seen me, and proved my heart toward thee. Drag them out like sheep for the slaughter, and set them apart for the day of slaughter. 4 How long shall the land mourn, and the herbs of all the fields wither? Because of the wickedness of them that dwell therein, the beasts and the birds perish; for they say, He will not see our end. 5 If thou hast run with footmen, and they have wearied thee, how wilt thou then contend with horses? And if in a land of peace thou thinkest thyself in security, how wilt thou then do in the swelling of the Jordan? 6 For even thy brethren, and the house of thy father, even they have dealt treacherously with thee, even they have cried aloud after thee. Believe them not, though they speak good words unto thee.

7 I have forsaken my house, I have cast off my heritage, I have given the beloved of my soul into the hand of her enemies. 8 My heritage is become unto me as a lion in the forest; it hath raised its voice against me: therefore have I hated it. 9 My heritage is unto me as a speckled bird of prey; the birds of prey round about are against her. Go, assemble all the beasts of the field, bring them to devour. 10 Many shepherds have destroyed my vineyard, they have trodden my portion under foot, they have made my pleasant portion a desolate wilderness: 11 they have made it a desolation; desolate, it mourneth unto me: the whole land is made desolate, for no man layeth it to heart. 12 Spoilers are come upon all heights in the wilderness; for the sword of Jehovah devoureth from one end of the land even to the other end of the land: no flesh hath peace. 13 They have sown wheat, and they reap thorns; they have put themselves to pain, and do not profit. Be ye therefore ashamed of your revenues, because of the fierce anger of Jehovah.

14 Thus saith Jehovah against all mine evil neighbours, that touch the inheritance which I have caused my people Israel to inherit: Behold, I will pluck them up out of their land, and pluck out the house of Judah from among them. 15 And it shall come to pass, after I have plucked them up, I will return, and have compassion on them, and will bring them back, each one to his inheritance, and each one to his land. 16 And it shall come to pass, if they will diligently learn the ways of my people, to swear by my name, as Jehovah liveth--even as they taught my people to swear by Baal--they shall be built up in the midst of my people. 17 And if they will not obey, I will utterly pluck up and destroy that nation, saith Jehovah.

Jeremiah 14

1 The word of Jehovah that came to Jeremiah concerning the drought. 2 Judah mourneth, and the gates thereof languish, they are black unto the ground; and the cry of Jerusalem goeth up. 3 And their nobles send their little ones for water: they come to the pits, they find no water; they return with their vessels empty; they are ashamed, they are confounded, and have covered their heads. 4 Because the ground is chapt, for there hath been no rain on the earth, the ploughmen are ashamed, they cover their heads. 5 For the hind also calveth in the field, and forsaketh its young, because there is no grass. 6 And the wild asses stand on the heights, they snuff up the wind like jackals; their eyes fail, because there is no herbage. 7 Jehovah, though our iniquities testify against us, do thou act for thy name's sake; for our backslidings are many--we have sinned against thee. 8 Thou hope of Israel, its Saviour in the time of trouble, why wilt thou be as a stranger in the land, and as a traveller that turneth aside to stay a night? 9 Why wilt thou be as a man astonished, as a mighty man that cannot save? Yet thou, Jehovah, art in the midst of us, and we are called by thy name: leave us not.

10 Thus saith Jehovah to this people: Even so have they loved to wander, they have not refrained their feet; and Jehovah hath no delight in them: now will he remember their iniquity, and visit their sins. 11 And Jehovah said unto me, Pray not for this people for their good. 12 When they fast, I will not hear their cry; and when they offer up burnt-offering and oblation, I will not accept them: for I will consume them by sword, and by famine, and by pestilence. 13 And I said, Alas, Lord Jehovah! Behold, the prophets say unto them, Ye shall not see the sword, neither shall ye have famine; for I will give you assured peace in this place. 14 And Jehovah said unto me, The prophets prophesy falsehood in my name; I have not sent them, neither have I commanded them, nor spoken unto them: they prophesy unto you a false vision, and divination, and a thing of nought, and the deceit of their heart. 15 Therefore thus saith Jehovah concerning the prophets that prophesy in my name, and I sent them not, and who say, Sword and famine shall not be in this land: By sword and by famine shall those prophets be consumed; 16 and the people to whom they prophesy shall be cast out in the streets of Jerusalem, because of the famine and the sword; and there shall be none to bury them, them, their wives, and their sons, and their daughters; and I will pour their wickedness upon them.

17 And thou shalt say this word unto them: Let mine eyes run down with tears, night and day, and not cease; for the virgin daughter of my people is broken with a great breach, with a very grievous blow. 18 If I go forth into the field, behold the slain with the sword! and if I enter into the city, behold them that pine away with famine! For both prophet and priest shall go about into a land that they know not. 19 --Hast thou then utterly rejected Judah? Doth thy soul loathe Zion? Why hast thou smitten us, and there is no healing for us? Peace is looked for, and there is no good, --and a time of healing, and behold terror! 20 Jehovah, we acknowledge our wickedness, the iniquity of our fathers; for we have sinned against thee. 21 For thy name's sake, do not spurn us, do not disgrace the throne of thy glory: remember, break not thy covenant with us. 22 Are there any among the vanities of the nations that can cause rain? or can the heavens give showers? Art not thou HE, Jehovah, our God[*] And we wait upon thee; for thou hast made all these things.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 15

1 And Jehovah said unto me, Though Moses and Samuel stood before me, my soul would not turn toward this people. Send them out of my sight, and let them go forth. 2 And it shall come to pass, if they say unto thee, Whither shall we go forth? then thou shalt tell them, Thus saith Jehovah: Such as are for death, to death; and such as are for the sword, to the sword; and such as are for the famine, to the famine; and such as are for captivity, to captivity. 3 For I will visit them with four kinds of punishments, saith Jehovah: the sword to slay, and dogs to tear, and the fowl of the heavens, and the beasts of the earth, to devour and to destroy. 4 And I will give them over to be driven hither and thither amongst all the kingdoms of the earth, because of Manasseh the son of Hezekiah, king of Judah, for that which he did in Jerusalem. 5 For who shall have pity upon thee, Jerusalem? and who shall bemoan thee? and who shall turn aside to ask after thy welfare? 6 Thou hast cast me off, saith Jehovah, thou art gone backward; and I have stretched out my hand against thee, and will destroy thee: I am become weary of repenting. 7 And I will fan them with a fan in the gates of the land; I will bereave of children and destroy my people: they have not returned from their ways. 8 Their widows are increased to me more than the sand of the seas; I have brought upon them, against the mother of the young men, a spoiler at noonday; I have caused anguish and terror to fall upon her suddenly. 9 She that hath borne seven languisheth, she hath given up the ghost; her sun is gone down while it is yet day; she is put to shame and confounded. And the residue of them will I give up to the sword before their enemies, saith Jehovah.

10 Woe is me, my mother, that thou hast borne me a man of strife and a man of contention to the whole land! I have not lent on usury, nor have they lent to me on usury; yet every one of them doth curse me. 11 Jehovah said, Verily I will set thee free for thy good; verily I will cause the enemy to meet thee kindly in the time of evil and in the time of affliction. 12 Will iron break? iron from the north? and bronze? 13 Thy substance and thy treasures will I give to the spoil without price, and that for all thy sins, and in all thy borders; 14 and I will make them to pass with thine enemies into a land that thou knowest not: for a fire is kindled in mine anger; it shall burn upon you.

15 Jehovah, thou knowest: remember me, and visit me, and avenge me of my persecutors; in thy long-suffering take me not away: know that for thy sake I bear reproach. 16 Thy words were found, and I did eat them, and thy words were unto me the joy and rejoicing of my heart; for I am called by thy name, O Jehovah, God[*] of hosts. 17 I sat not in the assembly of the mockers, nor exulted: I sat alone because of thy hand; for thou hast filled me with indignation. 18 Why is my pain perpetual, and my wound incurable? It refuseth to be healed. Wilt thou be altogether unto me as a treacherous spring, as waters that fail? 19 Therefore thus saith Jehovah: If thou return, then will I bring thee again, thou shalt stand before me; and if thou take forth the precious from the vile, thou shalt be as my mouth. Let them return unto thee; but return not thou unto them. 20 And I will make thee unto this people a strong brazen wall; and they shall fight against thee, but they shall not prevail against thee: for I am with thee, to save thee and to deliver thee, saith Jehovah; 21 yea, I will deliver thee out of the hand of the wicked, and I will redeem thee out of the hand of the terrible.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 17

1 The sin of Judah is written with a style of iron, with the point of a diamond, engraven upon the tablet of their heart, and upon the horns of your altars; 2 whilst their children remember their altars and their Asherahs, by the green trees, upon the high hills. 3 My mountain in the field, thy substance, all thy treasures will I give for a spoil, --thy high places, because of sin throughout thy borders. 4 And of thyself thou shalt let go thine inheritance which I gave thee; and I will cause thee to serve thine enemies in a land that thou knowest not; for ye have kindled a fire in mine anger, --it shall burn for ever.

5 Thus saith Jehovah: Cursed is the man that confideth in man, and maketh flesh his arm, and whose heart departeth from Jehovah. 6 And he shall be like the heath in the desert, and shall not see when good cometh; but he shall inhabit the parched places in the wilderness, a salt land and not inhabited. 7 Blessed is the man that confideth in Jehovah, and whose confidence Jehovah is. 8 For he shall be like a tree planted by the waters, and that spreadeth out its roots by the stream, and he shall not see when heat cometh, but his leaf shall be green; and in the year of drought he shall not be careful, neither shall he cease to yield fruit. 9 The heart is deceitful above all things, and incurable; who can know it? 10 I Jehovah search the heart, I try the reins, even to give each one according to his ways, according to the fruit of his doings. 11 As the partridge sitteth on eggs it hath not laid, so is he that getteth riches and not by right: in the midst of his days shall he leave them, and at his end shall be a fool.

12 A throne of glory, set on high from the beginning, is the place of our sanctuary. 13 Thou hope of Israel, Jehovah! all that forsake thee shall be ashamed. They that depart from me shall be written in the earth; because they have forsaken Jehovah, the fountain of living waters. 14 Heal me, Jehovah, and I shall be healed; save me, and I shall be saved: for thou art my praise. 15 Behold, these say unto me, Where is the word of Jehovah? let it then come! 16 But as for me, I have not hastened from being a shepherd in following thee, neither have I desired the fatal day, thou knowest: that which came out of my lips was before thy face. 17 Be not a terror unto me: thou art my refuge in the day of evil. 18 Let them be ashamed that persecute me, but let not me be ashamed; let them be dismayed, but let not me be dismayed; bring upon them the day of evil, and break them with a double breaking.

19 Thus hath Jehovah said unto me: Go and stand in the gate of the children of the people, by which the kings of Judah come in, and by which they go out, and in all the gates of Jerusalem; 20 and say unto them, Hear the word of Jehovah, ye kings of Judah, and all Judah, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, that enter in by these gates; 21 thus saith Jehovah: Take heed to your souls, and bear no burden on the sabbath day, and bring nothing in through the gates of Jerusalem; 22 and carry forth no burden out of your houses on the sabbath day, neither do any work; but hallow ye the sabbath day, as I commanded your fathers, 23 but they hearkened not, neither inclined their ear, but hardened their neck, that they might not hear nor receive instruction. 24 And it shall come to pass, if ye diligently hearken unto me, saith Jehovah, to bring in no burden through the gates of this city on the sabbath day, and to hallow the sabbath day, to do no work therein; 25 then shall there enter in, through the gates of this city, kings and princes sitting upon the throne of David, riding in chariots and on horses, they and their princes, the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem: and this city shall be inhabited for ever. 26 And they shall come from the cities of Judah, and from the places around Jerusalem, and from the land of Benjamin, and from the lowland, and from the hill-country, and from the south, bringing burnt-offerings, and sacrifices, and oblations, and incense, and bringing thanksgiving unto the house of Jehovah. 27 But if ye will not hearken unto me, to hallow the sabbath day and not to bear a burden and enter in through the gates of Jerusalem on the sabbath day, then will I kindle a fire in the gates thereof, and it shall devour the palaces of Jerusalem, and it shall not be quenched.

Jeremiah 18

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying, 2 Arise and go down to the potter's house, and there I will cause thee to hear my words. 3 And I went down to the potter's house; and behold, he wrought a work on the wheels. 4 And the vessel that he made was marred, as clay, in the hand of the potter; and he made it again another vessel, as seemed good to the potter to make. 5 And the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, 6 House of Israel, cannot I do with you as this potter? saith Jehovah. Behold, as the clay in the potter's hand, so are ye in my hand, house of Israel. 7 At the moment that I speak concerning a nation and concerning a kingdom, to pluck up, and to break down, and to destroy, 8 if that nation, concerning which I have spoken, turn from their evil, then I will repent of the evil that I thought to do unto them. 9 And at the moment that I speak concerning a nation and concerning a kingdom, to build and to plant, 10 if it do evil in my sight, that it hearken not unto my voice, then I will repent of the good wherewith I said I would benefit them.

11 And now, speak to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying, Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I prepare evil against you, and devise a device against you: turn ye then every one from his evil way, and amend your ways and your doings. 12 But they say, There is no hope; for we will walk after our own devices, and we will each one do according to the stubbornness of his evil heart. 13 Therefore thus saith Jehovah: Ask ye now among the nations, Who hath heard such things? The virgin of Israel hath done a very horrible thing. 14 Shall the snow of Lebanon cease from the rock of the field? Shall the cool flowing waters coming from afar be dried up? 15 For my people hath forgotten me: they burn incense to vanity; and they have caused them to stumble in their ways, the ancient paths, to walk in by-paths of a way not cast up; 16 to make their land an astonishment, a perpetual hissing: every one that passeth by shall be astonished, and shake his head. 17 As with an east wind will I scatter them before the enemy; I will shew them the back, and not the face, in the day of their calamity.

18 And they said, Come, and let us devise devices against Jeremiah; for law shall not perish from the priest, nor counsel from the wise, nor word from the prophet. Come and let us smite him with the tongue, and let us not give heed to any of his words. 19 Jehovah, give heed to me, and listen to the voice of those that contend with me. 20 Shall evil be recompensed for good? For they have digged a pit for my soul. Remember how I stood before thee to speak good for them, to turn away thy wrath from them. 21 Therefore give up their children to the famine, and deliver them over to the power of the sword; and let their wives be bereaved of children and be widows; and let their men be swept off by death, their young men be smitten by the sword in battle. 22 Let a cry be heard from their houses, when thou shalt bring a troop suddenly upon them; for they have digged a pit to take me, and have hidden snares for my feet. 23 And thou, Jehovah, knowest all their counsel against me to slay me. Forgive not their iniquity, neither blot out their sin from thy sight, but let them be overthrown before thee: deal with them in the time of thine anger.

Jeremiah 20

1 And Pashur the son of Immer, the priest--and he was chief officer in the house of Jehovah--heard Jeremiah prophesy these things. 2 And Pashur smote Jeremiah the prophet, and put him in the stocks that were in the upper gate of Benjamin, which was in the house of Jehovah. 3 And it came to pass the next day, that Pashur brought forth Jeremiah out of the stocks; and Jeremiah said unto him, Jehovah hath not called thy name Pashur, but Magor-missabib. 4 For thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I make thee a terror to thyself, and to all thy friends; and they shall fall by the sword of their enemies, and thine eyes shall see it; and I will give all Judah into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall carry them captive into Babylon, and shall smite them with the sword. 5 And, I will give all the wealth of this city, and all its gains, and all its precious things, and all the treasures of the kings of Judah, will I give into the hand of their enemies; and they shall make them a prey, and take them, and carry them to Babylon. 6 And thou, Pashur, and all that dwell in thy house shall go into captivity; and thou shalt come to Babylon, and there thou shalt die, and there thou shalt be buried, thou and all thy friends to whom thou hast prophesied falsehood.

7 Jehovah, thou hast enticed me, and I was enticed; thou hast laid hold of me, and hast prevailed; I am become a derision the whole day: every one mocketh me. 8 For as oft as I speak, I cry out; I proclaim violence and spoil; for the word of Jehovah is become unto me a reproach and a derision all the day. 9 And I said, I will not make mention of him, nor speak any more in his name: but it was in my heart as a burning fire shut up in my bones; and I became wearied with holding in, and I could not. 10 For I have heard the defaming of many, terror on every side: Report, and we will report it. All my familiars are watching for my stumbling: Peradventure he will be enticed, and we shall prevail against him; and we shall take our revenge on him. 11 But Jehovah is with me as a mighty terrible one; therefore my persecutors shall stumble and shall not prevail; they shall be greatly ashamed, for they have not prospered: it shall be an everlasting confusion that shall not be forgotten. 12 And thou, Jehovah of hosts, who triest the righteous, who seest the reins and the heart, let me see thy vengeance on them; for unto thee have I revealed my cause. 13 Sing ye unto Jehovah, praise Jehovah, for he hath delivered the soul of the needy from the hand of evildoers.

14 Cursed be the day wherein I was born; let not the day wherein my mother bore me be blessed! 15 Cursed be the man who brought tidings to my father, saying, A man child is born unto thee; making him very glad! 16 And let that man be as the cities which Jehovah overthrew, and repented not; and let him hear a cry in the morning, and a shouting at noonday, 17 because he slew me not from the womb. Or would that my mother had been my grave, and her womb always great with me! 18 Wherefore came I forth from the womb to see labour and sorrow, that my days should be consumed in shame?

Jeremiah 21

1 The word that came unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, when king Zedekiah sent unto him Pashur the son of Malchijah, and Zephaniah the son of Maaseiah, the priest, saying, 2 Inquire, I pray thee, of Jehovah for us; for Nebuchadrezzar the king of Babylon maketh war against us; if so be that Jehovah will deal with us according to all his marvellous works, that he may go up from us. 3 And Jeremiah said unto them, Thus shall ye say to Zedekiah: 4 Thus saith Jehovah the God[*] of Israel: Behold, I will turn back the weapons of war that are in your hands, with which ye fight against the king of Babylon, and against the Chaldeans who besiege you, outside the walls, and I will assemble them into the midst of this city. 5 And I myself will fight against you with a stretched-out hand, and with a strong arm, and in anger, and in fury, and in great wrath. 6 And I will smite the inhabitants of this city, both man and beast: they shall die of a great pestilence. 7 And afterwards, saith Jehovah, I will give Zedekiah king of Judah, and his servants, and the people, and such as are left in this city from the pestilence, from the sword, and from the famine, into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar the king of Babylon, and into the hand of their enemies, and into the hand of those that seek their life, and he shall smite them with the edge of the sword: he shall not spare them, neither have pity, nor have mercy.

8 And unto this people thou shalt say, Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I set before you the way of life, and the way of death. 9 He that abideth in this city shall die by the sword, and by the famine, and by the pestilence; but he that goeth out, and deserteth to the Chaldeans that besiege you, he shall live, and his life shall be unto him for a prey. 10 For I have set my face against this city for evil, and not for good, saith Jehovah: it shall be given into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall burn it with fire. 11 And touching the house of the king of Judah, hear ye the word of Jehovah. 12 House of David, thus saith Jehovah: Judge with justice in the morning, and deliver him that is spoiled out of the hand of the oppressor, lest my fury go forth like fire and burn, and there be none to quench it, because of the evil of your doings. 13 Behold, I am against thee, inhabitress of the valley, the rock of the plain, saith Jehovah; ye that say, Who shall come down against us, or who shall enter into our dwellings? 14 And I will visit you according to the fruit of your doings, saith Jehovah; and I will kindle a fire in her forest, and it shall devour all that is round about her.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 22

1 Thus saith Jehovah: Go down to the house of the king of Judah, and speak there this word, 2 and say, Hear the word of Jehovah, O king of Judah, that sittest upon the throne of David, thou, and thy servants, and thy people who enter in through these gates. 3 Thus saith Jehovah: Execute judgment and righteousness, and deliver the spoiled out of the hand of the oppressor; and do no wrong, do no violence to the stranger, the fatherless, or the widow, and shed not innocent blood in this place. 4 For if ye do this thing indeed, then shall there enter in through the gates of this house kings sitting in the place of David upon his throne, riding in chariots and on horses, --he, and his servants, and his people. 5 But if ye will not hear these words, I have sworn by myself, saith Jehovah, that this house shall become a waste. 6 For thus saith Jehovah concerning the house of the king of Judah: Thou art a Gilead unto me, the summit of Lebanon: verily I will make thee a wilderness, cities not inhabited. 7 And I will prepare destroyers against thee, every one with his weapons; and they shall cut down the choice of thy cedars, and cast them into the fire. 8 And many nations shall pass by this city, and they shall say every man to his neighbour, Wherefore hath Jehovah done thus unto this great city? 9 And they shall say, Because they have forsaken the covenant of Jehovah their God[*] and worshipped other gods, and served them.

10 Weep not for the dead, neither bemoan him; but weep sore for him that goeth away, for he shall return no more, nor see his native country. 11 For thus saith Jehovah concerning Shallum the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, who reigned instead of Josiah his father, who went forth out of this place: He shall not return thither any more; 12 for he shall die in the place whither they have led him captive, and shall see this land no more. 13 Woe unto him that buildeth his house by unrighteousness, and his upper chambers by injustice; that taketh his neighbour's service without wages, and giveth him not his earning; 14 that saith, I will build me a wide house, and spacious upper chambers; and he cutteth out for himself windows; and it is wainscoted with cedar, and painted with vermilion. 15 Shalt thou reign, because thou viest with the cedar? Did not thy father eat and drink, and do judgment and justice? Then it was well with him. 16 He judged the cause of the poor and needy; then it was well. Was not this to know me? saith Jehovah. 17 But thine eyes and thy heart are only on thine extortion, and on the blood of the innocent, to shed it, and on oppression and on violence, to do it. 18 Therefore thus saith Jehovah concerning Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, the king of Judah: They shall not lament for him, Ah, my brother! or, Ah, sister! They shall not lament for him, Ah, lord! or Ah, his glory! 19 He shall be buried with the burial of an ass, dragged along and cast forth beyond the gates of Jerusalem.

20 Go up to Lebanon, and cry; and give forth thy voice in Bashan, and cry from the heights of Abarim: for all thy lovers are destroyed. 21 I spoke unto thee in thy prosperity; but thou saidst, I will not hear. This hath been thy way from thy youth, that thou hearkenedst not unto my voice. 22 The wind shall feed on all thy shepherds, and thy lovers shall go into captivity; surely, then shalt thou be ashamed and confounded for all thy wickedness. 23 Thou inhabitress of Lebanon, that makest thy nest in the cedars, how pitiful shalt thou be when pangs come upon thee, pain as of a woman in travail! 24 As I live, saith Jehovah, though Coniah the son of Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, were a signet upon my right hand, yet will I pluck thee thence; 25 and I will give thee into the hand of them that seek thy life, and into the hand of them before whom thou art afraid, even into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of the Chaldeans. 26 And I will cast thee out, and thy mother that bare thee, into another country, where ye were not born; and there shall ye die. 27 And into the land whereunto they lift up their souls to return, thither shall they not return. 28 Is this man Coniah a despised broken vase? a vessel wherein is no delight? Wherefore are they thrown out, he and his seed, and are cast into a land which they know not? 29 O earth, earth, earth, hear the word of Jehovah! 30 Thus saith Jehovah: Write this man childless, a man that shall not prosper in his days; for no man of his seed shall prosper, sitting upon the throne of David, and ruling any more in Judah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 33

1 And the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah the second time, while he was still shut up in the court of the prison, saying, 2 Thus saith Jehovah the doer of it, Jehovah that formeth it to establish it, Jehovah is his name: 3 Call unto me, and I will answer thee, and I will shew thee great and hidden things, which thou knowest not. 4 For thus saith Jehovah the God[*] of Israel concerning the houses of this city, and concerning the houses of the kings of Judah, which are thrown down because of the mounds and because of the sword: 5 They come to fight with the Chaldeans, but to fill them with the dead bodies of the men whom I have slain in mine anger and in my fury, and for all whose wickedness I have hid my face from this city. 6 Behold, I will apply a healing dressing to it and cure, and I will heal them, and will reveal unto them an abundance of peace and truth. 7 And I will turn the captivity of Judah and the captivity of Israel, and will build them, as at the beginning. 8 And I will cleanse them from all their iniquity, whereby they have sinned against me, and I will pardon all their iniquities, whereby they have sinned against me, and whereby they have transgressed against me. 9 And it shall be to me a name of joy, a praise and a glory before all the nations of the earth, which shall hear of all the good that I do unto them; and they shall fear and tremble for all the good and for all the prosperity that I procure unto it.

10 Thus saith Jehovah: In this place of which ye say, It is waste, without man and without beast! in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem that are desolate, without man, and without inhabitant, and without beast, 11 there shall again be heard the voice of mirth and the voice of joy, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, the voice of them that say, Give ye thanks unto Jehovah of hosts; for Jehovah is good, for his loving-kindness endureth for ever, --of them that bring thanksgiving unto the house of Jehovah. For I will turn the captivity of the land as in the beginning, saith Jehovah. 12 Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: In this place which is waste, without man and without beast, and in all the cities thereof, there shall again be a habitation of shepherds causing their flocks to lie down. 13 In the cities of the hill-country, in the cities of the lowland, and in the cities of the south, and in the land of Benjamin, and in the environs of Jerusalem, and in the cities of Judah, shall the flocks pass again under the hands of him that counteth them, saith Jehovah. 14 Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that I will perform the good word which I have spoken unto the house of Israel and unto the house of Judah. 15 In those days, and at that time, will I cause a Branch of righteousness to grow up unto David; and he shall execute judgment and righteousness in the land. 16 In those days shall Judah be saved, and Jerusalem shall dwell in safety. And this is the name wherewith she shall be called: Jehovah our Righteousness.

17 For thus saith Jehovah: There shall never fail to David a man to sit upon the throne of the house of Israel; 18 neither shall there fail to the priests the Levites a man before me to offer up burnt-offerings, and to burn oblations, and to do sacrifice continually. 19 And the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah, saying, 20 Thus saith Jehovah: If ye can break my covenant in respect of the day, and my covenant in respect of the night, so that there should not be day and night in their season, 21 then shall also my covenant be broken with David my servant, that he should not have a son to reign upon his throne; and with the Levites, the priests, my ministers. 22 As the host of the heavens cannot be numbered, nor the sand of the sea measured, so will I multiply the seed of David my servant, and the Levites that minister unto me. 23 And the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah, saying, 24 Hast thou not seen what this people have spoken, saying, The two families that Jehovah had chosen, he hath even cast them off? And they despise my people, that they should be no more a nation before them. 25 Thus saith Jehovah: If my covenant of day and night stand not, if I have not appointed the ordinances of the heavens and the earth, 26 then will I also cast away the seed of Jacob, and of David my servant, so as not to take of his seed to be rulers over the seed of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob: for I will turn their captivity, and will have mercy on them.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 39

1 And it came to pass when Jerusalem was taken, in the ninth year of Zedekiah king of Judah, in the tenth month, came Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon and all his army against Jerusalem, and they besieged it. 2 In the eleventh year of Zedekiah, in the fourth month, on the ninth of the month, the city was broken into; 3 and all the princes of the king of Babylon came in, and sat in the middle gate: Nergal-sharezer, Samgar-nebu, Sarsechim, chief chamberlain, Nergal-sharezer, chief magian, and all the rest of the princes of the king of Babylon. 4 And it came to pass when Zedekiah the king of Judah and all the men of war saw them, that they fled, and went forth out of the city by night, by the way of the king's garden, by the gate between the two walls; and he went out the way of the plain. 5 And the army of the Chaldeans pursued after them, and overtook Zedekiah in the plains of Jericho; and they took him, and brought him up to Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, unto Riblah in the land of Hamath; and he pronounced judgment upon him. 6 And the king of Babylon slaughtered the sons of Zedekiah in Riblah before his eyes, and the king of Babylon slaughtered all the nobles of Judah; 7 and he put out the eyes of Zedekiah, and bound him with chains of brass, to carry him to Babylon. 8 And the Chaldeans burned the king's house and the houses of the people with fire, and broke down the walls of Jerusalem. 9 And Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard carried away captive into Babylon the rest of the people that were left in the city, and the deserters that had deserted to him, with the rest of the people that were left. 10 But Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard left certain of the people, the poor who had nothing, in the land of Judah, and gave them vineyards and fields at the same time.

11 And Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon had given charge concerning Jeremiah by Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard, saying, 12 Take him, and keep an eye upon him, and do him no harm; but do unto him even as he shall say unto thee. 13 So Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard sent, and Nebushazban, chief chamberlain, and Nergal-sharezer, chief magian, and all the king of Babylon's princes, 14 even they sent, and took Jeremiah out of the court of the guard and committed him to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the son of Shaphan, that he should conduct him away home. And he dwelt among the people. 15 And the word of Jehovah came unto Jeremiah, while he was shut up in the court of the guard, saying, 16 Go and speak to Ebed-melech the Ethiopian, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God[*] of Israel: Behold, I will bring my words upon this city for evil, and not for good, and they shall come to pass before thy face in that day. 17 And I will deliver thee in that day, saith Jehovah; and thou shalt not be given into the hand of the men of whom thou art afraid; 18 for I will certainly save thee, and thou shalt not fall by the sword, but thou shalt have thy life for a prey; for thou hast put thy confidence in me, saith Jehovah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 40

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, after that Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard had let him go from Ramah, when he had taken him, being bound in chains, among all the captivity of Jerusalem and Judah, that were carried away captive to Babylon. 2 And the captain of the body-guard took Jeremiah, and said unto him, Jehovah thy God[*] pronounced this evil upon this place, 3 and Jehovah hath brought it about and done according as he said; for ye have sinned against Jehovah, and have not hearkened unto his voice, therefore this thing is come upon you. 4 And now, behold, I loose thee this day from the chains that are upon thy hand. If it seem good in thy sight to come with me to Babylon, come, and I will keep mine eye upon thee; but if it seem ill unto thee to come with me to Babylon, forbear. See, all the land is before thee: whither it seemeth good and right in thy sight to go, thither go. 5 And while he had not yet given answer; he said, Yea, go back to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the son of Shaphan, whom the king of Babylon hath appointed over the cities of Judah, and abide with him in the midst of the people; or go wheresoever it seemeth right in thy sight to go. And the captain of the body-guard gave him provisions and a present, and let him go. 6 And Jeremiah came unto Gedaliah the son of Ahikam to Mizpah, and abode with him among the people that remained in the land.

7 And all the captains of the forces that were in the fields, they and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Gedaliah the son of Ahikam over the land, and had committed unto him men, and women, and children, and of the poor of the land, of them that had not been carried away captive to Babylon. 8 And they came to Gedaliah to Mizpah; even Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and Johanan and Jonathan the sons of Kareah, and Seraiah the son of Tanhumeth, and the sons of Ephai the Netophathite, and Jezaniah the son of a Maachathite, they and their men. 9 And Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the son of Shaphan swore unto them and to their men, saying, Fear not to serve the Chaldeans: dwell in the land, and serve the king of Babylon, and it shall be well with you. 10 And as for me, behold, I dwell at Mizpah, to stand before the Chaldeans, who will come unto us; and ye, gather wine, and summer fruits, and oil, and put them in your vessels, and dwell in your cities which ye have taken. 11 Likewise all the Jews that were in Moab, and among the children of Ammon and in Edom, and that were in all the lands, heard that the king of Babylon had left a remnant in Judah, and that he had appointed over them Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the son of Shaphan; 12 and all the Jews returned out of all the places whither they had been driven, and came to the land of Judah to Gedaliah, unto Mizpah, and gathered wine and summer fruits in great abundance. 13 And Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces that were in the fields, came to Gedaliah unto Mizpah, 14 and said unto him, Dost thou indeed know that Baalis the king of the children of Ammon hath sent Ishmael the son of Nethaniah to smite thee to death? But Gedaliah the son of Ahikam believed them not. 15 And Johanan the son of Kareah spoke to Gedaliah in Mizpah secretly, saying, Let me go, I pray thee, and I will smite Ishmael the son of Nethaniah and no man shall know it: why should he take thy life, and all they of Judah who are gathered unto thee be scattered, and the remnant of Judah perish? 16 But Gedaliah the son of Ahikam said unto Johanan the son of Kareah, Thou shalt not do this thing; for thou speakest falsely of Ishmael.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 46

1 The word of Jehovah that came to Jeremiah the prophet concerning the nations. 2 Of Egypt: concerning the army of Pharaoh-Necho king of Egypt, which was by the river Euphrates at Carchemish, which Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon smote in the fourth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, the king of Judah. 3 Make ready buckler and shield, and draw near to battle! 4 Harness the horses, and mount ye horsemen, and stand forth with helmets; polish the spears, put on the coats of mail! 5 Why do I see them dismayed, turned away back? And their mighty ones are beaten down, and take to flight, and look not back? Terror is on every side, saith Jehovah. 6 Let not the swift flee away, neither let the mighty man escape! --Toward the north, hard by the river Euphrates, they have stumbled and fallen. 7 Who is this that riseth up as the Nile, whose waters toss themselves like the rivers? 8 It is Egypt that riseth up as the Nile, and his waters toss themselves like the rivers; and he saith, I will rise up, I will cover the earth; I will destroy the city and the inhabitants thereof. 9 Go up, ye horses, and drive furiously, ye chariots; and let the mighty men go forth: Cush and Phut that handle the shield, and the Ludim that handle the bow and bend it. 10 For this is the day of the Lord Jehovah of hosts, a day of vengeance, that he may be avenged of his adversaries; and the sword shall devour, and it shall be sated and made drunk with their blood; for the Lord Jehovah of hosts hath a sacrifice in the north country, by the river Euphrates. 11 Go up to Gilead, and fetch balm, O virgin-daughter of Egypt! In vain shalt thou multiply remedies: there is no healing for thee.

12 The nations have heard of thy shame, and thy cry hath filled the earth; for the mighty man stumbleth against the mighty, they are both fallen together. 13 The word that Jehovah spoke to Jeremiah the prophet, concerning the coming of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon to smite the land of Egypt: 14 Declare in Egypt, and publish in Migdol, and publish in Noph, and in Tahpanhes; say, Stand fast, and prepare thee; for the sword devoureth round about thee. 15 Why are thy valiants swept away? They stood not, for Jehovah did thrust them down. 16 He made many to stumble, yea, one fell upon another; and they said, Arise, and let us return to our own people and to the land of our nativity, from the oppressing sword. 17 There did they cry, Pharaoh king of Egypt is but a noise; he hath let the time appointed go by. 18 As I live, saith the King, whose name is Jehovah of hosts, surely as Tabor among the mountains, and as Carmel by the sea, so shall he come. 19 Thou, inhabitress, daughter of Egypt, furnish for thyself a captive's baggage, for Noph shall be a desolation and shall be ruined, so that none shall dwell therein. 20 Egypt is a very fair heifer; the gad-fly cometh, it cometh from the north. 21 Also her hired men in the midst of her are like fatted bullocks; for they also have turned back, they have fled away together, they did not stand; for the day of their calamity is come upon them, the time of their visitation. 22 Her voice shall go like a serpent's; for they shall march with an army, and come against her with axes, as hewers of wood. 23 They shall cut down her forest, saith Jehovah, though it be impenetrable; for they are more than the locusts, and are innumerable. 24 The daughter of Egypt is put to shame; she is delivered into the hand of the people of the north. 25 Jehovah of hosts, the God[*] of Israel, saith, Behold, I will punish Amon of No, and Pharaoh, and Egypt, and her gods, and her kings; yea, Pharaoh and them that confide in him. 26 And I will give them into the hand of those that seek their life, and into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of his servants; but afterwards it shall be inhabited, as in the days of old, saith Jehovah. 27 But thou, my servant Jacob, fear not, neither be dismayed, Israel: for behold, I will save thee from afar, and thy seed from the land of their captivity; and Jacob shall return, and be in rest and at ease, and none shall make himafraid. 28 Fear thou not, my servant Jacob, saith Jehovah: for I am with thee; for I will make a full end of all the nations whither I have driven thee, but I will not make a full end of thee; but I will correct thee with judgment, and I will not hold thee altogether guiltless.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 48

1 Concerning Moab. Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, the God[*] of Israel: Woe unto Nebo! for it is spoiled; Kirjathaim is put to shame, it is taken; Misgab is put to shame and dismayed. 2 Moab's praise is no more; in Heshbon they have devised evil against her: Come, and let us cut her off from being a nation. Thou also, O Madmen, shalt be cut down; the sword shall pursue thee. 3 A voice of crying from Horonaim; wasting and great destruction! 4 Moab is destroyed; her little ones have caused a cry to be heard. 5 For by the ascent of Luhith continual weeping shall go up; for in the descent of Horonaim is heard the anguish of the cry of destruction. 6 Flee, save your lives, and be like a shrub in the wilderness. 7 For because thou hast confided in thy works and in thy treasures, thou also shalt be taken, and Chemosh shall go forth into captivity, his priests and his princes together. 8 And the waster shall come upon every city, that not a city shall escape; and the valley shall perish, and the plateau shall be destroyed: as Jehovah hath said. 9 Give wings unto Moab, that she may flee and get away; and the cities thereof shall become a desolation, without inhabitant. 10 Cursed be he that doeth the work of Jehovah negligently, and cursed be he that keepeth back his sword from blood! 11 Moab hath been at ease from his youth, and hath settled on his lees; he hath not been emptied from vessel to vessel, neither hath he gone into captivity: therefore his taste hath remained in him, and his scent is not changed. 12 Therefore behold, days come, saith Jehovah, that I will send unto him pourers that shall pour him off, and shall empty his vessels, and break in pieces his flagons. 13 And Moab shall be ashamed of Chemosh, as the house of Israel was ashamed of Bethel, their confidence.

14 How do ye say, We are mighty, and men of valour for the war? 15 Moab is laid waste, and his cities are gone up in smoke, and his chosen young men are gone down to the slaughter, saith the King, whose name is Jehovah of hosts. 16 The calamity of Moab is near to come, and his affliction hasteth fast. 17 All ye that are about him, bemoan him; and all ye that know his name, say, How is the strong staff broken, the beautiful rod! 18 Come down from thy glory and sit in the drought, O inhabitress, daughter of Dibon; the spoiler of Moab is come up against thee, thy strongholds hath he destroyed. 19 Stand by the way, and watch, inhabitress of Aroer; ask him that fleeth, and her that escapeth; say, What is done? 20 Moab is put to shame; for he is broken down: howl and cry; tell it in Arnon, that Moab is laid waste. 21 And judgment is come upon the country of the plateau; upon Holon, and upon Jahzah, and upon Mephaath; 22 and upon Dibon, and upon Nebo, and upon Beth-diblathaim; 23 and upon Kirjathaim, and upon Beth-gamul, and upon Beth-meon; 24 and upon Kerijoth, and upon Bozrah, and upon all the cities of the land of Moab, far and near. 25 The horn of Moab is cut off, and his arm is broken, saith Jehovah. 26 Make him drunken, for he magnified himself against Jehovah; and Moab shall wallow in his vomit, and he also shall be in derision. 27 For was not Israel a derision unto thee? Was he found among thieves, that as oft as thou didst speak of him, thou didst shake the head? 28 Leave the cities, and dwell in the rocks, ye inhabitants of Moab, and be like the dove, that maketh her nest in the sides of the cave's mouth. 29 We have heard of the arrogance of Moab, -- he is very proud; --his loftiness, and his arrogance, and his pride, and the haughtiness of his heart. 30 I know his wrath, saith Jehovah; his pratings are vain: they do not as they say. 31 Therefore will I howl for Moab, and I will cry out for all Moab: for the men of Kir-heres shall there be moaning. 32 O vine of Sibmah, I will weep for thee with more than the weeping of Jaazer: thy shoots passed over the sea, they reached to the sea of Jaazer. The spoiler is fallen upon thy summer fruits and upon thy vintage. 33 And joy and gladness is taken away from the fruitful field and from the land of Moab; and I have caused wine to fail from the winepresses: they shall no more tread with shouting; the shouting shall be no shouting. 34 Because of the cry from Heshbon, unto Elaleh, unto Jahaz have they uttered their voice, from Zoar unto Horonaim, unto Eglath-shelishijah: for even the waters of Nimrim shall become desolations. 35 And I will cause to cease in Moab, saith Jehovah, him that offereth in the high place, and him that burneth incense to his gods. 36 Therefore my heart shall sound for Moab like pipes, and my heart shall sound like pipes for the men of Kir-heres; because the abundance that he hath gotten is perished. 37 For every head is bald, and every beard clipped; upon all the hands are cuttings, and upon the loins sackcloth. 38 It is wholly lamentation upon all the housetops of Moab, and in the public places thereof; for I have broken Moab, like a vessel wherein is no pleasure, saith Jehovah. 39 They howl, How is it broken down! how hath Moab turned the back with shame! And Moab shall be a derision and a terror to all that are round about him. 40 For thus saith Jehovah: Behold, he shall fly as an eagle, and shall spread forth his wings over Moab. 41 Kerijoth is taken, and the strongholds are seized, and at that day the heart of the mighty men of Moab shall be as the heart of a woman in her pangs. 42 And Moab shall be destroyed from being a people, because he hath magnified himself against Jehovah. 43 Fear, and the pit, and the snare shall be upon thee, O inhabitant of Moab, saith Jehovah. 44 He that fleeth from the fear shall fall into the pit; and he that getteth up out of the pit shall be taken in the snare: for I will bring upon her, upon Moab, the year of their visitation, saith Jehovah. 45 They that fled stood under the shadow of Heshbon powerless; for a fire hath come forth from Heshbon, and a flame from the midst of Sihon, and hath consumed the corner of Moab, and the crown of the head of the sons of tumult. 46 Woe to thee, Moab! The people of Chemosh is undone; for thy sons are taken away in captivity, and thy daughters are captives. 47 But I will turn the captivity of Moab at the end of the days, saith Jehovah. Thus far is the judgement of Moab.

Hebrew: Elohim

Jeremiah 49

1 Concerning the children of Ammon. Thus saith Jehovah: Hath Israel no sons? hath he no heir? Why is Malcam heir of Gad, and his people dwell in the cities thereof? 2 Therefore behold, days come, saith Jehovah, that I will cause the clamour of war to be heard in Rabbah of the children of Ammon; and it shall be a desolate heap; and her towns shall be burned with fire; and Israel shall possess them that possessed him, saith Jehovah. 3 Howl, Heshbon! for Ai is laid waste; cry, daughters of Rabbah, gird you with sackcloth, lament and run to and fro within the enclosures: for Malcam shall go into captivity, his priests and his princes together. 4 Wherefore gloriest thou in the valleys? Thy valley shall flow down, O backsliding daughter, that trusteth in her treasures, saying, Who shall come against me? 5 Behold, I will bring a fear upon thee, saith the Lord Jehovah of hosts, from all that are about thee; and ye shall be driven out every man right forth; and none shall assemble the fugitives. 6 And afterwards I will turn the captivity of the children of Ammon, saith Jehovah.

7 Concerning Edom. Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Is there no more wisdom in Teman? is counsel perished from the prudent? is their wisdom spent? 8 Flee, turn back, dwell deep down, ye inhabitants of Dedan! For I will bring the calamity of Esau upon him, the time that I visit him. 9 If grape-gatherers had come to thee, would they not have left a gleaning? If thieves by night, they would destroy only till they had enough. 10 But I have made Esau bare, I have uncovered his secret places, that he is unable to hide himself: his seed is wasted, and his brethren, and his neighbours, and he is not. 11 Leave thine orphans, I will preserve them alive; and let thy widows trust in me. 12 For thus saith Jehovah: Behold, they whose judgment was not to drink of the cup shall assuredly drink; and thou indeed, shouldest thou be altogether unpunished? Thou shalt not go unpunished, but thou shalt surely drink. 13 For I have sworn by myself, saith Jehovah, that Bozrah shall become an astonishment, a reproach, a waste, and a curse; and all the cities thereof shall be perpetual wastes. 14 I have heard a rumour from Jehovah, and an ambassador is sent among the nations: --Gather yourselves together, and come against her and rise up for the battle. 15 For behold, I have made thee small among the nations, despised among men. 16 Thy terribleness, the pride of thy heart, hath deceived thee, thou that dwellest in the clefts of the rock, that holdest the height of the hill. Though thou shouldest make thy nest high as the eagle, I will bring thee down from thence, saith Jehovah. 17 And Edom shall be an astonishment: every one that goeth by it shall be astonished, and shall hiss, because of all the plagues thereof. 18 As in the overthrow of Sodom and Gomorrah, and their neighbour cities, saith Jehovah, no one shall dwell there, neither shall a son of man sojourn therein. 19 Behold, he shall come up like a lion from the swelling of the Jordan against the strong habitation; for I will make them suddenly run away from it; and who is a chosen man whom I shall appoint over her? For who is like me? and who will assign me a time? and who is that shepherd that will stand before me? 20 Therefore hear the counsel of Jehovah, which he hath taken against Edom, and his purposes which he hath purposed against the inhabitants of Teman: The little ones of the flock shall certainly draw them away; he shall certainly make their habitation desolate for them. 21 The earth quaketh at the sound of their fall; there is a cry, the sound whereof is heard in the Red sea. 22 Behold, he shall come up, and fly as an eagle, and spread forth his wings against Bozrah; and at that day the heart of the mighty men of Edom shall be as the heart of a woman in her pangs.

23 Concerning Damascus. Hamath is put to shame, and Arpad; for they have heard evil tidings, they are melted away: there is distress on the sea; it cannot be quiet. 24 Damascus is grown feeble: she turneth herself to flee, and terror hath seized on her; trouble and sorrows have taken hold of her as of a woman in travail. 25 How is not the town of praise forsaken, the city of my joy! 26 Therefore shall her young men fall in her streets, and all the men of war be cut off in that day, saith Jehovah of hosts. 27 And I will kindle a fire in the wall of Damascus, and it shall consume the palaces of Ben-Hadad.

28 Concerning Kedar, and concerning the kingdoms of Hazor, which Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon smote. Thus saith Jehovah: Arise, go up to Kedar, and spoil the men of the east. 29 Their tents and their flocks shall they take; their curtains and all their vessels, and their camels, shall they carry away for themselves; and they shall cry unto them, Terror on every side! 30 Flee, wander very far, dwell deep down, ye inhabitants of Hazor, saith Jehovah; for Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon hath taken counsel against you, and hath conceived a purpose against you. 31 Arise, get you up against the nation at ease, that dwelleth securely, saith Jehovah, which hath neither gates nor bars: they dwell alone. 32 And their camels shall be a booty, and the multitude of their cattle a spoil; and I will scatter to every wind them that have the corners of their beard cut off, and I will bring their calamity from all sides thereof, saith Jehovah. 33 And Hazor shall be a dwelling-place of jackals, a desolation for ever. No one shall dwell there, neither shall a son of man sojourn therein.

34 The word of Jehovah that came to Jeremiah the prophet concerning Elam, in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah king of Judah, saying, 35 Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Behold, I will break the bow of Elam, the chief of their might. 36 And upon Elam will I bring the four winds, from the four ends of the heavens, and I will scatter them toward all those winds; and there shall be no nation whither the outcasts of Elam shall not come. 37 And I will cause Elam to be dismayed before their enemies, and before them that seek their life; and I will bring evil upon them, my fierce anger, saith Jehovah; and I will send the sword after them, till I have consumed them. 38 And I will set my throne in Elam, and will destroy from thence king and princes, saith Jehovah. 39 But it shall come to pass at the end of the days, I will turn the captivity of Elam, saith Jehovah.

Jeremiah 52

1 Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem; and his mother's name was Hamutal, daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. 2 And he did evil in the sight of Jehovah, according to all that Jehoiakim had done. 3 For, because the anger of Jehovah was against Jerusalem and Judah, until he had cast them out from his presence, Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon. 4 And it came to pass in the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth of the month, that Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon came, he and all his army, against Jerusalem; and they encamped against it, and built turrets against it round about. 5 And the city was besieged until the eleventh year of king Zedekiah. 6 In the fourth month, on the ninth of the month, the famine prevailed in the city, and there was no bread for the people of the land. 7 And the city was broken into: and all the men of war fled, and went forth out of the city by night, by the way of the gate between the two walls, which was by the king's garden (now the Chaldeans were near the city round about); and they went the way toward the plain. 8 And the army of the Chaldeans pursued after the king, and overtook Zedekiah in the plains of Jericho; and all his army was scattered from him. 9 And they took the king, and brought him up to the king of Babylon, unto Riblah in the land of Hamath, and he pronounced judgment upon him. 10 And the king of Babylon slaughtered the sons of Zedekiah before his eyes; and he slaughtered also all the princes of Judah in Riblah. 11 And he put out the eyes of Zedekiah, and bound him with chains of brass; and the king of Babylon carried him to Babylon, and put him in prison till the day of his death.

12 And in the fifth month, on the tenth of the month, which was in the nineteenth year of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, Nebuzar-adan, captain of the body-guard, who stood before the king of Babylon, came unto Jerusalem; 13 and he burned the house of Jehovah, and the king's house, and all the houses of Jerusalem; and every great man's house he burned with fire. 14 And all the army of the Chaldeans, that were with the captain of the body-guard, broke down all the walls of Jerusalem round about. 15 And Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard carried away captive of the poorest sort of the people, and the rest of the people that were left in the city, and the deserters that had deserted to the king of Babylon, and the rest of the multitude. 16 But Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard left of the poor of the land for vinedressers and for husbandmen. 17 And the brazen pillars that were in the house of Jehovah, and the bases, and the brazen sea that was in the house of Jehovah, the Chaldeans broke up, and carried all the brass thereof to Babylon. 18 The pots also, and the shovels, and the knives, and the bowls, and the cups, and all the vessels of brass wherewith they ministered, they took away. 19 And the basons and the censers, and the bowls, and the pots, and the candlesticks, and the cups, and the goblets, that which was of gold in gold, and that which was of silver in silver, the captain of the body-guard took away. 20 The two pillars, the one sea, and the twelve brazen oxen that formed the bases, which king Solomon had made for the house of Jehovah: for the brass of all these vessels there was no weight. 21 And as to the pillars: the height of one pillar was eighteen cubits, and a line of twelve cubits encompassed it; and the thickness thereof was four fingers: it was hollow. 22 And the capital upon it was brass, and the height of the one capital was five cubits; and the network and the pomegranates, upon the capital round about, all of brass; and similarly for the second pillar, and the pomegranates. 23 And there were ninety-six pomegranates on the four sides; all the pomegranates upon the network were a hundred round about.

24 And the captain of the body-guard took Seraiah the chief priest, and Zephaniah the second priest, and the three doorkeepers. 25 And out of the city he took a eunuch that was set over the men of war, and seven men of them that were in the king's presence, who were found in the city, and the scribe of the captain of the host, who enrolled the people of the land. And sixty men of the people of the land that were found in the midst of the city. 26 And Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard took them, and brought them to the king of Babylon to Riblah; 27 and the king of Babylon smote them, and put them to death at Riblah in the land of Hamath. Thus Judah was carried away captive out of his land. 28 This is the people whom Nebuchadrezzar carried away captive: in the seventh year three thousand and twenty-three Jews; 29 in the eighteenth year of Nebuchadrezzar he carried away captive from Jerusalem eight hundred and thirty-two persons; 30 in the twenty-third year of Nebuchadrezzar, Nebuzar-adan the captain of the body-guard carried away captive of the Jews seven hundred and forty-five persons: all the persons were four thousand six hundred.

31 And it came to pass in the thirty-seventh year of the captivity of Jehoiachin king of Judah, in the twelfth month, on the twenty-fifth of the month, that Evil-Merodach king of Babylon, in the year that he began to reign, lifted up the head of Jehoiachin king of Judah, and brought him forth out of prison; 32 and he spoke kindly unto him, and set his seat above the seat of the kings that were with him in Babylon. 33 And he changed his prison garments; and he ate bread before him continually all the days of his life; 34 and his allowance was a continual allowance given him by the king of Babylon, every day a portion until the day of his death, all the days of his life.

Lamentations 3

1 I am the man that hath seen affliction by the rod of his wrath. 2 Me hath he led, and brought into darkness, and not into light. 3 Surely against me hath he turned again and again his hand all the day. 4 My flesh and my skin hath he wasted away, he hath broken my bones. 5 He hath built against me, and encompassed me with gall and toil. 6 He hath made me to dwell in dark places as those that have been long dead. 7 He hath hedged me about that I cannot get out: he hath made my chain heavy. 8 Even when I cry and shout, he shutteth out my prayer. 9 He hath inclosed my ways with hewn stone, he hath made my paths crooked. 10 He is unto me as a bear lying in wait, a lion in secret places. 11 He hath turned aside my ways, and pulled me in pieces; he hath made me desolate. 12 He hath bent his bow, and set me as a mark for the arrow. 13 He hath caused the arrows of his quiver to enter into my reins. 14 I am become a derision to all my people; their song all the day. 15 He hath sated me with bitterness, he hath made me drunk with wormwood. 16 He hath also broken my teeth with gravel stones, he hath covered me with ashes. 17 And thou hast removed my soul far off from peace: I have forgotten prosperity. 18 And I said, My strength is perished, and my hope in Jehovah. 19 Remember thou mine affliction and my wandering, the wormwood and the gall. 20 My soul hath them constantly in remembrance, and is humbled in me.

21 --This I recall to heart, therefore have I hope. 22 It is of Jehovah's loving-kindness we are not consumed, because his compassions fail not; 23 they are new every morning: great is thy faithfulness. 24 Jehovah is my portion, saith my soul; therefore will I hope in him. 25 Jehovah is good unto them that wait for him, to the soul that seeketh him. 26 It is good that one should both wait, and that in silence, for the salvation of Jehovah. 27 It is good for a man that he bear the yoke in his youth: 28 He sitteth solitary and keepeth silence, because he hath laid it upon him; 29 he putteth his mouth in the dust, if so be there may be hope; 30 he giveth his cheek to him that smiteth him; he is filled full with reproach. 31 For the Lord will not cast off for ever; 32 but if he have caused grief, he will have compassion according to the multitude of his loving-kindnesses: 33 for he doth not willingly afflict or grieve the children of men. 34 To crush under foot all the prisoners of the earth, 35 to turn aside the right of a man before the face of the Most High, 36 to wrong a man in his cause, --will not the Lord see it?

37 Who is he that saith, and there cometh to pass, what the Lord hath not commanded? 38 Out of the mouth of the Most High doth not there proceed evil and good? 39 Wherefore doth a living man complain, a man for the punishment of his sins? 40 Let us search and try our ways, and turn again to Jehovah. 41 Let us lift up our heart with our hands unto ·God[*] in the heavens.

42 We have transgressed and have rebelled: thou hast not pardoned. 43 Thou hast covered thyself with anger, and pursued us; thou hast slain, thou hast not spared. 44 Thou hast covered thyself with a cloud, that prayer should not pass through. 45 Thou hast made us the offscouring and refuse in the midst of the peoples. 46 All our enemies have opened their mouth against us. 47 Fear and the pit are come upon us, devastation and ruin. 48 Mine eye runneth down with streams of water for the ruin of the daughter of my people. 49 Mine eye poureth down, and ceaseth not, without any intermission, 50 till Jehovah look down and behold from the heavens. 51 Mine eye affecteth my soul, because of all the daughters of my city. 52 They that are mine enemies without cause have chased me sore like a bird. 53 They have cut off my life in a pit, and cast a stone upon me. 54 Waters streamed over my head; I said, I am cut off.

55 I called upon thy name, Jehovah, out of the lowest pit. 56 Thou hast heard my voice: hide not thine ear at my sighing, at my cry. 57 Thou drewest near in the day that I called upon thee; thou saidst, Fear not. 58 Lord, thou hast pleaded the cause of my soul, thou hast redeemed my life. 59 Jehovah, thou hast seen my wrong: judge thou my cause. 60 Thou hast seen all their vengeance, all their imaginations against me. 61 Thou hast heard their reproach, O Jehovah, all their imaginations against me; 62 the lips of those that rise up against me and their meditation against me all the day. 63 Behold thou their sitting down and their rising up: I am their song. 64 Render unto them a recompence, O Jehovah, according to the work of their hands; 65 give them obduracy of heart, thy curse unto them; 66 pursue them in anger, and destroy them from under the heavens of Jehovah.

Hebrew: El

Lamentations 4

1 How is the gold become dim! the most pure gold changed! the stones of the sanctuary poured out at the top of all the streets! 2 The sons of Zion, so precious, comparable to fine gold, how are they esteemed as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of the potter! 3 Even the jackals offer the breast, they give suck to their young; the daughter of my people is become cruel, like the ostriches in the wilderness. 4 The tongue of the sucking child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth for thirst; the young children ask bread, no man breaketh it unto them. 5 They that fed delicately are desolate in the streets; they that were brought up in scarlet embrace dung-hills. 6 And the punishment of the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the reward of the sin of Sodom, which was overthrown as in a moment, and no hands were violently laid upon her. 7 Her Nazarites were purer than snow, whiter than milk; they were more ruddy in body than rubies, their figure was as sapphire. 8 Their visage is darker than blackness, they are not known in the streets; their skin cleaveth to their bones, it is withered, it is become like a stick. 9 The slain with the sword are happier than the slain with hunger; for these pine away, stricken through for want of the fruits of the field. 10 The hands of pitiful women have boiled their own children: they were their meat in the ruin of the daughter of my people. 11 Jehovah hath accomplished his fury; he hath poured out his fierce anger, and hath kindled a fire in Zion, which hath consumed the foundations thereof. 12 The kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world, would not have believed that the adversary and the enemy should enter into the gates of Jerusalem.

13 It is for the sins of her prophets, and the iniquities of her priests, who have shed the blood of the righteous in the midst of her. 14 They wandered about blind in the streets; they were polluted with blood, so that men could not touch their garments. 15 They cried unto them, Depart! Unclean! Depart! depart, touch not! When they fled away, and wandered about, it was said among the nations, They shall no more sojourn there. 16 The face of Jehovah hath divided them; he will no more regard them. They respected not the persons of the priests, they favoured not the aged. 17 Our eyes still failed for our vain help; in our watching, we have watched for a nation that did not save. 18 They hunted our steps, that we could not go in our streets: our end is near, our days are fulfilled; for our end is come. 19 Our pursuers were swifter than the eagles of the heavens; they chased us hotly upon the mountains, they laid wait for us in the wilderness. 20 The breath of our nostrils, the anointed of Jehovah, was taken in their pits; of whom we said, Under his shadow we shall live among the nations.

21 Rejoice and be glad, daughter of Edom, that dwellest in the land of Uz: the cup shall pass also unto thee; thou shalt be drunken, and make thyself naked. 22 The punishment of thine iniquity is accomplished, O daughter of Zion; he will no more carry thee away into captivity. He will visit thine iniquity, O daughter of Edom; he will discover thy sins.

Ezekiel 1

1 Now it came to pass in the thirtieth year, in the fourth month, on the fifth of the month, as I was among the captives by the river Chebar, the heavens were opened, and I saw visions of God[*] 2 On the fifth of the month, (it was the fifth year of king Jehoiachin's captivity,) 3 the word of Jehovah came expressly unto Ezekiel the priest, the son of Buzi, in the land of the Chaldeans by the river Chebar; and the hand of Jehovah was there upon him.

4 And I looked, and behold, a stormy wind came out of the north, a great cloud, and a fire infolding itself, and a brightness was about it, and out of the midst thereof as the look of glowing brass, out of the midst of the fire. 5 Also out of the midst thereof, the likeness of four living creatures. And this was their appearance: they had the likeness of a man. 6 And every one had four faces, and every one of them had four wings. 7 And their feet were straight feet; and the sole of their feet was like the sole of a calf's foot; and they sparkled as the look of burnished brass. 8 And they had the hands of a man under their wings on their four sides; and they four had their faces and their wings: 9 their wings were joined one to another; they turned not when they went; they went every one straight forward. 10 And the likeness of their faces was the face of a man; and they four had the face of a lion on the right side; and they four had the face of an ox on the left side; they four had also the face of an eagle. 11 And their faces and their wings were parted above; two wings of every one were joined one to another, and two covered their bodies. 12 And they went every one straight forward: whither the Spirit was to go, they went; they turned not when they went. 13 And as for the likeness of the living creatures, their appearance was like burning coals of fire, as the appearance of torches: it went up and down among the living creatures; and the fire was bright; and out of the fire went forth lightning. 14 And the living creatures ran and returned as the appearance of a flash of lightning.

15 And I looked at the living creatures, and behold, one wheel upon the earth beside the living creatures, toward their four faces. 16 The appearance of the wheels and their work was as the look of a chrysolite; and they four had one likeness; and their appearance and their work was as it were a wheel in the middle of a wheel. 17 When they went, they went upon their four sides; they turned not when they went. 18 As for their rims, they were high and dreadful; and they four had their rims full of eyes round about. 19 And when the living creatures went, the wheels went beside them; and when the living creatures were lifted up from the earth, the wheels were lifted up. 20 Whithersoever the Spirit was to go, they went, thither would their spirit go; and the wheels were lifted up along with them: for the spirit of the living creature was in the wheels. 21 When those went, they went; and when those stood, they stood; and when those were lifted up from the earth, the wheels were lifted up along with them: for the spirit of the living creature was in the wheels. 22 And there was the likeness of an expanse over the heads of the living creature, as the look of the terrible crystal, stretched forth over their heads above. 23 And under the expanse were their wings straight, the one toward the other: every one had two which covered on this side, and every one had two which covered on that side their bodies. 24 And when they went, I heard the noise of their wings, like the noise of great waters, as the voice of the Almighty, a tumultuous noise, as the noise of a host: when they stood, they let down their wings; 25 and there was a voice from above the expanse that was over their heads. When they stood, they let down their wings.

26 And above the expanse that was over their heads was the likeness of a throne, as the appearance of a sapphire stone; and upon the likeness of the throne was a likeness as the appearance of a man above upon it. 27 And I saw as the look of glowing brass, as the appearance of fire, within it round about; from the appearance of his loins and upward, and from the appearance of his loins and downward, I saw as it were the appearance of fire, and it had brightness round about. 28 As the appearance of the bow that is in the cloud in the day of rain, so was the appearance of the brightness round about. This was the appearance of the likeness of the glory of Jehovah. And when I saw, I fell on my face, and I heard a voice of one that spoke.

Hebrew: Elohim

Ezekiel 2

1 And he said unto me, Son of man, stand upon thy feet, and I will speak with thee. 2 And the Spirit entered into me when he spoke unto me, and set me upon my feet; and I heard him that spoke unto me. 3 And he said unto me, Son of man, I send thee to the children of Israel, to nations that are rebellious, which have rebelled against me: they and their fathers have transgressed against me unto this very day; 4 and these children are impudent and hard-hearted: I am sending thee unto them; and thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah. 5 And they, whether they will hear or whether they will forbear--for they are a rebellious house--yet shall they know that there hath been a prophet among them.

6 And thou, son of man, be not afraid of them, and be not afraid of their words; for briars and thorns are with thee, and thou dwellest among scorpions: be not afraid of their words, and be not dismayed at their faces; for they are a rebellious house. 7 And thou shalt speak my words unto them, whether they will hear or whether they will forbear; for they are rebellious. 8 And thou, son of man, hear what I say unto thee; be not thou rebellious like that rebellious house: open thy mouth, and eat that I give thee. 9 And I looked, and behold, a hand was put forth toward me; and behold, a roll of a book therein. 10 And he spread it out before me; and it was written within and without; and there were written in it lamentations, and mourning, and woe.

Ezekiel 3

1 And he said unto me, Son of man, eat what thou findest; eat this roll, and go, speak unto the house of Israel. 2 So I opened my mouth, and he caused me to eat that roll. 3 And he said unto me, Son of man, cause thy belly to eat, and fill thy bowels with this roll which I give thee. And I ate, and it was in my mouth as honey for sweetness. 4 And he said unto me, Son of man, go, get thee unto the house of Israel, and speak with my words unto them. 5 For thou art not sent to a people of strange language, and of difficult speech, but to the house of Israel; 6 not to many peoples of strange language and of difficult speech, whose words thou canst not understand: had I sent thee to them, would they not hearken unto thee? 7 But the house of Israel will not hearken unto thee, for none of them will hearken unto me. For all the house of Israel are hard of forehead and stiff of heart. 8 Behold, I have made thy face hard against their faces, and thy forehead hard against their foreheads. 9 As an adamant harder than flint have I made thy forehead. Fear them not, neither be dismayed at them, for they are a rebellious house. 10 And he said unto me, Son of man, all my words which I shall speak unto thee, receive in thy heart, and hear with thine ears; 11 and go, get thee to them of the captivity, unto the children of thy people, and speak unto them, and tell them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah, --whether they will hear or whether they will forbear. 12 And the Spirit lifted me up, and I heard behind me the sound of a great rushing, saying, Blessed be the glory of Jehovah from his place! 13 --and the sound of the wings of the living creatures that touched one another, and the sound of the wheels beside them, and the sound of a great rushing. 14 And the Spirit lifted me up, and took me away; and I went in bitterness, in the heat of my spirit, and the hand of Jehovah was strong upon me. 15 And I came to them of the captivity at Tel-abib, that dwelt by the river Chebar, and I sat where they sat; and I sat there astonied among them seven days.

16 And it came to pass at the end of seven days, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 17 Son of man, I have appointed thee a watchman unto the house of Israel, and thou shalt hear the word from my mouth, and give them warning from me. 18 When I say unto the wicked, Thou shalt certainly die; and thou givest him not warning, nor speakest to warn the wicked from his wicked way, that he may live: the same wicked man shall die in his iniquity; but his blood will I require at thy hand. 19 But if thou warn the wicked, and he turn not from his wickedness, nor from his wicked way, he shall die in his iniquity; but thou hast delivered thy soul. 20 And when a righteous man doth turn from his righteousness, and do what is wrong, and I lay a stumbling-block before him, he shall die; because thou hast not given him warning, he shall die in his sin, and his righteous acts which he hath done shall not be remembered; but his blood will I require at thy hand. 21 And if thou warn the righteous man, that the righteous sin not, and he doth not sin, he shall certainly live, for he hath taken warning; and thou hast delivered thy soul.

22 And the hand of Jehovah was there upon me; and he said unto me, Arise, go forth into the valley, and there I will talk with thee. 23 And I arose, and went forth into the valley, and behold, the glory of Jehovah stood there, like the glory which I saw by the river Chebar; and I fell on my face. 24 And the Spirit entered into me, and set me upon my feet; and he spoke with me, and said unto me, Go, shut thyself within thy house. 25 And thou, son of man, behold, they shall put bands upon thee, and shall bind thee therewith, and thou shalt not go out among them. 26 And I will make thy tongue cleave to the roof of thy mouth, that thou shalt be dumb, and shalt not be to them a reprover; for they are a rebellious house. 27 And when I speak with thee, I will open thy mouth, and thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: He that heareth, let him hear; and he that forbeareth, let him forbear: for they are a rebellious house.

Ezekiel 4

1 And thou, son of man, take thee a brick, and lay it before thee, and portray upon it a city, --Jerusalem: 2 and lay siege against it, and build forts against it, and cast a mound against it, and set camps against it, and place battering-rams against it round about. 3 And take thou unto thee an iron plate, and put it for a wall of iron between thee and the city; and set thy face against it, and it shall be besieged, and thou shalt lay siege against it: this shall be a sign to the house of Israel. 4 And thou, lie upon thy left side, and lay the iniquity of the house of Israel upon it: the number of the days that thou liest upon it, thou shalt bear their iniquity. 5 And I have appointed thee the years of their iniquity, according to the number of the days, three hundred and ninety days; and thou shalt bear the iniquity of the house of Israel. 6 And when thou hast accomplished them, thou shalt lie again on thy right side, and thou shalt bear the iniquity of the house of Judah forty days: I have appointed thee each day for a year. 7 And thou shalt set thy face toward the siege of Jerusalem, and thine arm shall be uncovered, and thou shalt prophesy against it. 8 And behold, I lay bands upon thee, and thou shalt not turn thyself from one side to the other, till thou hast ended the days of thy siege.

9 And thou, take unto thee wheat, and barley, and beans, and lentils, and millet, and spelt, and put them in one vessel, and make thee bread thereof, according to the number of the days that thou liest upon thy side: three hundred and ninety days shalt thou eat thereof. 10 And thy meat which thou shalt eat shall be by weight, twenty shekels a day: from time to time shalt thou eat it. 11 And thou shalt drink water by measure, the sixth part of a hin: from time to time shalt thou drink. 12 And thou shalt eat it as barley-cake, and thou shalt bake it in their sight with dung that cometh out of man. 13 And Jehovah said, So shall the children of Israel eat their bread unclean among the nations whither I will drive them. 14 Then said I, Ah, Lord Jehovah! behold, my soul hath not been defiled, and from my youth up even until now have I not eaten of that which dieth of itself, or of that which is torn; neither came there abominable flesh into my mouth. 15 And he said unto me, See, I have given thee cow's dung for man's dung, and thou shalt prepare thy bread therewith. 16 And he said unto me, Son of man, behold, I break the staff of bread in Jerusalem; and they shall eat bread by weight, and with anxiety; and they shall drink water by measure, and with astonishment: 17 because bread and water shall fail them, and they shall be astonied one with another, and waste away in their iniquity.

Ezekiel 5

1 And thou, son of man, take thee a sharp knife; a barber's razor shalt thou take; and cause it to pass upon thy head and upon thy beard: and thou shalt take balances to weigh, and divide the hair. 2 A third part shalt thou burn in the fire in the midst of the city, when the days of the siege are fulfilled; and thou shalt take a third part, and smite about it with a knife; and a third part thou shalt scatter to the wind, and I will draw out a sword after them. 3 And thou shalt take thereof a few in number, and bind them in thy skirts; 4 and thou shalt take of these again, and cast them into the midst of the fire, and burn them in the fire: from it shall a fire come forth against all the house of Israel.

5 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: This is Jerusalem: I have set her in the midst of the nations, and the countries are round about her. 6 And she hath rebelled against my judgments in wickedness more than the nations, and against my statutes more than the countries that are round about her: for mine ordinances have they refused; and my statutes, they have not walked in them. 7 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because ye have been turbulent more than the nations that are round about you, and have not walked in my statutes, neither have kept mine ordinances, nor even have done according to the ordinances of the nations that are round about you; 8 therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I, even I, am against thee, and will execute judgments in the midst of thee in the sight of the nations; 9 and I will do in thee that which I have not done, and whereunto I will not do any more the like, because of all thine abominations. 10 Therefore the fathers shall eat the sons in the midst of thee, and the sons shall eat their fathers; and I will execute judgments in thee, and the whole remnant of thee will I scatter to all the winds. 11 Wherefore, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, verily because thou hast defiled my sanctuary with all thy detestable things, and with all thine abominations, therefore will I also withdraw mine eye, and it shall not spare, nor will I have any pity. 12 A third part of thee shall die by the pestilence, and shall be consumed by the famine in the midst of thee; and a third part shall fall by the sword round about thee; and I will scatter a third part to all the winds, and I will draw out a sword after them. 13 And mine anger shall be accomplished, and I will satisfy my fury upon them, and I will comfort myself; and they shall know that I Jehovah have spoken in my jealousy, when I have accomplished my fury upon them. 14 And I will make thee a waste and a reproach among the nations that are round about thee, in the sight of all that pass by. 15 And it shall be a reproach, and a taunt, an instruction, and an astonishment unto the nations that are round about thee, when I shall execute judgments upon thee in anger, and in fury, and in furious rebukes: I, Jehovah, have spoken. 16 When I send upon them the evil arrows of famine, that are for their destruction, which I send to destroy you, then will I increase the famine upon you, and will break your staff of bread. 17 And I will send upon you famine and evil beasts, which shall bereave thee of children; and pestilence and blood shall pass through thee; and I will bring the sword upon thee: I, Jehovah, have spoken.

Ezekiel 6

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, set thy face toward the mountains of Israel, and prophesy against them, 3 and say, Mountains of Israel, hear the word of the Lord Jehovah: thus saith the Lord Jehovah to the mountains and to the hills, to the water-courses and to the valleys: Behold, I, evenI, do bring a sword upon you, and will destroy your high places. 4 And your altars shall be desolate, and your sun-images shall be broken; and I will cast down your slain men before your idols; 5 and I will lay the dead bodies of the children of Israel before their idols; and I will scatter your bones round about your altars. 6 In all your dwelling-places the cities shall be laid waste, and the high places shall be desolate; that your altars may be laid waste and made desolate, and your idols may be broken and cease, and your sun-images may be cut down, and your works may be abolished. 7 And the slain shall fall in the midst of you, and ye shall know that I am Jehovah.

8 Yet will I leave a remnant, in that ye shall have some escaped from the sword among the nations, when ye shall be scattered through the countries. 9 And they that escape of you shall remember me among the nations whither they have been carried captives, when I shall have broken their whorish heart, which hath departed from me, and their eyes, which go a whoring after their idols; and they shall loathe themselves for the evils which they have committed, in all their abominations. 10 And they shall know that I am Jehovah: I have not said in vain that I would do this evil unto them.

11 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Smite with thy hand, and stamp with thy foot, and say, Alas for all the abominations of the iniquities of the house of Israel! for they shall fall by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence. 12 He that is far off shall die of the pestilence; and he that is near shall fall by the sword; and he that is left, and is besieged, shall die by the famine: and I will accomplish my fury upon them. 13 And ye shall know that I am Jehovah, when their slain shall be among their idols, round about their altars, upon every high hill, on all the tops of the mountains, and under every green tree, and under every thick terebinth, the places where they offered sweet savour to all their idols. 14 And I will stretch out my hand upon them, and make the land desolate, yea, more desolate than the wilderness of Diblath, in all their dwellings; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 7

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 And thou, son of man, thus saith the Lord Jehovah unto the land of Israel: An end, the end is come upon the four corners of the land. 3 Now is the end upon thee; and I will send mine anger upon thee, and will judge thee according to thy ways, and will bring upon thee all thine abominations. 4 And mine eye shall not spare thee, neither will I have pity; but I will bring thy ways upon thee, and thine abominations shall be in the midst of thee; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. 5 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: An evil, an only evil! behold, it is come. 6 The end is come, the end is come; it awaketh against thee: behold, it cometh. 7 The doom is come unto thee, inhabitant of the land; the time is come, the day is near, --tumult, and not the joyous cry from the mountains. 8 Now will I soon pour out my fury upon thee, and accomplish mine anger against thee; and I will judge thee according to thy ways, and will bring upon thee all thine abominations. 9 And mine eye shall not spare, neither will I have pity: I will render unto thee according to thy ways, and thine abominations shall be in the midst of thee; and ye shall know that it is I, Jehovah, that smite. 10 Behold the day, behold, it is come: the doom is gone forth; the rod hath blossomed, pride is full blown. 11 Violence is risen up into a rod of wickedness: nothing of them shall remain, nor of their multitude, nor of their wealth, nor of the magnificence in the midst of them. 12 The time is come, the day draweth near: let not the buyer rejoice, nor the seller mourn; for fierce anger is upon all the multitude thereof. 13 For the seller shall not return to that which is sold, even though he were yet alive amongst the living: for the vision is touching the whole multitude thereof; it shall not be revoked; and none shall through his iniquity assure his life. 14 They have blown the trumpet and made all ready, but none goeth to the battle; for my fierce anger is upon all the multitude thereof. 15 The sword is without, and the pestilence and the famine within: he that is in the field shall die by the sword; and he that is in the city, famine and pestilence shall devour him.

16 And they that escape of them shall escape, and shall be on the mountains like doves of the valleys, all of them moaning, every one for his iniquity. 17 All hands shall be feeble, and all knees shall melt into water. 18 And they shall gird on sackcloth, and horror shall cover them; and shame shall be upon all faces, and baldness upon all their heads. 19 They shall cast their silver in the streets, and their gold shall be as an impurity: their silver and their gold shall not be able to deliver them in the day of Jehovah's wrath; they shall not satisfy their souls, neither fill their belly; for it hath been the stumbling-block of their iniquity. 20 And he set in majesty his beautiful ornament; but they made therein the images of their abominations and of their detestable things: therefore have I made it an impurity unto them. 21 And I will give it into the hands of strangers for a prey, and to the wicked of the earth for a spoil; and they shall profane it. 22 And I will turn my face from them; and they shall profane my secret place; and the violent shall enter into it, and profane it.

23 Make the chain; for the land is full of bloody crimes, and the city is full of violence. 24 Therefore will I bring the worst of the nations, and they shall possess their houses; and I will make the pride of the strong to cease; and their sanctuaries shall be profaned. 25 Destruction cometh; and they shall seek peace, but there shall be none. 26 Mischief shall come upon mischief, and rumour shall be upon rumour; and they shall seek a vision from a prophet; but the law shall perish from the priest, and counsel from the elders. 27 The king shall mourn, and the prince shall be clothed with dismay, and the hands of the people of the land shall tremble: I will do unto them according to their way, and with their judgments will I judge them; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 8

1 And it came to pass in the sixth year, in the sixth month, on the fifth of the month, that as I sat in my house, and the elders of Judah sat before me, the hand of the Lord Jehovah fell there upon me. 2 And I looked, and behold, a likeness as the appearance of fire; from the appearance of his loins and downward, fire; and from his loins and upward, as the appearance of brightness, as the look of glowing brass. 3 And he stretched forth the form of a hand, and took me by a lock of my head; and the Spirit lifted me up between the earth and the heavens, and brought me in the visions of God[*] to Jerusalem, to the entry of the inner gate that looketh toward the north, where was the seat of the image of jealousy, which provoketh to jealousy. 4 And behold, the glory of the God[*] of Israel was there, according to the appearance that I saw in the valley. 5 And he said unto me, Son of man, lift up now thine eyes toward the north. And I lifted up mine eyes toward the north, and behold, northward of the gate of the altar, this image of jealousy in the entry. 6 And he said unto me, Son of man, seest thou what they do? the great abominations that the house of Israel commit here, to cause me to go far off from my sanctuary? And yet again thou shalt see great abominations.

7 And he brought me to the entry of the court, and I looked, and behold, a hole in the wall. 8 And he said unto me, Son of man, dig now through the wall; and I digged through the wall, and behold, a door. 9 And he said unto me, Go in, and behold the wicked abominations that they do here. 10 And I went in and looked, and behold, every form of creeping thing and abominable beast, and all the idols of the house of Israel, portrayed upon the wall round about. 11 And there stood before them seventy men of the elders of the house of Israel, and in the midst of them stood Jaazaniah the son of Shaphan, with every man his censer in his hand; and a thick cloud of incense went up. 12 And he said unto me, Hast thou seen, son of man, what the elders of the house of Israel do in the dark, every one in his chambers of imagery? for they say, Jehovah seeth us not; Jehovah hath forsaken the land.

13 And he said unto me, Yet again thou shalt see great abominations which they do. 14 And he brought me to the entry of the gate of Jehovah's house that was toward the north; and behold, there sat women weeping for Tammuz. 15 And he said unto me, Seest thou, son of man? Thou shalt yet again see greater abominations than these. 16 And he brought me into the inner court of Jehovah's house, and behold, at the entry of the temple of Jehovah, between the porch and the altar, were about five and twenty men, with their backs toward the temple of Jehovah and their faces toward the east; and they worshipped the sun toward the east. 17 And he said unto me, Seest thou, son of man? Is it a light thing to the house of Judah to commit the abominations which they commit here, that they yet fill the land with violence, and keep provoking me afresh to anger? And behold, they put the branch to their nose. 18 And I also will deal in fury: mine eye shall not spare, neither will I have pity; and though they cry in mine ears with a loud voice, I will not hear them.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Ezekiel 9

1 And he cried in mine ears with a loud voice, saying, Draw near, ye that have charge of the city, and every man with his destroying weapon in his hand. 2 And behold, six men came from the way of the upper gate, which is turned toward the north, and every man with his slaughter weapon in his hand; and in the midst of them, one man clothed with linen, with a writer's ink-horn by his side; and they went in, and stood beside the brazen altar. 3 And the glory of the God[*] of Israel was gone up from the cherub, whereupon it was, to the threshold of the house; and he called to the man clothed with linen, who had the writer's ink-horn by his side; 4 and Jehovah said unto him, Go through the midst of the city, through the midst of Jerusalem, and set a mark upon the foreheads of the men that sigh and that cry for all the abominations that are done in the midst thereof.

5 And to the others he said in my hearing, Go after him through the city, and smite: let not your eye spare, neither have pity. 6 Slay utterly the old man, the young man, and the maiden, and little children, and women; but come not near any man upon whom is the mark; and begin at my sanctuary. Then they began at the elders who were before the house. 7 And he said unto them, Defile the house, and fill the courts with the slain: go forth. And they went forth, and smote in the city. 8 And it came to pass, while they were smiting, and I was left, that I fell upon my face, and cried, and said, Ah, Lord Jehovah! wilt thou destroy all the remnant of Israel in thy pouring out of thy fury upon Jerusalem? 9 And he said unto me, The iniquity of the house of Israel and Judah is exceeding great, and the land is full of blood, and the city full of perverseness; for they say, Jehovah hath forsaken the earth, and Jehovah seeth not. 10 And as for me also, mine eye shall not spare, neither will I have pity: I will recompense their way upon their head. 11 And behold, the man clothed with linen, who had the ink-horn by his side, reported the matter, saying, I have done as thou hast commanded me.

Hebrew: Elohim

Ezekiel 12

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, thou dwellest in the midst of a rebellious house, which have eyes to see, and see not, which have ears to hear, and hear not; for they are a rebellious house. 3 And thou, son of man, prepare thee a captive's baggage, and go captive by day in their sight; and thou shalt go captive from thy place to another place in their sight. It may be they will consider, though they are a rebellious house. 4 And bring forth thy baggage by day in their sight, as a captive's baggage, and thou thyself, go forth at even in their sight as they that go forth into captivity. 5 Dig thou through the wall in their sight, and carry out thereby. 6 In their sight shalt thou bear it upon thy shoulder, and carry it forth in the dark; thou shalt cover thy face, and thou shalt not see the ground: for I have appointed thee for a sign unto the house of Israel. 7 And I did so as I was commanded: I brought forth my baggage by day, as a captive's baggage, and in the even I digged through the wall with my hand; I brought it forth in the dark, andbore it upon my shoulder, in their sight. 8 And in the morning the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 9 Son of man, hath not the house of Israel, the rebellious house, said unto thee, What doest thou? 10 Say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: This burden concerneth the prince in Jerusalem, and all the house of Israel that are among them. 11 Say, I am your sign: as I have done, so shall it be done unto them: they shall go into exile, into captivity. 12 And the prince that is among them shall bear upon his shoulder in the dark, and shall go forth; they shall dig through the wall to carry out thereby; he shall cover his face, that he see not the land with his eyes. 13 And I will spread my net upon him, and he shall be taken in my snare; and I will bring him to Babylon to the land of the Chaldeans; but he shall not see it, and there shall he die. 14 And I will scatter toward every wind all that are about him to help him, and all his troops; and I will draw out the sword after them. 15 And they shall know that I am Jehovah when I shall scatter them among the nations and disperse them through the countries. 16 But I will leave a few men of them from the sword, from the famine, and from the pestilence; that they may declare all their abominations among the nations whither they shall come; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

17 And the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, 18 Son of man, eat thy bread with quaking, and drink thy water with trembling and with anxiety; 19 and say unto the people of the land, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah concerning the inhabitants of Jerusalem, in the land of Israel: They shall eat their bread with anxiety, and drink their water with astonishment, because her land shall be left desolate of all that is in it, for the violence of all them that dwell therein. 20 And the cities that are inhabited shall be laid waste, and the land shall be a desolation; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah.

21 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 22 Son of man, what is that proverb which ye have in the land of Israel, saying, The days shall be prolonged, and every vision faileth? 23 Tell them therefore, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will make this proverb to cease, and they shall no more use it as a proverb in Israel; but say unto them, The days are at hand, and the accomplishment of every vision. 24 For there shall be no more any vain vision nor flattering divination in the midst of the house of Israel. 25 For I am Jehovah; I will speak, and the word that I shall speak shall be performed, it shall be no more deferred. For in your days, O rebellious house, will I speak the word and will perform it, saith the Lord Jehovah. 26 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 27 Son of man, behold, they of the house of Israel say, The vision that he seeth is for many days, and he prophesieth of times that are far off. 28 Therefore say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: There shall none of my words be deferred any more, but the word that I have spoken shall be done, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 13

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying: 2 Son of man, prophesy against the prophets of Israel that prophesy, and say unto them that prophesy out of their own heart, Hear ye the word of Jehovah. 3 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Woe unto the foolish prophets, that follow their own spirit, and have seen nothing! 4 O Israel, thy prophets have been like foxes in desert places. 5 Ye have not gone up into the breaches, nor made up the fence for the house of Israel, to stand in the battle in the day of Jehovah. 6 They have seen vanity and lying divination, that say, Jehovah saith! and Jehovah hath not sent them; and they make them to hope that the word will be fulfilled. 7 Have ye not seen a vain vision, and spoken a lying divination, when ye say, Jehovah saith; and I have not spoken? 8 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because ye speak vanity, and have seen lies, therefore behold, I am against you, saith the Lord Jehovah. 9 And my hand shall be against the prophets that see vanity and that divine lies: they shall not be in the council of my people, neither shall they be written in the register of the house of Israel, and they shall not enter into the land of Israel: and ye shall know that I am the Lord Jehovah.

10 Because, yea because they have seduced my people, saying, Peace! and there is no peace; and one buildeth up a wall, and lo, they daub it with untempered mortar-- 11 say unto them which daub it with untempered mortar that it shall fall: there shall be an overflowing rain, and ye, O great hailstones, shall fall, and a stormy wind shall burst forth. 12 And lo, when the wall is fallen, shall it not be said unto you, Where is the daubing with which ye have daubed it? 13 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will cause to burst forth a stormy wind in my fury; and there shall be an overflowing rain in mine anger, and hail-stones in fury for utter destruction. 14 And I will break down the wall that ye have daubed with untempered mortar, and bring it down to the ground, so that the foundation thereof shall be discovered; and it shall fall, and ye shall be destroyed in the midst thereof; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. 15 And I will accomplish my fury upon the wall, and upon them that daub it with untempered mortar, and will say unto you, The wall is no more, neither they that daubed it, 16 the prophets of Israel who prophesy concerning Jerusalem, and who see a vision of peace for her, and there is no peace, saith the Lord Jehovah.

17 And thou, son of man, set thy face against the daughters of thy people, who prophesy out of their own heart; and prophesy against them, 18 and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Woe unto the women that sew pillows for all wrists, and that make veils for the head of persons of every stature to catch souls! Will ye catch the souls of my people, and will ye save your own souls alive? 19 And will ye profane me among my people for handfuls of barley and for morsels of bread, to slay the souls that should not die, and to save the souls alive that should not live, by your lying to my people that listen to lying? 20 Wherefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against your pillows, that the souls which ye catch by their means may fly away; and I will tear them from your arms, and will let the souls go, the souls that ye catch, that they may fly away. 21 And I will tear your veils and deliver my people out of your hand, and they shall be no more in your hand to be hunted; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. 22 Because with falsehood ye have grieved the heart of the righteous, whom I have not made sad; and have strengthened the hands of the wicked, that he should not return from his wicked way, to save his life: 23 therefore ye shall no more see vanity, nor divine divinations; and I will deliver my people out of your hand: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 14

1 And there came certain of the elders of Israel unto me, and sat before me. 2 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 3 Son of man, these men have set up their idols in their heart, and put the stumbling-block of their iniquity before their face: should I be inquired of at all by them? 4 Therefore speak to them, and say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Every man of the house of Israel that setteth up his idols in his heart, and putteth the stumbling-block of his iniquity before his face, and cometh to the prophet, I Jehovah will answer him according to this, according to the multitude of his idols: 5 that I may take the house of Israel by their own heart, because they are all estranged from me through their idols. 6 Therefore say unto the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Return ye, and turn yourselves from your idols; and turn away your faces from all your abominations. 7 For every one of the house of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn in Israel, who separateth himself from me, and setteth up his idols in his heart, and putteth the stumbling-block of his iniquity before his face, and cometh to the prophet to inquire of me by him, I Jehovah will answer him by myself; 8 and I will set my face against that man, and will make him desolate, so that he shall be for a sign and for proverbs, and I will cut him off from the midst of my people: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. 9 And if the prophet be enticed and shall speak a word, I Jehovah have enticed that prophet; and I will stretch out my hand against him, and will destroy him from the midst of my people Israel. 10 And they shall bear their iniquity: the iniquity of the prophet shall be even as the iniquity of the inquirer; 11 that the house of Israel may go no more astray from me, neither make themselves any more unclean with all their transgressions; and they shall be my people, and I will be their God[*] saith the Lord Jehovah.

12 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 13 Son of man, when a land sinneth against me by working unfaithfulness, and I stretch out my hand upon it, and break the staff of the bread thereof, and send famine upon it, and cut off man and beast from it; 14 though these three men, Noah, Daniel, and Job, should be in it, they should deliver but their own souls by their righteousness, saith the Lord Jehovah. 15 If I cause evil beasts to pass through the land, and they bereave it, and it become a desolation, so that no one passeth through because of the beasts; 16 --though these three men should be in it, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, they should deliver neither sons nor daughters: they only should be delivered, and the land should be a desolation. 17 Or if I bring the sword upon that land, and say, Sword, go through the land, so that I cut off man and beast from it, 18 and these three men should be in it, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, they should deliver neither sons nor daughters, but they only themselves should be delivered. 19 Or if I send a pestilence into that land, and pour out my fury upon it in blood, to cut off from it man and beast, 20 and Noah, Daniel, and Job should be in it, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, they should deliver neither son nor daughter: they should but deliver their own souls by their righteousness. 21 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: How much more when I send my four sore judgments upon Jerusalem, the sword, and the famine, and the evil beast, and the pestilence, to cut off from it man and beast! 22 But behold, there shall be left in it those that escape, who shall be brought out of it, sons and daughters. Behold, they shall come forth unto you, and ye shall see their way and their doings; and ye shall be comforted concerning the evil that I have brought upon Jerusalem, as to all that I have brought upon it. 23 And they shall comfort you, when ye see their way and their doings; and ye shall know that I have not done without cause all that I have done in it, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Ezekiel 16

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, cause Jerusalem to know her abominations, 3 and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah unto Jerusalem: Thy birth and thy nativity is of the land of the Canaanite: thy father was an Amorite, and thy mother a Hittite. 4 And as for thy nativity, in the day thou wast born thy navel was not cut, neither wast thou washed in water for cleansing; thou wast not rubbed with salt at all, nor swaddled at all. 5 No eye pitied thee, to do any of these unto thee, to have compassion upon thee; but thou wast cast out in the open field, from abhorrence of thy person, in the day that thou wast born.

6 And I passed by thee, and saw thee weltering in thy blood, and I said unto thee, in thy blood, Live! yea, I said unto thee, in thy blood, Live! 7 I caused thee to multiply, as the bud of the field; and thou didst increase and grow great, and thou camest to fulness of beauty; thy breasts were fashioned, and thy hair grew: but thou wast naked and bare. 8 And I passed by thee, and looked upon thee, and behold, thy time was the time of love; and I spread my skirt over thee, and covered thy nakedness; and I swore unto thee, and entered into a covenant with thee, saith the Lord Jehovah, and thou becamest mine. 9 And I washed thee with water, and thoroughly washed away thy blood from thee, and I anointed thee with oil; 10 and I clothed thee with embroidered work, and shod thee with badgers' skin, and I bound thee about with byssus, and covered thee with silk. 11 And I decked thee with ornaments, and I put bracelets upon thy hands, and a chain on thy neck; 12 and I put a ring on thy nose, and earrings in thine ears, and a beautiful crown upon thy head. 13 Thus wast thou decked with gold and silver, and thy raiment was byssus, and silk, and embroidered work. Thou didst eat fine flour, and honey, and oil; and thou becamest exceedingly beautiful, and thou didst prosper into a kingdom. 14 And thy fame went forth among the nations for thy beauty; for it was perfect through my magnificence, which I had put upon thee, saith the Lord Jehovah.

15 But thou didst confide in thy beauty, and playedst the harlot because of thy renown, and pouredst out thy whoredoms on every one that passed by: his it was. 16 And of thy garments thou didst take, and madest for thyself high places decked with divers colours, and didst play the harlot thereupon: the like hath not come to pass, and shall be no more. 17 And thou didst take thy fair jewels of my gold and of my silver, which I had given thee, and madest to thyself images of males, and didst commit fornication with them. 18 And thou tookest thine embroidered garments, and coveredst them; and thou didst set mine oil and mine incense before them. 19 And my bread which I had given thee, the fine flour and the oil and the honey wherewith I fed thee, thou didst even set it before them for a sweet savour: thus it was, saith the Lord Jehovah. 20 And thou didst take thy sons and thy daughters, whom thou hadst borne unto me, and these didst thou sacrifice unto them, to be devoured. Were thy whoredoms a small matter, 21 that thou didst slay my children and give them up in passing them over to them? 22 And in all thine abominations and thy whoredoms thou hast not remembered the days of thy youth, when thou wast naked and bare, when thou wast weltering in thy blood. 23 And it came to pass after all thy wickedness (woe, woe unto thee! saith the Lord Jehovah), 24 that thou didst also build unto thee a place of debauchery, and didst make thee a high place in every street: 25 thou didst build thy high place at every head of the way, and madest thy beauty to be abhorred, and thou didst open thy feet to every one that passed by, and multiply thy whoredom. 26 And thou didst commit fornication with the Egyptians thy neighbours, great of flesh; and didst multiply thy whoredom to provoke me to anger. 27 And behold, I stretched out my hand over thee, and diminished thine appointed portion; and I gave thee over unto the will of them that hate thee, the daughters of the Philistines, who were confounded at thy lewd way. 28 And thou didst commit fornication with the Assyrians, because thou wast insatiable; yea, thou didst commit fornication with them, and yet couldest not be satisfied. 29 And thou didst multiply thy whoredom with the land of merchants, Chaldea, and yet thou wast not satisfied herewith. 30 How weak is thy heart, saith the Lord Jehovah, seeing thou doest all these things, the work of a whorish woman, under no restraint; 31 in that thou buildest thy place of debauchery at the head of every way, and makest thy high place in every street! And thou hast not been as a harlot, in that thou scornest reward, 32 O adulterous wife, that taketh strangers instead of her husband. 33 They give rewards to all harlots; but thou gavest thy rewards to all thy lovers, and rewardedst them, that they might come unto thee on every side for thy whoredoms. 34 And in thee is the contrary from other women, in thy whoredoms, in that none followeth thee to commit fornication; and whereas thou givest a reward, and no reward is given unto thee, so art thou contrary.

35 Therefore, O harlot, hear the word of Jehovah. 36 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because thy money hath been poured out, and thy nakedness discovered through thy fornications with thy lovers, and with all the idols of thine abominations, and because of the blood of thy children which thou didst give unto them; 37 therefore, behold, I will gather all thy lovers with whom thou hast taken pleasure, and all that thou hast loved, with all that thou hast hated, --I will even gather them round about against thee, and will discover thy nakedness unto them, that they may see all thy nakedness. 38 And I will judge thee with the judgments of women that commit adultery and shed blood; and I will give thee up to the blood of fury and jealousy; 39 and I will give thee into their hand, and they shall throw down thy place of debauchery, and shall break down thy high places; and they shall strip thee of thy garments, and shall take thy fair jewels, and leave thee naked and bare. 40 And they shall bring up an assemblage against thee, and they shall stone thee with stones, and thrust thee through with their swords. 41 And they shall burn thy houses with fire, and execute judgments upon thee in the sight of many women; and I will cause thee to cease from being a harlot, and thou also shalt give no more any reward. 42 And I will appease my fury against thee, and my jealousy shall depart from thee; and I will be quiet, and will be no more angry. 43 Because thou hast not remembered the days of thy youth, but hast raged against me in all these things, behold, therefore, I also will recompense thy way upon thy head, saith the Lord Jehovah, and thou shalt not commit this lewdness besides all thine abominations.

44 Behold, every one that useth proverbs shall speak in a proverb against thee, saying, As the mother, so is her daughter! 45 Thou art the daughter of thy mother that loathed her husband and her children; and thou art the sister of thy sisters, who loathed their husbands and their children. Your mother was a Hittite, and your father an Amorite. 46 And thine elder sister is Samaria that dwelleth at thy left hand, she and her daughters; and thy younger sister, that dwelleth at thy right hand, is Sodom and her daughters. 47 And thou hast not walked in their ways, nor done according to their abominations; but as though that were a very little, thou hast been more corrupt than they in all thy ways. 48 As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, Sodom thy sister hath not done, she nor her daughters, as thou hast done, thou and thy daughters! 49 Behold, this was the iniquity of thy sister Sodom: pride, fulness of bread, and careless ease was in her and in her daughters, but she did not strengthen the hand of the poor and needy. 50 And they were haughty, and committed abomination before me, and I took them away when I saw it. 51 And Samaria hath not sinned according to the half of thy sins; but thou hast multiplied thine abominations more than they, and hast justified thy sisters by all thine abominations which thou hast done. 52 Thou also, who hast judged thy sisters, bear thine own confusion, because of thy sins in which thou hast acted more abominably than they: they are more righteous than thou. So be thou ashamed also, and bear thy confusion, in that thou hast justified thy sisters. 53 And I will bring again their captivity, the captivity of Sodom and her daughters, and the captivity of Samaria and her daughters, and the captivity of thy captives in the midst of them; 54 that thou mayest bear thy confusion, and mayest be confounded for all that thou hast done, in that thou comfortest them. 55 And thy sisters, Sodom and her daughters, shall return to their former estate, and Samaria and her daughters shall return to their former estate; thou also and thy daughters, ye shall return to your former estate. 56 Yea, Sodom thy sister was not mentioned by thy mouth in the day of thy pride, 57 before thy wickedness was discovered, as at the time of the reproach of the daughters of Syria, and of all that are round about her, the daughters of the Philistines, who despise thee on every side. 58 Thy lewdness and thine abominations, thou bearest them, saith Jehovah. 59 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will even deal with thee as thou hast done, who hast despised the oath, and broken the covenant.

60 Nevertheless I will remember my covenant with thee in the days of thy youth, and I will establish unto thee an everlasting covenant. 61 And thou shalt remember thy ways, and be confounded, when thou shalt receive thy sisters who are older than thou, together with those who are younger than thou; for I will give them unto thee for daughters, but not by virtue of thy covenant. 62 And I will establish my covenant with thee, and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah; 63 that thou mayest remember, and be ashamed, and no more open thy mouth because of thy confusion, when I forgive thee all that thou hast done, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 17

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, put forth a riddle, and speak a parable unto the house of Israel, 3 and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: A great eagle with great wings, long-pinioned, full of feathers, which was of divers colours, came unto Lebanon, and took the highest branch of the cedar. 4 He cropped off the top of its young shoots, and carried it into a merchants' land; he set it in a city of traders. 5 And he took of the seed of the land, and planted it in a fruitful field; he placed it by great waters, he set it as a willow tree. 6 And it grew, and became a spreading vine of low stature, so that its branches should turn toward him, and the roots thereof be under him; and it became a vine, and brought forth branches, and shot forth sprigs. 7 And there was another great eagle with great wings and many feathers; and behold, from the beds of her plantation, this vine did bend her roots unto him, and shot forth her branches toward him, that he might water it. 8 It was planted in a good field by many waters, that it might bring forth branches and bear fruit, that it might be a noble vine. 9 Say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Shall it prosper? Shall he not pull up its roots, and cut off its fruit, that it may wither? All its fresh sprouting leaves shall wither, even without a great arm and many people to pluck it up by its roots. 10 And behold, being planted, shall it prosper? shall it not utterly wither when the east wind toucheth it? It shall wither in the beds where it grew. 11 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 12 Say now to the rebellious house, Know ye not what these things are? Say, Behold, the king of Babylon came to Jerusalem, and took its king and its princes, and led them with him to Babylon. 13 And he took of the king's seed, and made a covenant with him, and brought him under an oath, and he took away the mighty of the land; 14 that the kingdom might be abased, that it might not lift itself up, that it might keep his covenant in order to stand. 15 But he rebelled against him in sending his ambassadors into Egypt, that they might give him horses and much people. Shall he prosper? shall he escape that doeth such things? shall he break the covenant, and yet escape? 16 As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, verily in the place of the king that made him king, whose oath he despised, and whose covenant he broke, even with him, in the midst of Babylon, shall he die. 17 Neither shall Pharaoh with a mighty army and a great assemblage do anything for him in the war, when they cast up mounds and build forts to cut off many persons. 18 He despised the oath, and broke the covenant; and behold, he had given his hand, yet hath he done all these things: he shall not escape. 19 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: As I live, verily, mine oath which he hath despised, and my covenant which he hath broken, even it will I recompense upon his head. 20 And I will spread my net upon him, and he shall be taken in my snare; and I will bring him to Babylon, and will enter into judgment with him there for his unfaithfulness in which he hath been unfaithful against me. 21 And all his fugitives with all his bands shall fall by the sword, and they that remain shall be scattered toward every wind; and ye shall know that I Jehovah have spoken.

22 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will also take of the highest branch of the lofty cedar, and will set it; I will crop off from the top of its young shoots a tender one, and I will plant it upon a high and eminent mountain: 23 upon the mountain of the height of Israel will I plant it; and it shall bring forth branches, and bear fruit, and become a noble cedar; and under it shall dwell all birds of every wing; in the shadow of the branches thereof shall they dwell. 24 And all the trees of the field shall know that I Jehovah have brought down the high tree, have exalted the low tree, have dried up the green tree, and made the dry tree to flourish: I Jehovah have spoken, and will do it.

Ezekiel 18

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 What mean ye, ye who use this proverb of the land of Israel, saying, The fathers eat sour grapes, and the children's teeth are set on edge? 3 As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, ye shall not have any more to use this proverb in Israel. 4 Behold, all the souls are mine; as the soul of the father, so also the soul of the son is mine: the soul that sinneth, it shall die. 5 And if a man be righteous, and do judgment and justice: 6 --he hath not eaten upon the mountains, nor lifted up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel, neither hath defiled his neighbour's wife, nor come near to a woman in her separation, 7 and hath not oppressed any; he hath restored to the debtor his pledge, hath not exercised robbery, hath given his bread to the hungry, and covered the naked with a garment; 8 he hath not given forth upon usury, nor taken increase; he hath withdrawn his hand from unrighteousness, hath executed true judgment between man and man, 9 hath walked in my statutes, and kept mine ordinances, to deal faithfully: he is righteous, he shall certainly live, saith the Lord Jehovah.

10 And if he have begotten a son that is violent, a shedder of blood, and that doeth only one of any of these things, 11 and that doeth not any of those duties, but also hath eaten upon the mountains, and defiled his neighbour's wife, 12 hath oppressed the poor and needy, exercised robbery, hath not restored the pledge, and hath lifted up his eyes to the idols, committed abomination, 13 given forth upon usury, and taken increase; shall he then live? He shall not live: he hath done all these abominations; he shall certainly die; his blood shall be upon him. 14 But lo, if he have begotten a son that seeth all his father's sins which he hath done, and considereth, and doeth not such like: 15 --he hath not eaten upon the mountains, nor lifted up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel; he hath not defiled his neighbour's wife, 16 and hath not oppressed any, nor withholden the pledge, neither hath exercised robbery; he hath given his bread to the hungry, and covered the naked with a garment; 17 he hath withdrawn his hand from the poor, hath not received usury nor increase, hath executed my judgments, and walked in my statutes: he shall not die for the iniquity of his father, he shall certainly live. 18 As for his father, because he practised oppression, exercised robbery upon his brother, and did what was not good among his people, behold, he shall die in his iniquity. 19 And ye say, Why doth not the son bear the iniquity of the father? But the son hath done judgment and justice, hath kept all my statutes, and hath done them; he shall certainly live. 20 The soul that sinneth, it shall die. The son shall not bear the iniquity of the father, neither shall the father bear the iniquity of the son; the righteousness of the righteous shall be upon him, and the wickedness of the wicked shall be upon him.

21 And the wicked, if he turn from all his sins which he hath committed, and keep all my statutes, and do judgment and justice, he shall certainly live, he shall not die. 22 None of his transgressions which he hath committed shall be remembered against him; in his righteousness which he hath done shall he live. 23 Have I any pleasure at all in the death of the wicked? saith the Lord Jehovah; is it not in his turning from his way, that he may live? 24 And when the righteous turneth from his righteousness and practiseth what is wrong, and doeth according to all the abominations that the wicked doeth, shall he live? None of his righteous acts which he hath done shall be remembered: in his unfaithfulness which he hath wrought, and in his sin which he hath sinned, in them shall he die. 25 And ye say, The way of the Lord is not equal. Hear then, house of Israel. Is not my way equal? are not your ways unequal? 26 When the righteous turneth away from his righteousness, and practiseth what is wrong, and dieth for it; in his wrong that he hath done shall he die. 27 And when the wicked turneth from his wickedness which he hath committed, and doeth judgment and justice, he shall keep his soul alive. 28 Because he considereth, and turneth from all his transgressions which he hath committed, he shall certainly live, he shall not die. 29 But the house of Israel say, The way of the Lord is not equal. O house of Israel, are not my ways equal? Is it not your ways that are unequal?

30 Therefore I will judge you, house of Israel, every one according to his ways, saith the Lord Jehovah. Return ye, and turn from all your transgressions; so iniquity shall not be your snare. 31 Cast away from you all your transgressions wherewith ye have transgressed, and make you a new heart and a new spirit: why then will ye die, house of Israel? 32 For I have no pleasure in the death of him that dieth, saith the Lord Jehovah; therefore turn ye and live.

Ezekiel 21

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, set thy face against Jerusalem, and drop words against the holy places, and prophesy against the land of Israel, 3 and say to the land of Israel, Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, and I will draw forth my sword out of its sheath, and will cut off from thee the righteous and the wicked. 4 Seeing that I will cut off from thee the righteous and the wicked, therefore shall my sword go forth out of its sheath against all flesh, from the south to the north; 5 and all flesh shall know that I Jehovah have drawn forth my sword out of its sheath: it shall not return any more. 6 Sigh then, thou son of man; with breaking of the loins, and with bitterness sigh before their eyes. 7 And it shall be, when they say unto thee, Wherefore dost thou sigh? that thou shalt say, Because of the tidings, for it cometh; and every heart shall melt, and all hands shall be feeble, and every spirit shall languish, and all knees shall melt into water: behold, it cometh; it is here, saith the Lord Jehovah.

8 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 9 Son of man, prophesy, and say, Thus saith Jehovah: Say, A sword, a sword is sharpened, and also furbished. 10 It is sharpened for sore slaughter, it is furbished that it may glitter. Shall we then make mirth, saying, The sceptre of my son contemneth all wood? 11 And he hath given it to be furbished that it may be handled. The sword, --it is sharpened, and it is furbished to give it into the hand of the slayer. 12 Cry and howl, son of man; for it shall be against my people, it shall be against all the princes of Israel: they are given up to the sword along with my people: smite therefore upon the thigh. 13 For the trial is made; and what if even the contemning sceptre shall be no more? saith the Lord Jehovah. 14 And thou, son of man, prophesy, and smite thy hands together; for the strokes of the sword shall be doubled the third time: it is the sword of the slain, the sword that hath slain the great one, which encompasseth them privily. 15 In order that the heart may melt, and the stumbling-blocks be multiplied, I have set the threatening sword against all their gates: ah! it is made glittering, it is whetted for the slaughter. 16 Gather up strength, go to the right hand, turn thee, go to the left, whithersoever thy face is appointed. 17 And I myself will smite my hands together, and I will satisfy my fury: I Jehovah have spoken it.

18 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 19 And thou, son of man, set thee two ways, by which the sword of the king of Babylon may come--out of one land shall they both come--and make thee a signpost, make it at the head of the way to the city. 20 Appoint a way for the coming of the sword to Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and to Judah at the fenced city of Jerusalem. 21 For the king of Babylon standeth at the parting of the way, at the head of the two ways, to use divination: he shaketh his arrows, he inquireth of the teraphim, he looketh in the liver. 22 In his right hand is the lot of Jerusalem to appoint battering-rams, to open the mouth for bloodshed, to lift up the voice with shouting, to appoint battering-rams against the gates, to cast mounds, to build siege-towers. 23 And this shall be a false divination in their sight, for them that have sworn oaths; but he will call to remembrance the iniquity, that they may be taken. 24 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because ye make your iniquity to be remembered in that your transgressions are discovered, so that in all your doings your sins appear; because ye are come to remembrance, ye shall be taken with the hand. 25 And thou, profane, wicked prince of Israel, whose day is come, at the time of the iniquity of the end, 26 --thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Remove the mitre and take off the crown; what is shall be no more. Exalt that which is low, and abase that which is high. 27 I will overturn, overturn, overturn it! This also shall be no more, until he come whose right it is; and I will give it to him.

28 And thou, son of man, prophesy and say, Thus speaketh the Lord Jehovah concerning the children of Ammon, and concerning their reproach; and thou shalt say, A sword, a sword is drawn; for the slaughter is it furbished, that it may consume, that it may glitter: 29 whilst they see vanity for thee, whilst they divine a lie unto thee, to lay thee upon the necks of the wicked that are slain, whose day is come at the time of the iniquity of the end. 30 Restore it to its sheath. I will judge thee in the place where thou wast created, in the land of thy birth. 31 And I will pour out mine indignation upon thee, I will blow upon thee the fire of my wrath, and give thee into the hand of brutish men, skilful to destroy. 32 Thou shalt be for fuel to the fire; thy blood shall be in the midst of the land; thou shalt not be remembered: for I Jehovah have spoken.

Ezekiel 22

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 And thou, son of man, wilt thou judge, wilt thou judge the bloody city? Yea, cause her to know all her abominations, 3 and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: A city that sheddeth blood in her midst, that her time may come, and maketh idols against herself to defile herself. 4 Thou art become guilty by thy blood which thou hast shed, and hast defiled thyself with thine idols which thou hast made; and thou hast caused thy days to draw near, and art come unto thy years: therefore have I made thee a reproach unto the nations, and a mocking unto all countries. 5 Those that are near, and those that are far from thee, shall mock thee, who art infamous and full of tumult. 6 Behold, the princes of Israel have been in thee to shed blood, each according to his power. 7 In thee have they made light of father and mother; in the midst of thee have they dealt by oppression with the stranger; in thee have they vexed the fatherless and the widow. 8 Thou hast despised my holy things, and hast profaned my sabbaths. 9 In thee there have been slanderous men to shed blood; and in thee have they eaten upon the mountains; in the midst of thee they have committed lewdness; 10 in thee have they discovered their fathers' nakedness; in thee have they humbled her that was unclean in her separation. 11 And one hath committed abomination with his neighbour's wife; and another hath lewdly defiled his daughter-in-law; and another in thee hath humbled his sister, his father's daughter. 12 In thee have they taken gifts to shed blood; thou hast taken usury and increase, and thou hast overreached thy neighbours by oppression, and hast forgotten me, saith the Lord Jehovah. 13 And behold, I have smitten mine hand at thine overreaching which thou hast done, and at thy bloodshed which hath been in the midst of thee. 14 Shall thy heart endure, shall thy hands be strong, in the days that I shall deal with thee? I Jehovah have spoken, and will do it. 15 And I will scatter thee among the nations, and disperse thee through the countries, and will consume thy filthiness out of thee. 16 And thou shalt be polluted through thyself in the sight of the nations, and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah.

17 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 18 Son of man, the house of Israel is become dross to me: they are all copper, and tin, and iron, and lead, in the midst of the furnace: they are become the dross of silver. 19 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because ye are all become dross, therefore behold, I will gather you into the midst of Jerusalem. 20 As they gather silver, and copper, and iron, and lead, and tin, into the midst of the furnace, to blow the fire upon it, to melt it, so will I gather you in mine anger and in my fury, and I will lay you on and melt you. 21 Yea, I will collect you, and blow upon you the fire of my wrath, and ye shall be melted in the midst thereof. 22 As silver is melted in the midst of the furnace, so shall ye be melted in the midst thereof: and ye shall know that I Jehovah have poured out my fury upon you.

23 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 24 Son of man, say unto her, Thou art a land that is not cleansed, nor rained upon in the day of indignation. 25 There is a conspiracy of her prophets in the midst of her like a roaring lion ravening the prey; they devour souls; they take away treasure and precious things; they increase her widows in the midst of her; 26 her priests do violence to my law, and profane my holy things: they put no difference between the holy and profane, neither do they make known the difference between the unclean and the clean, and they hide their eyes from my sabbaths, and I am profaned among them. 27 Her princes in the midst of her are like wolves ravening the prey, to shed blood, to destroy souls, to get dishonest gain. 28 And her prophets have daubed for them with untempered mortar, seeing vanity and divining lies unto them, saying, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah! and Jehovah hath not spoken. 29 The people of the land use oppression and practise robbery; and they vex the poor and needy, and oppress the stranger wrongfully. 30 And I sought for a man among them, that should make up the fence, and stand in the breach before me for the land, that I should not destroy it; but I found none. 31 And I will pour out mine indignation upon them; I will consume them in the fire of my wrath: their own way will I recompense upon their head, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 23

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, there were two women, daughters of one mother. 3 And they committed whoredom in Egypt; they committed whoredom in their youth: there were their breasts pressed, and there were handled the teats of their virginity. 4 And their names were Oholah the elder, and Oholibah her sister; and they were mine, and they bore sons and daughters. As for their names: Samaria is Oholah, and Jerusalem Oholibah. 5 And Oholah played the harlot when she was mine; and she lusted after her lovers, after the Assyrians her neighbours, 6 clothed with blue, governors and rulers, all of them attractive young men, horsemen riding upon horses. 7 And she bestowed her whoredoms upon them, all of them the choice of the children of Asshur; and with all after whom she lusted, with all their idols she defiled herself. 8 Neither left she her whoredoms brought from Egypt; for in her youth they had lain with her, and had handled the breasts of her virginity, and poured their fornication upon her. 9 Therefore I gave her into the hand of her lovers, into the hand of the children of Asshur, after whom she lusted. 10 These discovered her nakedness, they took her sons and her daughters, and slew her with the sword; and she became a name among women; and they executed judgment upon her.

11 And her sister Oholibah saw this, and was more corrupt in her passion than she, and in her fornications more than the whoredoms of her sister. 12 She lusted after the children of Asshur her neighbours, governors and rulers, clothed most gorgeously, horsemen riding upon horses, all of them attractive young men. 13 And I saw that she was defiled: both took one way. 14 And she increased her fornications; for she saw men portrayed upon the wall, the images of the Chaldeans portrayed with vermilion, 15 girded with girdles upon their loins, with flowing turbans on their heads, all of them captains in appearance, after the likeness of the children of Babylon, of Chaldea, the land of their nativity. 16 And as soon as she saw them with her eyes, she lusted after them, and sent messengers unto them into Chaldea. 17 And the children of Babylon came to her into the bed of love, and they defiled her with their fornication; she too defiled herself with them, and her soul was alienated from them. 18 And she discovered her whoredoms, and discovered her nakedness; and my soul was alienated from her, like as my soul was alienated from her sister. 19 Yet she multiplied her whoredoms, calling to remembrance the days of her youth, wherein she played the harlot in the land of Egypt; 20 and she lusted after their paramours, whose flesh is as the flesh of asses, and whose issue is as the issue of horses. 21 And thou didst look back to the lewdness of thy youth, in the handling of thy teats by the Egyptians, for the breasts of thy youth.

22 Therefore, Oholibah, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will raise up thy lovers against thee, from whom thy soul is alienated, and I will bring them against thee on every side. 23 The children of Babylon, and all the Chaldeans, Pekod and Shoa and Koa, all the children of Asshur with them; all of them attractive young men, governors and rulers, great lords and renowned, all of them riding upon horses. 24 And they shall come against thee with armour, chariots and wheels, and with an assemblage of peoples; they shall set themselves against thee with target, and shield, and helmet round about; and I will put judgment before them, and they shall judge thee according to their judgments. 25 And I will set my jealousy against thee, and they shall deal furiously with thee: they shall cut off thy nose and thine ears, and thy remnant shall fall by the sword; they shall take thy sons and thy daughters; and thy residue shall be devoured by the fire. 26 They shall also strip the of thy garments, and take away thy fair jewels. 27 And I will make thy lewdness to cease from thee, and thy whoredom brought from the land of Egypt; and thou shalt not lift up thine eyes unto them, nor remember Egypt any more. 28 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will give thee over into the hand of them whom thou hatest, into the hand of them from whom thy soul is alienated. 29 And they shall deal with thee in hatred, and shall take away all thy labour, and shall leave thee naked and bare; so that the nakedness of thy whoredoms shall be discovered, both thy lewdness and thy fornications. 30 These things shall be done unto thee, because thou hast gone a whoring after the nations, because thou hast defiled thyself with their idols. 31 Thou hast walked in the way of thy sister; and I have given her cup into thy hand. 32 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Thou shalt drink of thy sister's cup deep and large; thou shalt be for a laughing-stock and a derision, for it containeth much. 33 Thou shalt be filled with drunkenness and sorrow, with the cup of astonishment and desolation, the cup of thy sister Samaria; 34 thou shalt even drink it and suck it out, and thou shalt gnaw the sherds thereof, and pluck off thine own breasts: for I have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah. 35 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because thou hast forgotten me, and cast me behind thy back, therefore bear thou also thy lewdness and thy fornications.

36 And Jehovah said unto me, Son of man, wilt thou judge Oholah and Oholibah? yea, declare unto them their abominations. 37 For they have committed adultery, and blood is in their hands; and with their idols have they committed adultery, and have also passed over unto them their children, whom they bore unto me, to be devoured. 38 Moreover this have they done unto me: in the same day have they defiled my sanctuary and profaned my sabbaths. 39 For when they had slaughtered their children unto their idols, they came the same day into my sanctuary to profane it; and behold, thus have they done in the midst of my house. 40 And furthermore, they sent for men to come from far, unto whom a messenger was sent; and behold, they came: for whom thou didst wash thyself, paintedst thine eyes, and deckedst thyself with ornaments; 41 and satest upon a stately bed, with a table prepared before it, whereupon thou hadst set mine incense and mine oil. 42 And the voice of a multitude living carelessly was with her; and with people of the common sort were brought Sabeans from the wilderness, and they put bracelets upon their hands, and a beautiful crown upon their heads. 43 And I said of her that was old in adulteries, Will she now commit her fornications, even she. 44 And they went in unto her, as they go in unto a whorish woman: so went they in unto Oholah and unto Oholibah the lewd women. 45 And righteous men, they shall judge them with the judgment of adulteresses, and with the judgment of women that shed blood; for they are adulteresses, and blood is in their hands. 46 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will bring up an assemblage against them, and will give them to be driven hither and thither and spoiled. 47 And the assemblage shall stone them with stones, and despatch them with their swords; they shall kill their sons and their daughters, and burn their houses with fire. 48 And I will cause lewdness to cease out of the land, and all women shall receive instruction and shall not do according to your lewdness. 49 And they shall recompense your lewdness upon you, and ye shall bear the sins of your idols; and ye shall know that I am the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 24

1 And in the ninth year, in the tenth month, on the tenth of the month, the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, write thee the name of the day, of this selfsame day: on this selfsame day the king of Babylon draws near to Jerusalem. 3 And propose a parable unto the rebellious house, and say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Set on the pot, set it on, and also pour water into it. 4 Gather the pieces thereof into it, every good piece, the thigh and the shoulder; fill it with the choice bones: 5 take the choice of the flock; and also put a pile of wood under it, for the bones; make it boil well, and let the bones of it seethe therein. 6 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Woe to the bloody city, to the pot whose rust is therein, and whose rust is not gone out of it! Bring it out piece by piece; let no lot fall upon it: 7 for her blood is in the midst of her; she set it upon the bare rock; she poured it not upon the ground, to cover it with dust. 8 That it might cause fury to come up to execute vengeance, I have set her blood upon the bare rock, that it should not be covered. 9 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Woe to the bloody city! I also will make the pile great. 10 Heap on the wood, kindle the fire, boil thoroughly the flesh, and spice it well, and let the bones be burned. 11 Then set it empty upon its coals, that it may be hot, and the brass of it may burn, and that its filthiness may be molten in it, and that its rust may be consumed. 12 She hath exhausted her labours, yet her great rust goeth not forth out of her: let her rust be in the fire. 13 In thy filthiness is lewdness, for I have purged thee, and thou art not pure. Thou shalt no more be purged from thy filthiness, till I have satisfied my fury upon thee. 14 I Jehovah have spoken it: it shall come to pass, and I will do it; I will not go back, neither will I spare, nor will I repent. According to thy ways, and according to thy doings, shall they judge thee, saith the Lord Jehovah.

15 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 16 Son of man, behold, I take away from thee the desire of thine eyes with a stroke; yet thou shalt not mourn nor weep, neither shall thy tears run down. 17 Sigh in silence, make no mourning for the dead; bind thy turban upon thee, and put thy sandals upon thy feet, and cover not the beard, and eat not the bread of men. 18 --And I spoke unto the people in the morning; and at even my wife died. And I did in the morning as I was commanded. 19 And the people said unto me, Wilt thou not tell us what these things are to us, which thou doest? 20 And I said to them, The word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 21 Say unto the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will profane my sanctuary, the pride of your strength, the desire of your eyes, and your soul's longing; and your sons and your daughters whom ye have left behind shall fall by the sword. 22 And ye shall do as I have done: ye shall not cover the beard, neither eat the bread of men; 23 and your turbans shall be upon your heads, and your sandals upon your feet: ye shall not mourn nor weep; but ye shall waste away in your iniquities and moan one toward another. 24 Thus Ezekiel shall be unto you a sign; according to all that he hath done shall ye do: when it cometh, then ye shall know that I am the Lord Jehovah. 25 And thou, son of man, shall it not be in the day when I take from them their strength, the joy of their glory, the desire of their eyes, and that whereunto they lift up their soul, their sons and their daughters, 26 that in that day he that escapeth shall come unto thee, to cause thine ears to hear it? 27 In that day shall thy mouth be opened to him that is escaped, and thou shalt speak, and be no more dumb. So shalt thou be a sign unto them; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 25

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, set thy face against the children of Ammon, and prophesy against them; 3 and say unto the children of Ammon, Hear the word of the Lord Jehovah. Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because thou saidst, Aha, against my sanctuary, when it was profaned; and against the land of Israel, when it was made desolate; and against the house of Judah, when they went into captivity: 4 therefore behold, I will give thee to the children of the east for a possession, and they shall set their encampments in thee, and make their dwellings in thee; they shall eat thy fruits, and they shall drink thy milk. 5 And I will make Rabbah a pasture for camels, and the children of Ammon a couching-place for flocks: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. 6 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because thou hast clapped the hands, and stamped with the feet, and rejoiced with all the despite of thy soul against the land of Israel; 7 therefore behold, I will stretch out my hand upon thee, and will give thee for a spoil to the nations; and I will cut thee off from the peoples, and I will cause thee to perish out of the countries: I will destroy thee, and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah.

8 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because Moab and Seir do say, Behold, the house of Judah is like unto all the nations, 9 therefore behold, I will open the side of Moab from the cities, from his cities even to the last of them, the glory of the country, Beth-jeshimoth, Baal-meon, and Kirjathaim, 10 unto the children of the east, with the land of the children of Ammon; and I will give it them for a possession, that the children of Ammon may not be remembered among the nations: 11 and I will execute judgments upon Moab, and they shall know that I am Jehovah. 12 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because Edom hath dealt against the house of Judah by taking vengeance, and hath made himself very guilty, and revenged himself upon them, 13 therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will also stretch out my hand upon Edom; and will cut off man and beast from it; and I will make it desolate from Teman; and unto Dedan shall they fall by the sword. 14 And I will execute my vengeance upon Edom, by the hand of my people Israel; and they shall do in Edom according to mine anger and according to my fury; and they shall know my vengeance, saith the Lord Jehovah. 15 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because the Philistines have dealt by revenge, and have taken vengeance with despite of soul, to destroy, from old hatred; 16 therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I stretch out my hands upon the Philistines, and I will cut off the Kerethites, and cause the remnant of the sea-coast to perish. 17 And I will execute great vengeance upon them with furious rebukes; and they shall know that I am Jehovah, when I shall lay my vengeance upon them.

Ezekiel 26

1 And it came to pass in the eleventh year, on the first of the month, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, because Tyre hath said against Jerusalem, Aha, she is broken, the gate of the peoples! she is turned unto me: I shall be replenished now she is laid waste; 3 therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, Tyre, and will cause many nations to come up against thee, as the sea causeth its waves to come up. 4 And they shall destroy the walls of Tyre, and break down her towers. And I will scrape her dust from her, and make her a bare rock. 5 She shall be a place for the spreading of nets in the midst of the sea; for I have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah; and she shall become a spoil for the nations. 6 And her daughters that are in the field shall be slain by the sword; and they shall know that I am Jehovah. 7 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will bring from the north, against Tyre, Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, the king of kings, with horses, and with chariots, and with horsemen, and an assemblage, and much people. 8 He shall slay with the sword thy daughters in the field, and he shall make forts against thee, and cast up a mound against thee, and lift up the target against thee; 9 and he shall set his engines of attack against thy walls, and with his spikes he shall break down thy towers. 10 By reason of the abundance of his horses their dust shall cover thee; thy walls shall shake at the noise of the horsemen, and of the wheels, and of the chariots, when he shall enter through thy gates, as a city is entered into, wherein is made a breach. 11 With the hoofs of his horses shall he tread down all thy streets; he shall slay thy people by the sword, and the pillars of thy strength shall go down to the ground. 12 And they shall make a spoil of thy riches, and make a prey of thy wares; and they shall break down thy walls, and destroy thy pleasant houses; and they shall lay thy stones and thy timber and thy dust in the midst of the waters. 13 And I will cause the noise of thy songs to cease; and the sound of thy harps shall be no more heard. 14 And I will make thee a bare rock; thou shalt be a place for the spreading of nets; thou shalt be built no more: for I Jehovah have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah.

15 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah to Tyre: Shall not the isles shake at the sound of thy fall, when the wounded groan, when the slaughter is made in the midst of thee? 16 And all the princes of the sea shall come down from their thrones, and lay aside their robes, and put off their broidered garments: they shall clothe themselves with trembling, they shall sit upon the ground, and shall tremble every moment, and be astonied because of thee. 17 And they shall take up a lamentation for thee, and say to thee, How hast thou perished, that wast inhabited from the seas, O renowned city, which wast strong in the sea, --she and her inhabitants, who caused their terror to be on all them that dwell therein! 18 Now shall the isles tremble in the day of thy fall; and the isles that are in the sea shall be troubled at thy departure. 19 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: When I shall make thee a desolate city, like the cities that are not inhabited; when I bring up the deep upon thee, and the great waters cover thee: 20 then will I bring thee down, with them that go down to the pit, to the people of old time, and will cause thee to dwell in the lower parts of the earth, in places desolate of old, with them that go down to the pit, that thou be not inhabited; and I will set glory in the land of the living. 21 And I will make thee a terror, and thou shalt be no more; and thou shalt be sought for, and shalt never be found again, for ever, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 27

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying: 2 And thou, son of man, take up a lamentation for Tyre, 3 and say unto Tyre: O thou that art situate at the entries of the sea, and traffickest with the peoples in many isles, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Thou, Tyre, hast said, I am perfect in beauty. 4 Thy borders are in the heart of the seas, thy builders have perfected thy beauty. 5 They made all thy double boards of cypress-trees of Senir; they took cedars from Lebanon to make masts for thee. 6 Of the oaks of Bashan did they make thine oars; they made thy benches of ivory, inlaid in box-wood, out of the isles of Chittim. 7 Byssus with broidered work from Egypt was thy sail, to serve thee for a banner; blue and purple from the isles of Elishah was thine awning. 8 The inhabitants of Zidon and Arvad were thy rowers; thy wise men, O Tyre, who were in thee, were thy pilots. 9 The elders of Gebal and the wise men thereof were in thee repairing thy leaks; all the ships of the sea with their mariners were in thee, to barter with thee. 10 Persia and Lud and Phut were in thine army, thy men of war: they hanged shield and helmet in thee; they gave splendour to thee. 11 The children of Arvad with thine army were upon thy walls round about, and the Gammadim were on thy towers: they hanged their shields upon thy walls round about; they made thy beauty perfect. 12 Tarshish dealt with thee by reason of the abundance of all substance; with silver, iron, tin, and lead, they furnished thy markets. 13 Javan, Tubal, and Meshech, they were thy traffickers: they bartered with thee the persons of men, and vessels of bronze. 14 They of the house of Togarmah furnished thy markets with horses, and horsemen, and mules. 15 The children of Dedan were thy traffickers; many isles were the mart of thy hand: they rendered in payment horns of ivory, and ebony. 16 Syria dealt with thee for the multitude of thy handiworks: they traded in thy markets with carbuncles, purple, and broidered work, and fine linen, and corals, and rubies. 17 Judah and the land of Israel were thy traffickers: they bartered with thee wheat of Minnith, and sweet cakes, and honey, and oil, and balm. 18 Damascus dealt with thee because of the multitude of thy handiworks, by reason of the abundance of all substance, with wine of Helbon, and white wool. 19 Vedan and Javan of Uzal traded in thy markets: wrought iron, cassia, and calamus were in thy traffic. 20 Dedan was thy trafficker in precious riding-cloths. 21 Arabia and all the princes of Kedar were the merchants of thy hand: in lambs, and rams, and goats, in these did they trade with thee. 22 The merchants of Sheba and Raamah were thy traffickers: they furnished thy markets with all the choice spices, and with all precious stones and gold. 23 Haran, and Canneh, and Eden, the merchants of Sheba, Asshur, and Chilmad traded with thee: 24 these traded with thee in sumptuous clothes, in wrappings of blue and broidered work, and in chests full of variegated stuffs, bound with cords and made of cedar-wood, amongst thy merchandise. 25 The ships of Tarshish were thy caravans for thy traffic; and thou wast replenished, and highly honoured, in the heart of the seas.

26 Thy rowers have brought thee into great waters; the east wind hath broken thee in the heart of the seas. 27 Thy substance, and thy markets, thy merchandise, thy mariners, and thy pilots, they that repair thy leaks, and they that barter with thee, and all thy men of war that are in thee, along with all thine assemblage which is in the midst of thee, shall fall into the heart of the seas in the day of thy fall. 28 The open places shall shake at the sound of the cry of thy pilots. 29 And all that handle the oar, the mariners, all the pilots of the sea, shall come down from their ships; they shall stand upon the land, 30 and shall cause their voice to be heard over thee, and shall cry bitterly; and they shall cast up dust upon their heads; they shall wallow themselves in ashes. 31 And they shall make themselves utterly bald for thee, and gird themselves with sackcloth; and they shall weep for thee in bitterness of soul with bitter mourning. 32 And in their wailing they shall take up a lamentation for thee, and lament over thee, saying, Who is like Tyre, like her that is destroyed in the midst of the sea? 33 When thy wares went forth over the seas, thou filledst many peoples; thou didst enrich the kings of the earth with the abundance of thy substance and of thy merchandise. 34 In the time when thou art broken by the seas, in the depths of the waters, thy merchandise and all thine assemblage in the midst of thee have fallen. 35 All the inhabitants of the isles are amazed at thee, and their kings are horribly afraid, their countenance is troubled. 36 The merchants among the peoples hiss at thee; thou art become a terror, and thou shalt never be any more.

Ezekiel 29

1 In the tenth year, in the tenth month, on the twelfth of the month, the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, set thy face against Pharaoh king of Egypt, and prophesy against him, and against the whole of Egypt; 3 speak, and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, Pharaoh king of Egypt, the great monster that lieth in the midst of his rivers, which saith, My river is mine own, and I made it for myself. 4 And I will put hooks in thy jaws, and I will cause the fish of thy rivers to stick unto thy scales, and I will bring thee up out of the midst of thy rivers, and all the fish of thy rivers shall stick unto thy scales; 5 and I will cast thee into the wilderness, thee and all the fish of thy rivers: thou shalt fall upon the open field; thou shalt not be brought together nor gathered: I will give thee for meat to the beasts of the earth and to the fowl of the heavens. 6 And all the inhabitants of Egypt shall know that I am Jehovah, because they have been a staff of reed to the house of Israel. 7 When they took hold of thee by thy hand, thou didst give way and rend all their shoulder; and when they leaned upon thee, thou didst break, and didst make all their loins to tremble.

8 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will bring a sword upon thee, and cut off man and beast from thee. 9 And the land of Egypt shall be a desolation and a waste: and they shall know that I am Jehovah, because he saith, The river is mine, and I made it. 10 Therefore behold, I am against thee, and against thy rivers, and I will make the land of Egypt deserts of wasteness and desolation, from Migdol to Syene, even unto the border of Ethiopia. 11 No foot of man shall pass through it, nor shall foot of beast pass through it, nor shall it be inhabited, forty years. 12 And I will make the land of Egypt a desolation in the midst of the countries that are desolated, and her cities shall be, in the midst of the cities that are laid waste, a desolation forty years; and I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations, and will disperse them through the countries. 13 Yet thus saith the Lord Jehovah: At the end of forty years will I gather the Egyptians from the peoples whither they were scattered; 14 and I will turn again the captivity of Egypt, and will cause them to return to the land of Pathros, into the land of their birth, and they shall there be a base kingdom. 15 It shall be the basest of kingdoms; neither shall it exalt itself any more above the nations; and I will diminish them, so that they shall no more rule over the nations. 16 And it shall be no more the confidence of the house of Israel, bringing iniquity to remembrance, when they turn after them: and they shall know that I am the Lord Jehovah.

17 And it came to pass in the twenty-seventh year, in the first month, on the first of the month, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 18 Son of man, Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon caused his army to do hard service against Tyre; every head was made bald, and every shoulder was peeled: yet had he from Tyre no wages, nor his army, for the service that he had served against it. 19 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will give the land of Egypt unto Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon; and he shall carry away her multitude, and seize her spoil, and take her prey; and it shall be the wages for his army. 20 I have given him the land of Egypt for his labour wherewith he served against it, because they wrought for me, saith the Lord Jehovah. 21 In that day will I cause the horn of the house of Israel to bud forth, and I will give thee the opening of the mouth in the midst of them: and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 32

1 And it came to pass in the twelfth year, in the twelfth month, on the first of the month, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, take up a lamentation for Pharaoh king of Egypt, and say unto him, Thou wast like a young lion among the nations, and thou wast as a monster in the seas; and thou didst break forth in thy rivers, and troubledst the waters with thy feet, and fouledst their rivers. 3 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will also spread out my net over thee with an assemblage of many peoples; and they shall bring thee up in my net. 4 And I will leave thee upon the land, I will cast thee forth upon the open field, and will cause all the fowl of the heavens to settle upon thee, and I will fill the beasts of the whole earth with thee. 5 And I will lay thy flesh upon the mountains, and fill the valleys with the heap of thy members; 6 and I will water with thy blood the land wherein thou swimmest, even to the mountains; and the water-courses shall be full of thee. 7 And when I shall put thee out, I will cover the heavens, and make the stars thereof black; I will cover the sun with a cloud, and the moon shall not give her light. 8 All the bright lights of the heavens will I make black over thee, and bring darkness upon thy land, saith the Lord Jehovah. 9 And I will vex the heart of many peoples, when I bring the news of thy destruction among the nations, into the countries that thou hast not known. 10 And I will make many peoples amazed at thee, and their kings shall be horribly afraid at thee, when I brandish my sword before them; and they shall tremble at every moment, each one for his life, in the day of thy fall. 11 For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: The sword of the king of Babylon shall come upon thee. 12 By the swords of the mighty will I cause thy multitude to fall: the terrible of the nations are they all: and they shall spoil the pride of Egypt, and all the multitude thereof shall be destroyed. 13 And I will destroy all the beasts thereof, from beside the great waters; and the foot of man shall not trouble them any more, nor shall the cloven hoofs of beasts trouble them. 14 Then will I make their waters clear, and cause their rivers to run like oil, saith the Lord Jehovah. 15 When I shall make the land of Egypt a desolation, and the country shall be left desolate of all that was in it, when I have smitten all them that dwell therein, then shall they know that I am Jehovah. 16 It is a lamentation, and thus they shall lament her: the daughters of the nations shall say it in lamenting; they shall say it in lamenting over Egypt and over all her multitude, saith the Lord Jehovah.

17 And it came to pass in the twelfth year, on the fifteenth of the month, the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 18 Son of man, wail for the multitude of Egypt, and cast them down, her and the daughters of the famous nations, unto the lower parts of the earth, with them that go down into the pit. 19 Whom dost thou surpass in beauty? Go down, and be thou laid with the uncircumcised. 20 They shall fall in the midst of them that are slain by the sword. The sword hath been given: draw her out, and all her multitudes. 21 The strong among the mighty, with them that helped him, shall speak to him out of the midst of Sheol: they are gone down, they lie still, the uncircumcised, slain by the sword. 22 There is Asshur and all his assemblage, his graves round about him: all of them slain, fallen by the sword; 23 their graves are set in the sides of the pit, and his assemblage is round about his grave; all of them slain, fallen by the sword, --who caused terror in the land of the living. 24 There is Elam and all her multitude round about her grave, all of them slain, fallen by the sword, who are gone down uncircumcised unto the lower parts of the earth, who caused their terror in the land of the living; yet have they borne their confusion with them that go down to the pit. 25 They have set him a bed in the midst of the slain, with all his multitude: their graves are round about him, all of them uncircumcised, slain by the sword, though their terror was caused in the land of the living; and they have borne their confusion with them that go down to the pit: he is put in the midst of them that are slain. 26 There is Meshech, Tubal, and all their multitude, their graves round about them, all of them uncircumcised, slain by the sword, though they caused their terror in the land of the living. 27 And they lie not with the mighty, that are fallen of the uncircumcised, who are gone down to Sheol with their weapons of war; and whose swords are laid under their heads, and whose iniquities are upon their bones, though they were the terror of the mighty in the land of the living. 28 Thou also shalt be broken in the midst of the uncircumcised, and shalt lie with them that are slain with the sword. 29 There is Edom, her kings, and all her princes, who in their might are laid with them that are slain by the sword: they lie with the uncircumcised, and with them that go down to the pit. 30 There are the princes of the north, all of them, and all the Zidonians, that are gone down with the slain--ashamed of the terror which they caused through their might; and they lie uncircumcised with them that are slain by the sword, and bear their confusion with them that go down to the pit. 31 Pharaoh shall see them, and shall be comforted over all his multitude, Pharaoh and all his army slain by the sword, saith the Lord Jehovah. 32 For I have caused my terror in the land of the living; and he shall be laid in the midst of the uncircumcised, with them that are slain by the sword, Pharaoh and all his multitude, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 33

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, speak to the children of thy people, and say unto them, When I bring the sword upon a land, and the people of the land take one man from among them all, and set him for their watchman: 3 if he see the sword coming upon the land, and blow the trumpet, and warn the people; 4 then whosoever heareth the sound of the trumpet, and taketh not warning, if the sword come and take him away, his blood shall be upon his own head. 5 He heard the sound of the trumpet, and took not warning; his blood is upon him: whereas had he taken warning, he would have delivered his soul. 6 But if the watchman see the sword coming, and blow not the trumpet, and the people be not warned, if the sword come and take a person from among them, he is taken away in his iniquity; but his blood will I require at the watchman's hand. 7 So thou, son of man, I have set thee a watchman unto the house of Israel; and thou shalt hear the word from my mouth, and warn them from me. 8 When I say unto the wicked, Wicked man, thou shalt certainly die; and thou speakest not to warn the wicked from his way, that wicked man shall die in his iniquity; but his blood will I require at thy hand. 9 But if thou warn the wicked of his way to turn from it, and he do not turn from his way, he shall die in his iniquity; but thou hast delivered thy soul.

10 And thou, son of man, say unto the house of Israel, Thus ye speak, saying, Our transgressions and our sins are upon us, and we waste away in them, how then should we live? 11 Say unto them, As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, I have no pleasure in the death of the wicked; but that the wicked turn from his way and live. Turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways; for why will ye die, O house of Israel? 12 And thou, son of man, say unto the children of thy people, The righteousness of the righteous shall not deliver him in the day of his transgression; and as for the wickedness of the wicked, he shall not fall thereby in the day that he turneth from his wickedness; neither shall the righteous be able to live thereby in the day that he sinneth. 13 When I say to the righteous that he shall certainly live, and he trusteth to his righteousness and doeth what is wrong, none of his righteous acts shall be remembered; but in his unrighteousness which he hath done, in it shall he die. 14 And when I say unto the wicked, Thou shalt certainly die, and he turneth from his sin, and doeth judgment and justice; 15 if the wicked restore the pledge, give again that he had taken by robbery, walk in the statutes of life, doing nothing that is wrong; he shall certainly live, he shall not die. 16 None of his sins which he hath committed shall be remembered against him: he hath done judgment and justice; he shall certainly live. 17 Yet the children of thy people say, The way of the Lord is not equal: but as for them, their way is not equal. 18 When the righteous turneth from his righteousness, and doeth what is wrong, then he shall die therein. 19 And when the wicked turneth from his wickedness, and doeth judgment and justice, he shall live for these things. 20 Yet ye say, The way of the Lord is not equal. O house of Israel, I will judge you every one after his ways.

21 And it came to pass in the twelfth year of our captivity, in the tenth month, on the fifth of the month, that one who had escaped out of Jerusalem came unto me, saying, The city is smitten! 22 Now the hand of Jehovah had been upon me in the evening, before he that had escaped came; and he had opened my mouth against his coming to me in the morning; and my mouth was opened, and I was no more dumb. 23 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 24 Son of man, they that inhabit those waste places in the land of Israel speak, saying, Abraham was one, and he inherited this land, and we are many: the land is given us for a possession. 25 Therefore say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Ye eat with the blood, and lift up your eyes toward your idols, and shed blood; and shall ye possess the land? 26 Ye stand upon your sword, ye work abomination, and ye defile every one his neighbour's wife; and shall ye possess the land? 27 Say thou thus unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: As I live, verily they that are in the waste places shall fall by the sword, and him that is in the open field will I give to the beasts to be devoured, and they that are in the strongholds and in the caves shall die of the pestilence. 28 And I will make the land a desolation and an astonishment, and the pride of her strength shall cease; and the mountains of Israel shall be desolated, so that none shall pass through. 29 And they shall know that I am Jehovah, when I have made the land a desolation and an astonishment because of all their abominations which they have committed.

30 And as for thee, son of man, the children of thy people keep talking of thee by the walls and in the doors of the houses, and speak one to another, every one to his brother, saying, Come, I pray you, and hear what is the word that cometh forth from Jehovah. 31 And they come unto thee as a people cometh, and they sit before thee as my people, and they hear thy words, but they do them not; for with their mouth they shew much love, but their heart goeth after their dishonest gain. 32 And behold, thou art unto them as a lovely song, a pleasant voice, and one that playeth well on an instrument; and they hear thy words, but they do them not. 33 And when this cometh to pass (behold, it will come), then shall they know that a prophet hath been among them.

Ezekiel 35

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, set thy face against mount Seir, and prophesy against it, 3 and say unto it, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, mount Seir, and I will stretch out my hand upon thee, and I will make thee a desolation and an astonishment. 4 I will lay thy cities waste, and thou shalt be a desolation: and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah. 5 Because thou hast had a perpetual hatred, and hast given over the children of Israel to the power of the sword, in the time of their calamity, in the time of the iniquity of the end; 6 therefore, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, I will certainly appoint thee unto blood, and blood shall pursue thee; since thou hast not hated blood, blood shall pursue thee. 7 And I will make mount Seir a desolation and an astonishment, and cut off from it him that passeth out and him that returneth; 8 and I will fill his mountains with his slain. In thy hills, and in thy valleys, and in all thy water-courses shall they fall that are slain with the sword. 9 I will make thee perpetual desolations, and thy cities shall not be inhabited: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah.

10 Because thou hast said, These two nations and these two countries shall be mine, and we will possess it, whereas Jehovah was there: 11 therefore, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, I will even do according to thine anger and according to thine envy, as thou hast done out of thy hatred against them; and I will make myself known among them, when I shall judge thee. 12 And thou shalt know that I Jehovah have heard all thy reproaches, which thou hast uttered against the mountains of Israel, saying, They are laid desolate, they are given us to devour. 13 And ye have magnified yourselves against me with your mouth, and have multiplied your words against me: I have heard them. 14 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: When the whole earth rejoiceth, I will make thee a desolation. 15 As thou didst rejoice at the inheritance of the house of Israel, because it was desolated, so will I do unto thee: thou shalt be a desolation, O mount Seir, and all Edom, the whole of it: and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 38

1 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 2 Son of man, set thy face against Gog, the land of Magog, the prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal, and prophesy against him, 3 and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, O Gog, prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal. 4 And I will turn thee back, and put hooks into thy jaws, and I will bring thee forth, and all thine army, horses and horsemen, all of them thoroughly equipped, a great assemblage with targets and shields, all of them handling swords: 5 Persia, Cush, and Phut with them, all of them with shield and helmet; 6 Gomer, and all his bands; the house of Togarmah from the uttermost north, and all his bands; --many peoples with thee. 7 Be thou prepared, and prepare for thyself thou, and all thine assemblage that are assembled unto thee, and be thou a guard unto them. 8 After many days shalt thou be visited; at the end of years thou shalt come into the land brought back from the sword and gathered out of many peoples, upon the mountains of Israel which have been a perpetual waste: but it is brought forth out from the peoples, and they shall all of them be dwelling in safety. 9 And thou shalt ascend, thou shalt come like a storm, thou shalt be like a cloud to cover the land, thou, and all thy bands, and many peoples with thee. 10 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: It shall even come to pass in that day that things shall come into thy mind, and thou shalt think an evil thought; 11 and thou shalt say, I will go up to the land of unwalled villages; I will come to them that are in quiet, that dwell in safety, all of them dwelling without walls, and having neither bars nor gates, 12 to seize a spoil, and to take a prey; to turn thy hand against the waste places that are now inhabited, and against a people gathered out of the nations, which have gotten cattle and goods, that dwell in the middle of the land. 13 Sheba, and Dedan, and the merchants of Tarshish, with all the young lions thereof, shall say unto thee, Art thou come to seize a spoil? hast thou gathered thine assemblage to take a prey? to carry away silver and gold, to take cattle and goods, to seize a great spoil?

14 Therefore prophesy, son of man, and say unto Gog, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: In that day when my people Israel dwelleth in safety, shalt thou not know it? 15 And thou shalt come from thy place out of the uttermost north, thou and many peoples with thee, all of them riding upon horses, a great assemblage and a mighty army. 16 And thou shalt come up against my people Israel as a cloud to cover the land--it shall be at the end of days--and I will bring thee against my land, that the nations may know me, when I shall be hallowed in thee, O Gog, before their eyes. 17 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Art thou not he of whom I have spoken in old time through my servants the prophets of Israel, who prophesied in those days, for many years, that I would bring thee against them? 18 And it shall come to pass in that day, in the day when Gog shall come against the land of Israel, saith the Lord Jehovah, that my fury shall come up in my face; 19 for in my jealousy, in the fire of my wrath have I spoken, Verily in that day there shall be a great shaking in the land of Israel; 20 so that the fish of the sea, and the fowl of the heavens, and the beasts of the field, and all creeping things which creep upon the earth, and all mankind that are upon the face of the earth shall shake at my presence; and the mountains shall be thrown down, and the steep places shall fall, and every wall shall fall to the ground. 21 And I will call for a sword against him throughout all my mountains, saith the Lord Jehovah: every man's sword shall be against his brother. 22 And I will enter into judgment with him with pestilence and with blood; and I will rain upon him, and upon his bands, and upon the many peoples that are with him, overflowing rain and great hailstones, fire and brimstone. 23 And I will magnify myself, and sanctify myself, and I will be known in the eyes of many nations, and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 39

1 And thou, son of man, prophesy against Gog, and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, O Gog, prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal; 2 and I will turn thee back, and lead thee, and will cause thee to come up from the uttermost north, and will bring thee upon the mountains of Israel. 3 And I will smite thy bow out of thy left hand, and will cause thine arrows to fall out of thy right hand. 4 Thou shalt fall upon the mountains of Israel, thou, and all thy bands, and the peoples that are with thee: I have given thee to be meat for the birds of prey of every wing, and to the beasts of the field. 5 Thou shalt fall on the open field; for I have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah. 6 And I will send a fire on Magog, and among them that dwell at ease in the isles: and they shall know that I am Jehovah. 7 And my holy name will I make known in the midst of my people Israel; and I will not suffer my holy name to be profaned any more: and the nations shall know that I am Jehovah, the Holy One in Israel.

8 Behold, it cometh, and shall be done, saith the Lord Jehovah. This is the day whereof I have spoken. 9 And they that dwell in the cities of Israel shall go forth, and shall kindle fire, and burn weapons, and shields, and targets, bows, and arrows, and hand-staves, and spears: and they shall make fires with them seven years. 10 And no wood shall be taken out of the field, neither cut down out of the forests; for they shall make fire with the weapons; and they shall spoil those that spoiled them, and plunder those that plundered them, saith the Lord Jehovah. 11 And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will give unto Gog a place there for burial in Israel, the valley of the passers-by to the east of the sea; and it shall stop the wayof the passers-by; and there shall they bury Gog and all the multitude; and they shall call it, Valley of Hamon-Gog. 12 And seven months shall the house of Israel be burying them, that they may cleanse the land; 13 and all the people of the land shall bury them; and it shall be to them for renown in the day that I shall be glorified, saith the Lord Jehovah. 14 And they shall sever out men of continual employment to go through the land, who, with the passers-by, shall bury those that remain upon the face of the land, to cleanse it: at the end of seven months shall they make a search. 15 And the passers-by shall pass through the land, and when any seeth a man's bone, he shall set up a sign by it, till the buriers have buried it in the Valley of Hamon-Gog. 16 And also the name of the city shall be Hamonah. Thus shall they cleanse the land. 17 And thou, son of man, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Speak unto the birds of every wing, and to every beast of the field, Gather yourselves together and come, assemble yourselves on every side to my sacrifice which I sacrifice for you, a great sacrifice upon the mountains of Israel, that ye may eat flesh, and drink blood. 18 Ye shall eat the flesh of the mighty, and drink the blood of the princes of the earth, of rams, of lambs, and of goats, and of bullocks, all of them fatted beasts of Bashan. 19 And ye shall eat fat till ye are full, and drink blood till ye are drunken, of my sacrifice which I sacrifice for you. 20 And ye shall be filled at my table with horses and charioteers, with mighty men, and with all men of war, saith the Lord Jehovah. 21 And I will set my glory among the nations, and all the nations shall see my judgment which I have executed, and my hand which I have laid upon them. 22 And the house of Israel shall know that I am Jehovah their God[*] from that day and forward.

23 And the nations shall know that the house of Israel went into captivity for their iniquity, because they were unfaithful against me; and I hid my face from them, and gave them into the hand of their enemies, so that they fell all of them by the sword. 24 According to their uncleanness and according to their transgressions I did unto them, and I hid my face from them. 25 Therefore, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Now will I bring again the captivity of Jacob, and have mercy upon the whole house of Israel, and will be jealous for my holy name: 26 and they shall bear their confusion, and all their unfaithfulness in which they have acted unfaithfully against me, when they shall dwell safely in their land, and none shall make them afraid; 27 when I have brought them again from the peoples, and gathered them out of their enemies' lands, and am hallowed in them in the sight of many nations. 28 And they shall know that I am Jehovah their God[*] in that I caused them to be led into captivity among the nations, and have gathered them unto their own land, and have left none of them any more there. 29 And I will not hide my face any more from them, for I shall have poured out my Spirit upon the house of Israel, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Ezekiel 41

1 And he brought me to the temple; and he measured the posts, six cubits broad on the one side, and six cubits broad on the other side, the breadth of the tent. 2 And the breadth of the entry was ten cubits, and the sides of the entry were five cubits on this side, and five cubits on that side; and he measured its length, forty cubits, and the breadth, twenty cubits. 3 And he went inwards, and measured the post of the entry, two cubits; and the entry, six cubits; and the breadth of the entry, seven cubits. 4 And he measured its length, twenty cubits; and the breadth, twenty cubits, before the temple: and he said unto me, This is the most holy place. 5 And he measured the wall of the house, six cubits; and the breadth of the side-chambers, four cubits, round about the house on every side. 6 And the side-chambers were three, chamber over chamber, and thirty in order; and they entered into the wall which the house had for the side-chambers round about, that they might have hold; but they had not hold in the wall of the house. 7 And for the side-chambers there was an enlarging, and it went round about the house increasing upward; for the surrounding of the house increased upward round about the house; therefore the house had width upward, and so ascended from the lower story to the upper, by the middle one. 8 And I saw that the house had an elevation round about: the foundations of the side-chambers, a full reed, six cubits to the joint. 9 The thickness of the wall, which was for the side-chambers without, was five cubits, as also what was left free along the building of the side-chambers that pertained to the house. 10 And between the cells and the house was a width of twenty cubits round about the house on every side. 11 And the entry of the side-chambers was toward what was left free, one entry toward the north, and one entry toward the south; and the width of the space left free was five cubits round about.

12 And the building that was before the separate place at the end toward the west was seventy cubits broad; and the wall of the building was five cubits thick round about; and its length ninety cubits. 13 And he measured the house: the length a hundred cubits; and the separate place, and the building, and its walls, the length a hundred cubits; 14 and the breadth of the front of the house, and of the separate places toward the east, a hundred cubits. 15 And he measured the length of the building before the separate place, which was at the back of it, with its galleries on the one side and on the other side, a hundred cubits; and the inner temple, and the porches of the court. 16 The thresholds, and the closed windows, and the galleries round about the three of them (opposite the thresholds it was wainscoted with wood round about, and from the ground up to the windows, and the windows were covered), 17 and above, over the entry, even unto the inner house, and without, and by all the wall round about, within and without, all was by measure. 18 And it was made with cherubim and palm-trees, and a palm-tree was between cherub and cherub; and the cherub had two faces: 19 the face of a man was toward the palm-tree on the one side, and the face of a young lion toward the palm-tree on the other side: so was it made upon all the house round about. 20 From the ground unto above the entry were the cherubim and the palm-trees made, and on the wall of the temple. 21 As for the temple, the door-posts were squared; and the front of the sanctuary had the same appearance. 22 The altar was of wood, three cubits high, and its length two cubits; and its corners, and its length, and its walls were of wood. And he said unto me, This is the table which is before Jehovah. 23 And the temple and the sanctuary had two doors. 24 And the doors had two leaves, two turning-leaves: two for the one door, and two leaves for the other. 25 And there were made on them, on the doors of the temple, cherubim and palm-trees, as there were made upon the walls; and there was a wooden portal in front of the porch without, 26 and closed windows and palm-trees on the one side and on the other side, on the sides of the porch and the side chambers of the house and the portals.

Ezekiel 42

1 And he brought me forth into the outer court, the way toward the north; and he brought me to the cells that were over against the separate place and which were over against the building, toward the north, 2 before the length of the hundred cubits: the entry was on the north, and the breadth was fifty cubits, 3 over against the twenty cubits that pertained to the inner court, and over against the pavement that pertained to the outer court; there was gallery against gallery in the third story; 4 and before the cells was a walk of ten cubits in breadth, and a way of a hundred cubits inward; and their entries were toward the north. 5 And the upper cells, because the galleries encroached on them, were shorter than the lower, and than the middle-most of the building. 6 For they were in three stories, but had not pillars as the pillars of the courts; therefore the third story was straitened more than the lowest and the middle-most from the ground. 7 And the wall that was without, answering to the cells, toward the outer court in the front of the cells, its length was fifty cubits: 8 for the length of the cells that were against the outer court was fifty cubits; but behold, before the temple it was a hundred cubits. 9 And under these cells was the entry from the east, as one goeth into them from the outer court. 10 In the breadth of the wall of the court toward the south, before the separate place, and before the building, were cells; 11 and a passage before them, like the appearance of the cells that were toward the north, according to their length, according to their breadth and all their goings out, and according to their fashions, and according to their doors. 12 And according to the doors of the cells that were toward the south there was a door at the head of the way, the way directly before the corresponding wall toward the east as one entereth into them. 13 And he said unto me, The north cells and the south cells, which are before the separate place, they are holy cells, where the priests that come near unto Jehovah shall eat the most holy things; there shall they lay the most holy things, both the oblation and the sin-offering and the trespass-offering: for the place is holy. 14 When the priests enter in, they shall not go forth from the sanctuary into the outer court, but there they shall lay their garments wherein they minister, for they are holy; and they shall put on other garments, and shall approach to that which is for the people.

15 And when he had made an end of measuring the inner house, he brought me forth toward the gate whose front was toward the east, and measured the enclosure round about. 16 He measured the east side with the measuring-reed, five hundred reeds, with the measuring-reed round about. 17 He measured the north side, five hundred reeds, with the measuring-reed round about. 18 He measured the south side, five hundred reeds, with the measuring-reed. 19 He turned about to the west side, and measured five hundred reeds with the measuring-reed. 20 He measured it on the four sides; it had a wall round about, five hundred long, and five hundred broad, to make a separation between that which was holy and that which was common.

Ezekiel 43

1 And he brought me unto the gate, the gate which looked toward the east. 2 And behold, the glory of the God[*] of Israel came from the way of the east; and his voice was like the voice of many waters; and the earth was lit up with his glory. 3 And the appearance of the vision that I saw was according to the vision that I had seen when I came to destroy the city; and the visions were like the vision that I saw by the river Chebar: and I fell upon my face. 4 And the glory of Jehovah came into the house by the way of the gate whose front was toward the east. 5 And the Spirit lifted me up, and brought me into the inner court; and behold, the glory of Jehovah filled the house. 6 And I heard one speaking unto me out of the house; and a man was standing by me.

7 And he said unto me, Son of man, this is the place of my throne, and the place of the soles of my feet, where I will dwell in the midst of the children of Israel for ever; and the house of Israel shall no more defile my holy name, they nor their kings, with their fornication, and with the carcases of their kings in their high places, 8 in that they set their threshold by my threshold, and their post by my post, and there was only a wall between me and them, and they defiled my holy name with their abominations which they committed; and I consumed them in mine anger. 9 Now let them put away their fornication, and the carcases of their kings, far from me, and I will dwell in the midst of them for ever. 10 Thou, son of man, shew the house to the house of Israel, that they may be confounded at their iniquities; and let them measure the pattern. 11 And if they be confounded at all that they have done, make known to them the form of the house, and its fashion, and its goings out, and its comings in, and all its forms, and all its statutes, yea, all the forms thereof, and all the laws thereof; and write it in their sight, that they may keep the whole form thereof, and all the statutes thereof, and do them. 12 This is the law of the house: Upon the top of the mountain all its border round about is most holy. Behold, this is the law of the house.

13 And these are the measures of the altar in cubits: the cubit is a cubit and a hand breadth. The bottom was a cubit in height and the breadth a cubit, and its border on the edge thereof round about, one span: and this was the base of the altar. 14 And from the bottom upon the ground to the lower settle was two cubits, and the breadth one cubit; and from the small settle to the great settle, four cubits, and the breadth a cubit. 15 And the upper altar was four cubits; and from the hearth of ·God[*] and upward were four horns. 16 And the hearth of ·God[*] was twelve cubits long, by twelve broad, square in the four sides thereof. 17 And the settle was fourteen cubits long by fourteen broad in the four sides thereof; and the border about it, half a cubit; and the bottom thereof a cubit round about: and its steps looked toward the east. 18 And he said unto me, Son of man, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: These are the ordinances of the altar in the day when they shall make it, to offer up burnt-offerings thereon, and to sprinkle blood thereon. 19 And thou shalt give to the priests the Levites that are of the seed of Zadok, who come near unto me, to minister unto me, saith the Lord Jehovah, a young bullock for a sin-offering. 20 And thou shalt take of its blood, and put it on the four horns thereof, and on the four corners of the settle, and upon the border round about: so shalt thou purge and make atonement for it. 21 And thou shalt take the bullock of the sin-offering, and it shall be burned in the appointed place of the house, outside the sanctuary. 22 And on the second day thou shalt present a he-goat without blemish for a sin-offering; and they shall purge the altar, as they purged it with the bullock. 23 When thou hast ended purging it, thou shalt present a young bullock without blemish, and a ram out of the flock without blemish; 24 and thou shalt present them before Jehovah; and the priests shall cast salt upon them, and they shall offer them up for a burnt-offering unto Jehovah. 25 Seven days shalt thou offer daily a goat for a sin-offering; they shall also offer a young bullock, and a ram out of the flock without blemish. 26 Seven days shall they make atonement for the altar and purify it, and consecrate it. 27 And when these days are ended, it shall be that upon the eighth day and onwards the priests shall offer your burnt-offerings upon the altar, and your peace-offerings; and I will accept you, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: El

Hebrew: El

Ezekiel 44

1 And he brought me back toward the outer gate of the sanctuary which looked toward the east; and it was shut. 2 And Jehovah said unto me, This gate shall be shut; it shall not be opened, and no one shall enter in by it: for Jehovah, the God[*] of Israel, hath entered in by it; and it shall be shut. 3 As for the prince, he, the prince, shall sit in it to eat bread before Jehovah: he shall enter by the way of the porch of the gate, and shall go out by the way of the same.

4 And he brought me the way of the north gate before the house; and I beheld, and lo, the glory of Jehovah filled the house of Jehovah: and I fell upon my face. 5 And Jehovah said unto me, Son of man, apply thy heart, and behold with thine eyes, and hear with thine ears all that I say unto thee concerning all the statutes of the house of Jehovah, and all the laws thereof; and mark well the entering in of the house, with every going forth of the sanctuary; 6 and say to the rebellious, to the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Let it suffice you of all your abominations, O house of Israel, 7 in that ye have brought strangers, uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, to be in my sanctuary, to profane it, even my house, when ye offered my bread, the fat and the blood; and they have broken my covenant besides all your abominations. 8 And ye have not kept the charge of my holy things, but have set keepers of my charge in my sanctuary for yourselves. 9 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: No stranger, uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, shall enter into my sanctuary, of any stranger that is among the children of Israel.

10 But the Levites who went away far from me, when Israel went astray, going astray from me after their idols, they shall even bear their iniquity; 11 but they shall be ministers in my sanctuary, having oversight at the gates of the house, and doing the service of the house: they shall slaughter the burnt-offering and the sacrifice for the people, and they shall stand before them to minister unto them. 12 Because they ministered unto them before their idols, and were unto the house of Israel a stumbling-block of iniquity; therefore have I lifted up my hand against them, saith the Lord Jehovah, that they shall bear their iniquity. 13 And they shall not draw near unto me, to do the office of a priest unto me, nor to draw near to any of my holy things, even to the most holy; but they shall bear their confusion, and their abominations which they have committed. 14 And I will make them keepers of the charge of the house, for all the service thereof, and for all that shall be done therein. 15 But the priests, the Levites, the sons of Zadok, that kept the charge of my sanctuary when the children of Israel went astray from me, they shall approach unto me to minister unto me, and they shall stand before me to present unto me the fat and the blood, saith the Lord Jehovah. 16 They shall enter into my sanctuary, and they shall approach unto my table, to minister unto me, and they shall keep my charge.

17 And it shall come to pass when they enter in at the gates of the inner court, they shall be clothed with linen garments; and no wool shall come upon them, when they minister in the gates of the inner court, and towards the house. 18 They shall have linen tires upon their heads, and shall have linen breeches upon their loins; they shall not gird on anything that causeth sweat. 19 And when they go forth into the outer court, into the outer court to the people, they shall put off their garments wherein they ministered, and lay them in the holy cells; and they shall put on other garments, that they may not hallow the people with their garments. 20 Neither shall they shave their heads, nor suffer their locks to grow long: they shall duly poll their heads. 21 Neither shall any priest drink wine when they enter into the inner court. 22 And they shall not take for their wives a widow, nor her that is put away; but they shall take maidens of the seed of the house of Israel, or a widow that is the widow of a priest. 23 And they shall teach my people the difference between holy and profane, and cause them to discern between unclean and clean. 24 And in controversy they shall stand to judge: they shall judge it according to my judgments; and they shall keep my laws and my statutes in all my solemnities; and they shall hallow my sabbaths. 25 And they shall come at no dead person to become unclean; but for father, or for mother, or for son, or for daughter, for brother, or for sister that hath had no husband, they may become unclean. 26 And after he is cleansed, they shall count unto him seven days. 27 And on the day that he goeth into the sanctuary, unto the inner court, to minister in the sanctuary, he shall present his sin-offering, saith the Lord Jehovah. 28 And it shall be unto them for an inheritance; I am their inheritance: and ye shall give them no possession in Israel; I am their possession. 29 They shall eat the oblation and the sin-offering and the trespass-offering; and every devoted thing in Israel shall be theirs. 30 And the first of all the first-fruits of every kind, and every heave-offering of every kind, of all your heave-offerings, shall be for the priests; ye shall also give unto the priest the first of your dough, that he may cause the blessing to rest on thy house. 31 The priests shall not eat of anything that dieth of itself, or of that which is torn, whether of fowl or of beast.

Hebrew: Elohim

Ezekiel 45

1 And when ye shall divide by lot the land for inheritance, ye shall offer a heave-offering unto Jehovah, a holy portion of the land: the length shall be the length of five and twenty thousand cubits, and the breadth ten thousand. This shall be holy in all the borders thereof round about. 2 Of this there shall be for the sanctuary five hundred reeds by five hundred, square round about; and fifty cubits round about for the suburbs thereof. 3 And of this measure shalt thou measure the length of five and twenty thousand, and the breadth of ten thousand; and in it shall be the sanctuary, the holy of holies. 4 This is the holy portion of the land; it shall be for the priests who do the service of the sanctuary, who draw near to serve Jehovah, and it shall be a place for their houses, and a holy place for the sanctuary. 5 And a space of five and twenty thousand in length, and ten thousand in breadth, shall the Levites, who do the service of the house, have for themselves, for a possession, for their habitations. 6 And ye shall appoint the possession of the city five thousand in breadth, and five and twenty thousand in length, alongside of the holy heave-offering: it shall be for the whole house of Israel. 7 And the prince shall have his portion on the one side and on the other side of the holy heave-offering and of the possession of the city, over against the holy heave-offering, and over against the possession of the city, from the west side westward, and from the east side eastward; and in length answering to one of the portions of the tribes from the west border unto the east border. 8 As land shall it be his for a possession in Israel; and my princes shall no more oppress my people; but they shall give the land to the house of Israel according to their tribes.

9 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Let it suffice you, princes of Israel! Put away violence and spoil, and execute judgment and justice; take off your exactions from my people, saith the Lord Jehovah. 10 Ye shall have just balances, and a just ephah, and a just bath. 11 The ephah and the bath shall be of one measure, so that the bath may contain the tenth part of a homer, and the ephah the tenth part of a homer: the measure thereof shall be according to the homer. 12 And the shekel shall be twenty gerahs; twenty shekels, five and twenty shekels, fifteen shekels, shall be your maneh.

13 This is the heave-offering which ye shall offer: the sixth part of an ephah out of a homer of wheat, and ye shall give the sixth part of an ephah out of a homer of barley; 14 and the set portion of oil, by the bath of oil, the tenth part of a bath out of a cor, which is a homer of ten baths, for ten baths are a homer; 15 and one lamb out of the flock, out of two hundred, from the well-watered pastures of Israel; --for an oblation, and for a burnt-offering, and for peace-offerings, to make atonement for them, saith the Lord Jehovah. 16 All the people of the land shall be held to this heave-offering for the prince in Israel. 17 And it shall be the prince's part to supply the burnt-offerings, and the oblation, and the drink-offering, at the feasts, and at the new moons, and on the sabbaths, in all the solemnities of the house of Israel: it is he that shall prepare the sin-offering, and the oblation, and the burnt-offering, and the peace-offerings, to make atonement for the house of Israel. 18 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: In the first month, on the first of the month, thou shalt take a young bullock, without blemish, and thou shalt purge the sanctuary. 19 And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin-offering, and put it upon the posts of the house, and upon the four corners of the settle of the altar, and upon the posts of the gate of the inner court. 20 So thou shalt do also on the seventh of the month for every one that erreth, and for the simple; and ye shall make atonement for the house. 21 In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, ye shall have the passover, a feast of seven days: unleavened bread shall be eaten. 22 And upon that day shall the prince offer for himself and for all the people of the land a bullock for a sin-offering. 23 And the seven days of the feast he shall offer a burnt-offering to Jehovah, seven bullocks and seven rams without blemish daily for the seven days; and a he-goat daily for a sin-offering. 24 And he shall offer an oblation of an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram; and oil, a hin for an ephah. 25 In the seventh month, on the fifteenth day of the month, at the feast, shall he do the like seven days, according to the sin-offering, according to the burnt-offering, and according to the oblation, and according to the oil.

Ezekiel 46

1 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: The gate of the inner court that looketh toward the east shall be shut the six working-days; but on the sabbath-day it shall be opened, and on the day of the new moon it shall be opened. 2 And the prince shall enter by the way of the porch of that gate from without, and shall stand by the post of the gate, and the priests shall offer his burnt-offering and his peace-offerings, and he shall worship at the threshold of the gate, and shall go forth: but the gate shall not be shut until the evening. 3 And the people of the land shall worship at the door of this gate before Jehovah on the sabbaths and on the new moons. 4 And the burnt-offering that the prince shall present unto Jehovah on the sabbath-day shall be six lambs without blemish, and a ram without blemish. 5 And the oblation shall be an ephah for a ram, and the oblation for the lambs as he shall be able to give; and oil, a hin for an ephah. 6 And on the day of the new moon, a young bullock without blemish, and six lambs, and a ram: they shall be without blemish. 7 And he shall offer an oblation, an ephah for the bullock, and an ephah for the ram, and for the lambs according to what his hand may attain unto; and oil, a hin for an ephah. 8 And when the prince cometh in, he shall come in by the way of the porch of the gate, and he shall go out by the way thereof. 9 And when the people of the land come in before Jehovah in the set feasts, he that cometh in by the way of the north gate to worship shall go out by the way of the south gate; and he that cometh in by the way of the south gate shall go out by the way of the north gate: he shall not return by the way of the gate by which he came in, but shall go out straight before him. 10 And the prince shall come in in the midst of them, when they come in; and when they go out, they shall go out together. 11 And on the feast-days, and in the solemnities, the oblation shall be an ephah for a bullock and an ephah for a ram, and for the lambs as he is able to give; and oil, a hin for an ephah. 12 And when the prince shall offer a voluntary burnt-offering or voluntary peace-offerings unto Jehovah, the gate that looketh toward the east shall be opened for him and he shall offer his burnt-offering and his peace-offerings as he did on the sabbath-day, and he shall go out again, and the gate shall be shut after he hath gone out. 13 And thou shalt daily offer a burnt-offering unto Jehovah, of a yearling-lamb without blemish: thou shalt prepare it morning by morning. 14 And thou shalt prepare an oblation with it every morning, the sixth part of an ephah, and of oil the third part of a hin, to moisten the fine flour: an oblation unto Jehovah continually by a perpetual ordinance. 15 They shall offer the lamb, and the oblation, and the oil, every morning for a continual burnt-offering.

16 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: If the prince give a gift unto any of his sons, it shall be that one's inheritance, for his sons: it shall be their possession by inheritance. 17 But if he give a gift of his inheritance to one of his servants, it shall be his until the year of liberty; and it shall return to the prince: to his sons alone shall his inheritance remain. 18 And the prince shall not take of the people's inheritance, to thrust them by oppression out of their possession: he shall give his sons an inheritance out of his own possession: that my people be not scattered every one from his possession.

19 Then he brought me through the passage which was at the side of the gate, into the holy cells which were for the priests, which looked toward the north; and behold, a place was there at the end westward. 20 And he said unto me, This is the place where the priests shall boil the trespass-offering, and the sin-offering, and where they shall bake the oblation, that they bring them not out into the outer court, so as to hallow the people. 21 And he brought me forth into the outer court, and caused me to pass by the four corners of the court; and behold, in every corner of the court there was a court. 22 In the four corners of the court there were enclosed courts, forty cubits long and thirty broad: these four corner courts were of one measure. 23 And there was a row of building round about in them, round about those four, and it was made with boiling places under the rows round about. 24 And he said unto me, These are the boiling-houses, where those who do the service of the house shall boil the sacrifice of the people.

Ezekiel 47

1 And he brought me back to the door of the house; and behold, waters issued out from under the threshold of the house eastward: for the front of the house was eastward. And the waters came down from under, from the right side of the house, south of the altar. 2 And he brought me out by the way of the gate northward, and led me round outside unto the outer gate towards the gate that looketh eastward; and behold, waters ran out on the right side. 3 When the man went forth eastward, a line was in his hand; and he measured a thousand cubits, and he caused me to pass through the waters: the waters were to the ankles. 4 And he measured a thousand cubits, and caused me to pass through the waters: the waters were to the knees. And he measured a thousand and caused me to pass through: the waters were to the loins. 5 And he measured a thousand: it was a river that I could not pass through, for the waters were risen, waters to swim in, a river that could not be passed through. 6 And he said unto me, Son of man, hast thou seen this? And he led me, and brought me back to the bank of the river. 7 When I returned, behold, on the bank of the river were very many trees on the one side and on the other. 8 And he said unto me, These waters issue out toward the east district, and go down into the plain, and go into the sea; when they are brought forth into the sea, the waters thereof shall be healed. 9 And it shall come to pass that every living thing which moveth, whithersoever the double river shall come, shall live. And there shall be a very great multitude of fish; for these waters shall come thither, and the waters of the sea shall be healed; and everything shall live whither the river cometh. 10 And it shall come to pass, that fishers shall stand upon it; from En-gedi even unto En-eglaim shall be a place to spread forth nets: their fish shall be according to their kinds, as the fish of the great sea, exceeding many. 11 But its marshes and its pools shall not be healed; they shall be given up to salt. 12 And by the river, upon its bank, on the one side and on the other, shall grow all trees for food, whose leaf shall not fade, nor their fruit fail: it shall bring forth new fruit every month, for its waters issue out of the sanctuary; and the fruit thereof shall be for food, and the leaf thereof for medicine.

13 Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: This shall be the border whereby ye shall allot the land as inheritance according to the twelve tribes of Israel: Joseph shall have two portions. 14 And ye shall inherit it, one as well as another, the land concerning which I lifted up my hand to give it unto your fathers; and this land shall fall to you for inheritance. 15 And this shall be the border of the land: toward the north side, from the great sea, the way of Hethlon, as one goeth to Zedad, 16 Hamath, Berothah, Sibraim, which is between the border of Damascus and the border of Hamath; Hazer-hatticon, which is by the border of Hauran. 17 And the border from the sea shall be Hazar-enan, the border of Damascus, and the north northward, and the border of Hamath: this is the north side. 18 --And on the east side ye shall measure between Hauran and Damascus, and Gilead and the land of Israel by the Jordan, from the border unto the east sea: this is the east side. 19 --And the south side southward, from Tamar to the waters of Meribah-Kadesh, by the torrent, unto the great sea: this is the south side southward. 20 --And the west side shall be the great sea from the border, as far as over against the entering into Hamath: this is the west side. 21 And ye shall divide this land unto you according to the tribes of Israel. 22 And it shall come to pass that ye shall divide it by lot for an inheritance unto you, and to the strangers that sojourn among you, who shall beget children among you; and they shall be unto you as the home-born among the children of Israel: with you shall they draw by lot inheritance among the tribes of Israel. 23 And it shall come to pass that in the tribe in which the stranger sojourneth, there shall ye give him his inheritance, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Daniel 4

1 Nebuchadnezzar the king unto all the peoples, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied unto you. 2 It hath seemed good unto me to declare the signs and wonders that the Most High God[*] hath wrought toward me. 3 How great are his signs! and how mighty are his wonders! His kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and his dominion is from generation to generation.

4 I Nebuchadnezzar was at rest in my house, and flourishing in my palace. 5 I saw a dream which made me afraid, and the thoughts upon my bed and the visions of my head troubled me. 6 And I made a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before me, that they might make known unto me the interpretation of the dream. 7 Then came in the scribes, the magicians, the Chaldeans, and the astrologers; and I told the dream before them; but they did not make known unto me the interpretation of it. 8 But at the last Daniel came in before me, whose name is Belteshazzar, according to the name of my god, and in whom is the spirit of the holy gods; and before him I told the dream: 9 O Belteshazzar, master of the scribes, because I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in thee, and no secret is too hard for thee, tell me the visions of my dream which I have seen, and the interpretation of it. 10 Thus were the visions of my head upon my bed: I saw, and behold a tree in the midst of the earth, and its height was great. 11 The tree grew, and was strong, and its height reached unto the heavens, and the sight thereof to the end of all the earth. 12 Its leaves were beautiful, and its fruit abundant, and in it was food for all: the beasts of the field found shade under it, and the birds of the heavens dwelt in its branches, and all flesh was fed from it. 13 I saw in the visions of my head upon my bed, and behold, a watcher and a holy one came down from the heavens; 14 he cried aloud, and said thus: Hew down the tree, and cut off its branches, shake off its leaves, and scatter its fruit; let the beasts get away from under it, and the birds from its branches. 15 Nevertheless leave the stump of its roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be bathed with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts in the grass of the earth. 16 Let his heart be changed from man's, and let a beast's heart be given unto him; and let seven times pass over him. 17 This sentence is by the decree of the watchers, and the decision by the word of the holy ones: that the living may know that the Most High ruleth over the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will, and setteth up over it the basest of men. 18 This dream I, king Nebuchadnezzar, have seen; and thou, Belteshazzar, tell the interpretation, forasmuch as all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to make known unto me the interpretation; but thou art able, for the spirit of the holy gods is in thee.

19 Then Daniel, whose name is Belteshazzar, was astonied for one hour, and his thoughts troubled him. The king spoke and said, Belteshazzar, let not the dream, nor its interpretation, trouble thee. Belteshazzar answered and said, My lord, the dream be to them that hate thee, and its interpretation to thine enemies! 20 The tree that thou sawest, which grew and was strong, whose height reached unto the heavens, and the sight of it to all the earth; 21 whose leaves were beautiful, and its fruit abundant, and in it was food for all; under which the beasts of the field dwelt, and in whose branches the birds of the heavens had their habitation: 22 it is thou, O king, who art grown and become strong; for thy greatness is grown, and reacheth unto the heavens, and thy dominion to the end of the earth. 23 And whereas the king saw a watcher and a holy one coming down from the heavens, and saying, Hew the tree down, and destroy it; nevertheless leave the stump of its roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be bathed with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts of the field, till seven times pass over him: 24 this is the interpretation, O king, and it is the decree of the Most High, which cometh upon my lord the king: 25 They shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field, and they shall make thee to eat grass as oxen, and thou shalt be bathed with the dew of heaven; and seven times shall pass over thee, till thou know that the Most High ruleth over the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will. 26 And whereas it was commanded to leave the stump of the roots of the tree; thy kingdom shall remain unto thee, after that thou shalt know that the heavens do rule. 27 Therefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable unto thee, and break off thy sins by righteousness, and thine iniquities by shewing mercy to the poor; if it may be a lengthening of thy tranquillity.

28 All this came upon king Nebuchadnezzar. 29 At the end of twelve months he was walking upon the royal palace of Babylon: 30 the king spoke and said, Is not this great Babylon, that I have built for the house of the kingdom by the might of my power and for the glory of my majesty? 31 While the word was in the king's mouth, there fell a voice from the heavens: King Nebuchadnezzar, to thee it is spoken: The kingdom is departed from thee; 32 and they shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field; they shall make thee to eat grass as oxen, and seven times shall pass over thee, until thou know that the Most High ruleth over the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will. 33 The same hour was the word fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar; and he was driven from men, and ate grass as oxen; and his body was bathed with the dew of heaven, till his hair grew like eagles' feathers, and his nails like birds' claws.

34 And at the end of the days I Nebuchadnezzar lifted up mine eyes unto the heavens, and mine understanding returned unto me, and I blessed the Most High, and I praised and honoured him that liveth for ever, whose dominion is an everlasting dominion, and his kingdom is from generation to generation. 35 And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing; and he doeth according to his will in the army of the heavens, and among the inhabitants of the earth; and none can stay his hand, or say unto him, What doest thou? 36 At the same time mine understanding returned unto me; and for the glory of my kingdom, my majesty and brightness returned unto me; and my counsellors and my nobles sought me; and I was established in my kingdom, and excellent greatness was added unto me. 37 Now I Nebuchadnezzar praise and extol and honour the King of the heavens, all whose works are truth, and his paths judgment: and those that walk in pride he is able to abase.

Hebrew: Elohim

Daniel 8

1 In the third year of the reign of Belshazzar the king, a vision appeared unto me, even to me Daniel, after that which appeared unto me at the first. 2 And I saw in the vision; and it came to pass, when I saw, that I was in the fortress of Shushan, which is in the province of Elam. And I saw in the vision, and I was by the river Ulai. 3 And I lifted up mine eyes and saw, and behold, there stood before the river a ram which had two horns; and the two horns were high; and one was higher than the other, and the higher came up last. 4 I saw the ram pushing westward, and northward, and southward, and no beast could stand before him, neither was there any that could deliver out of his hand; and he did according to his will, and became great. 5 And as I was considering, behold, a he-goat came from the west over the face of the whole earth, and touched not the ground: and the goat had a notable horn between his eyes. 6 And he came to the ram that had the two horns, which I had seen standing before the river, and ran upon him in the fury of his power. 7 And I saw him come close to the ram, and he was enraged with him, and smote the ram, and broke his two horns; and there was no power in the ram to stand before him; and he cast him down to the ground, and trampled upon him; and there was none that could deliver the ram out of his hand. 8 And the he-goat became exceeding great; but when he was become strong, the great horn was broken; and in its stead came up four notable ones toward the four winds of the heavens. 9 And out of one of them came forth a little horn, which became exceeding great, toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the beauty of the earth. 10 And it became great, even to the host of heaven; and it cast down some of the host and of the stars to the ground, and trampled upon them. 11 (And he magnified himself even to the prince of the host, and from him the continual sacrifice was taken away, and the place of his sanctuary was cast down. 12 And a time of trial was appointed unto the continual sacrifice by reason of transgression.) And it cast down the truth to the ground; and it practised and prospered. 13 And I heard one saint speaking, and another saint said unto that one who spoke, How long shall be the vision of the continual sacrifice and of the transgression that maketh desolate, to give both the sanctuary and the host to be trodden down under foot? 14 And he said unto me, Until two thousand and three hundred evenings and mornings: then shall the sanctuary be vindicated.

15 And it came to pass, when I Daniel had seen the vision, I sought for the understanding of it, and behold, there stood before me as the appearance of a man. 16 And I heard a man's voice between the banks of the Ulai; and he called and said, Gabriel, make this man to understand the vision. 17 And he came near where I stood; and when he came, I was afraid, and fell on my face; and he said unto me, Understand, son of man; for the vision is for the time of the end. 18 Now, as he was speaking with me, I was in a deep stupor, with my face toward the ground. And he touched me, and set me up where I had stood. 19 And he said, Behold, I will make thee know what shall be at the end of the indignation: for at the set time the end shall be. 20 The ram that thou sawest having the two horns: they are the kings of Media and Persia. 21 And the rough goat is the king of Greece; and the great horn that was between his eyes is the first king. 22 Now that being broken, whereas four stood up in its stead, four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not with his power. 23 And at the latter time of their kingdom, when the transgressors shall have come to the full, a king of bold countenance, and understanding riddles, shall stand up. 24 And his power shall be mighty, but not by his own power; and he shall destroy marvellously, and shall prosper, and shall practise, and shall destroy the mighty ones, and the people of the saints. 25 And through his cunning shall he cause craft to prosper in his hand; and he will magnify himself in his heart, and by prosperity will corrupt many; and he will stand up against the Prince of princes: but he shall be broken without hand. 26 And the vision of the evening and the morning which hath been told is true; but close thou up the vision, for it is for many days to come. 27 And I Daniel fainted, and was sick certain days: then I rose up, and did the king's business. And I was astonished at the vision, but none understood it.

Daniel 10

1 In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was revealed unto Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar; and the thing is true, but the appointed time of trial is long; and he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision. 2 In those days I Daniel was mourning three full weeks: 3 I ate no pleasant bread, neither came flesh nor wine into my mouth, neither did I anoint myself at all, till three full weeks were fulfilled. 4 And on the four-and-twentieth day of the first month, I was by the side of the great river, which is Hiddekel: 5 and I lifted up mine eyes and looked, and behold, a certain man clothed in linen, and his loins were girded with pure gold of Uphaz; 6 and his body was like a chrysolite, and his face as the appearance of lightning, and his eyes as torches of fire, and his arms and his feet as the look of burnished brass, and the voice of his words like the voice of a multitude. 7 And I Daniel alone saw the vision; and the men that were with me saw not the vision, but a great quaking fell on them, and they fled to hide themselves. 8 And I was left alone, and saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me; and my comeliness was turned in me into corruption, and I retained no strength. 9 And I heard the voice of his words; and when I heard the voice of his words, I fell into a deep stupor on my face, and my face to the ground.

10 And behold, a hand touched me, which set me upon my knees and the palms of my hands. 11 And he said unto me, O Daniel, man greatly beloved, understand the words which I speak unto thee, and stand upright; for unto thee am I now sent. And as he spoke this word unto me, I stood trembling. 12 And he said unto me, Fear not, Daniel; for from the first day that thou didst set thy heart to understand, and to humble thyself before thy God[*] thy words were heard, and I am come because of thy words. 13 But the prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me one and twenty days; and behold, Michael, one of the chief princes, came to help me; and I remained there with the kings of Persia. 14 And I am come to make thee understand what shall befall thy people at the end of the days: for the vision is yet for many days. 15 And as he was speaking with me according to these words, I set my face toward the ground, and I became dumb. 16 And behold, one after the likeness of the sons of men touched my lips; and I opened my mouth and spoke, and said unto him that stood before me, My lord, by reason of the vision my pains are turned upon me, and I retain no strength. 17 And how can the servant of this my lord talk with this my lord? for as for me, straightway there remaineth no strength in me, neither is there breath left in me. 18 Then there touched me again one like the appearance of a man, and he strengthened me; 19 and he said, Fear not, man greatly beloved; peace be unto thee, be strong, yea, be strong. And as he was speaking with me I was strengthened, and I said, Let my lord speak; for thou hast strengthened me. 20 And he said, Knowest thou wherefore I am come unto thee? And now I return to fight with the prince of Persia; and when I go forth, behold, the prince of Greece shall come. 21 However, I will declare unto thee that which is set down in the scripture of truth; and there is not one that sheweth himself strong with me against these, but Michael your prince.

Hebrew: Elohim

Daniel 12

1 And at that time shall Michael stand up, the great prince who standeth for the children of thy people; and there shall be a time of distress, such as never was since there was a nation until that time. And at that time thy people shall be delivered, every one that is found written in the book. 2 And many of them that sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to everlasting life, and some to shame, to everlasting contempt. 3 And they that are wise shall shine as the brightness of the expanse; and they that turn the many to righteousness as the stars, for ever and ever. 4 And thou, Daniel, close the words, and seal the book, till the time of the end. Many shall run to and fro, and knowledge shall be increased.

5 And I Daniel looked, and behold, there stood other two, the one on this side, on the bank of the river, and the other on that side, on the bank of the river. 6 And he said to the man clothed in linen, who was above the waters of the river, How long is it to the end of these wonders? 7 And I heard the man clothed in linen, who was above the waters of the river; and he held up his right hand and his left hand unto the heavens, and swore by him that liveth for ever that it is for a time, times, and a half; and when the scattering of the power of the holy people shall be accomplished, all these things shall be finished. 8 And I heard, but I understood not. And I said, My lord, what shall be the end of these things? 9 And he said, Go thy way, Daniel; for these words are closed and sealed till the time of the end. 10 Many shall be purified, and be made white, and be refined; but the wicked shall do wickedly: and none of the wicked shall understand; but the wise shall understand. 11 And from the time that the continual sacrifice is taken away, and the abomination that maketh desolate set up, there shall be a thousand, two hundred, and ninety days. 12 Blessed is he that waiteth, and cometh to the thousand three hundred and thirty-five days! 13 But do thou go thy way until the end; and thou shalt rest, and stand in thy lot at the end of the days.

Hosea 1

1 The word of Jehovah that came unto Hosea, the son of Beeri, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel.

2 The beginning of the word of Jehovah through Hosea. And Jehovah said to Hosea, Go, take unto thee a wife of whoredoms, and children of whoredoms; for the land is entirely given up to whoredom, away from Jehovah. 3 And he went and took Gomer the daughter of Diblaim; and she conceived and bore him a son. 4 And Jehovah said unto him, Call his name Jizreel; for yet a little, and I will visit the blood of Jizreel upon the house of Jehu, and will cause the kingdom of the house of Israel to cease. 5 And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will break the bow of Israel in the valley of Jizreel. 6 And she conceived again, and bore a daughter. And he said unto him, Call her name Lo-ruhamah; for I will no more have mercy upon the house of Israel, so that I should pardon them. 7 But I will have mercy upon the house of Judah, and will save them by Jehovah their God[*] and I will not save them by bow, or by sword, or by battle, or by horses, or by horsemen.

8 And she weaned Lo-ruhamah; and she conceived and bore a son; 9 and he said, Call his name Lo-ammi; for ye are not my people, and I will not be for you. 10 Yet the number of the children of Israel shall be as the sand of the sea which cannot be measured or numbered; and it shall come to pass, that in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people, it shall be said unto them, Sons of the living ·God[*] 11 And the children of Judah and the children of Israel shall be gathered together, and they shall appoint themselves one head, and shall go up out of the land: for great is the day of Jizreel.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: El

Hosea 2

1 Say unto your brethren Ammi; and to your sisters, Ruhamah. 2 Plead with your mother, plead; for she is not my wife, neither am I her husband: and let her put away her whoredoms from her face, and her adulteries from between her breasts; 3 lest I strip her naked, and set her as in the day that she was born, and make her as a wilderness, and set her as a dry land, and slay her with thirst. 4 And I will not have mercy upon her children; for they are the children of whoredoms. 5 For their mother hath played the harlot; she that conceived them hath done shamefully: for she said, I will go after my lovers, that give me my bread and my water, my wool and my flax, mine oil and my drink.

6 Therefore behold, I will hedge up thy way with thorns; and I will fence her in with a wall, that she shall not find her paths. 7 And she shall pursue after her lovers, and shall not overtake them; and she shall seek them, and shall not find them: and she shall say, I will go and return to my first husband, for then was it better with me than now. 8 And she did not know that I had given her the corn and the new wine and the oil, and had multiplied to her the silver and gold, which they employed for Baal. 9 Therefore will I return, and take away my corn in the time thereof, and my new wine in its season, and will withdraw my wool and my flax which should have covered her nakedness. 10 And now will I discover her impiety in the sight of her lovers, and none shall deliver her out of my hand. 11 And I will cause all her mirth to cease: her feasts, her new moons, and her sabbaths! and all her solemnities. 12 And I will make desolate her vine and her fig-tree, whereof she hath said, These are my rewards which my lovers have given me; and I will make them a forest, and the beasts of the field shall eat them. 13 And I will visit upon her the days of the Baals, wherein she burned incense to them, and decked herself with her rings and jewels, and went after her lovers, and forgot me, saith Jehovah.

14 Therefore behold, I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderness, and speak to her heart. 15 And I will give her her vineyards from thence, and the valley of Achor for a door of hope; and she shall sing there, as in the days of her youth and as in the day when she came up out of the land of Egypt. 16 And it shall be in that day, saith Jehovah, that thou shalt call me, My husband, and shalt call me no more, Baali; 17 for I will take away the names of the Baals out of her mouth, and they shall no more be remembered by their name. 18 And I will make a covenant for them in that day with the beasts of the field, and with the fowl of the heavens, and the creeping things of the ground; and I will break bow and sword and battle out of the land; and I will make them to lie down safely. 19 And I will betroth thee unto me for ever; and I will betroth thee unto me in righteousness, and in judgment, and in loving-kindness, and in mercies; 20 and I will betroth thee unto me in faithfulness: and thou shalt know Jehovah. 21 And it shall come to pass in that day, I will hear, saith Jehovah, I will hear the heavens, and they shall hear the earth; 22 and the earth shall hear the corn, and the new wine, and the oil; and they shall hear Jizreel. 23 And I will sow her unto me in the land; and I will have mercy upon Lo-ruhamah; and I will say to Lo-ammi, Thou art my people; and they shall say, My God[*] .

Hebrew: Elohim

Hosea 5

1 Hear this, ye priests; and hearken, ye house of Israel; and give ear, O house of the king: for this judgment is for you; for ye have been a snare at Mizpah, and a net spread upon Tabor. 2 And they have plunged themselves in the corruption of apostasy, but I will be a chastiser of them all. 3 I know Ephraim, and Israel is not hid from me; for now, Ephraim, thou hast committed whoredom; Israel is defiled. 4 Their doings do not allow them to return unto their God[*] for the spirit of whoredoms is in the midst of them, and they know not Jehovah. 5 And Israel's pride doth testify to his face; and Israel and Ephraim shall fall by their iniquity: Judah also shall fall with them. 6 They shall go with their flocks and with their herds to seek Jehovah; but they shall not find him: he hath withdrawn himself from them. 7 They have dealt treacherously against Jehovah; for they have begotten strange children: now shall the new moon devour them, with their allotted possessions.

8 Blow the horn in Gibeah, the trumpet in Ramah; cry aloud at Beth-aven: behind thee, O Benjamin! 9 Ephraim shall be a desolation in the day of rebuke: among the tribes of Israel have I made known that which is sure. 10 The princes of Judah are become like them that remove the landmark: I will pour out my wrath upon them like water. 11 Ephraim is oppressed, crushed in judgment, because in selfwill he walked after the commandment of man. 12 And I will be unto Ephraim as a moth, and to the house of Judah as rottenness. 13 When Ephraim saw his sickness, and Judah his sore, then went Ephraim to the Assyrian, and sent to king Jareb; but he was unable to heal you, nor hath he removed your sore. 14 For I will be unto Ephraim as a lion, and as a young lion to the house of Judah. I, I will tear and go away; I will carry off, and there shall be none to deliver. 15 I will go away, I will return to my place, till they acknowledge their trespass, and seek my face: in their affliction they will seek me early.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hosea 6

1 Come and let us return unto Jehovah: for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he hath smitten, and he will bind us up. 2 After two days will he revive us; on the third day he will raise us up, and we shall live before his face; 3 and we shall know, --we shall follow on to know Jehovah: his going forth is assured as the morning dawn; and he will come unto us as the rain, as the latter rain which watereth the earth.

4 What shall I do unto thee, Ephraim? What shall I do unto thee, Judah? For your goodness is as a morning cloud, and as the dew that early passeth away. 5 Therefore have I hewed them by the prophets; I have slain them by the words of my mouth: and my judgment goeth forth as the light. 6 For I delight in loving-kindness, and not sacrifice; and the knowledge of God[*] more than burnt-offerings. 7 But they like Adam have transgressed the covenant: there have they dealt treacherously against me. 8 Gilead is a city of them that work iniquity; it is tracked with blood. 9 And as troops of robbers lie in wait for a man, so the company of priests murder in the way of Shechem; yea, they commit lewdness. 10 In the house of Israel have I seen a horrible thing: the whoredom of Ephraim is there; Israel is defiled. 11 Also, for thee, Judah, is a harvest appointed, when I shall turn again the captivity of my people.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hosea 7

1 When I would heal Israel, then the iniquity of Ephraim is discovered, and the wickedness of Samaria: for they practise falsehood; and the thief entereth in, and the troop of robbers assaileth without. 2 And they say not in their hearts that I remember all their wickedness: now do their own doings encompass them; they are before my face. 3 They make the king glad with their wickedness, and the princes with their lies. 4 They all practise adultery, as an oven heated by the baker: he ceaseth from stirring the fire after he hath kneaded the dough, until it be leavened. 5 In the day of our king, the princes made themselves sick with the heat of wine: he stretched out his hand to scorners. 6 For they have applied their heart like an oven to their lying in wait: their baker sleepeth all the night; in the morning it burneth like a flaming fire. 7 They are all hot as an oven, and devour their judges; all their kings are fallen: there is none among them that calleth unto me.

8 Ephraim, he mixeth himself with the peoples; Ephraim is a cake not turned. 9 Strangers have devoured his strength, and he knoweth it not; yea, gray hairs are here and there upon him, and he knoweth it not. 10 And the pride of Israel testifieth to his face; and they do not return to Jehovah their God[*] nor seek him for all this. 11 And Ephraim is become like a silly dove without understanding: they call to Egypt, they go to Assyria. 12 When they go, I will spread my net upon them; I will bring them down as the fowl of the heavens; I will chastise them, according as their assembly hath heard. 13 Woe unto them! for they have wandered from me; destruction unto them! for they have transgressed against me. And I would redeem them; but they speak lies against me. 14 And they cried not unto me in their heart, when they howled upon their beds; they assemble themselves for corn and new wine; they have turned aside from me. 15 I have indeed trained, I have strengthened their arms, but they imagine mischief against me. 16 They return, but not to the Most High: they are like a deceitful bow. Their princes shall fall by the sword for the rage of their tongue: this shall be their derision in the land of Egypt.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hosea 10

1 Israel is an unpruned vine, he bringeth forth fruit unto himself: according to the abundance of his fruit he hath multiplied altars; according to the goodness of his land they have made goodly statues. 2 Their heart is divided; now shall they be found guilty: he will break down their altars, he will destroy their statues. 3 For now they will say, We have no king, for we feared not Jehovah; and a king, what can he do for us? 4 They speak mere words, swearing falsely in making a covenant; therefore shall judgment spring up as hemlock in the furrows of the fields. 5 The inhabitants of Samaria shall fear because of the calf of Beth-aven; for the people thereof shall mourn over it, and the idolatrous priests thereof shall tremble for it, for its glory, because it is departed from it. 6 Yea, it shall be carried unto Assyria as a present for king Jareb: Ephraim shall be seized with shame, and Israel shall be ashamed of his own counsel. 7 As for Samaria her king is cut off as chips upon the face of the waters. 8 And the high places of Aven, the sin of Israel, shall be destroyed: the thorn and the thistle shall come up upon their altars; and they shall say to the mountains, Cover us! and to the hills, Fall on us!

9 From the days of Gibeah hast thou sinned, O Israel: there they stood: the battle in Gibeah against the children of iniquity did not overtake them. 10 At my pleasure will I chastise them; and the peoples shall be assembled against them, when they are bound for their two iniquities. 11 And Ephraim is a trained heifer, that loveth to tread out the corn; I have passed over upon her fair neck: I will make Ephraim to draw; Judah shall plough, Jacob shall break his clods. 12 Sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap according to mercy; break up your fallow ground: for it is time to seek Jehovah, till he come and rain righteousness upon you. 13 Ye have ploughed wickedness, reaped iniquity, eaten the fruit of lies; for thou didst confide in thy way, in the multitude of thy mighty men. 14 And a tumult shall arise among thy peoples, and all thy fortresses shall be spoiled, as Shalman spoiled Beth-arbel in the day of battle: the mother was dashed in pieces with the children. 15 So shall Bethel do unto you because of the wickedness of your wickedness: at day-break shall the king of Israel utterly be cut off.

Hosea 11

1 When Israel was a child, then I loved him, and out of Egypt I called my son. 2 As they called them, so they went from them: they sacrificed unto the Baals, and burned incense to graven images. 3 And I it was that taught Ephraim to walk, --He took them upon his arms, --but they knew not that I healed them. 4 I drew them with bands of a man, with cords of love; and I was to them as they that take off the yoke on their jaws, and I gently caused them to eat. 5 He shall not return into the land of Egypt, but the Assyrian shall be his king; for they refused to return to me; 6 and the sword shall turn about in his cities, and shall consume his bars, and devour them, because of their own counsels. 7 Yea, my people are bent upon backsliding from me: though they call them to the Most High, none at all exalteth him.

8 How shall I give thee over, Ephraim? how shall I deliver thee up, Israel? how shall I make thee as Admah? how shall I set thee as Zeboim? My heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together. 9 I will not execute the fierceness of mine anger, I will not again destroy Ephraim; for I am ·God[*] and not man, --the Holy One in the midst of thee: and I will not come in anger. 10 They shall walk after Jehovah; he shall roar like a lion; when he shall roar, then the children shall hasten from the west: 11 they shall hasten as a bird out of Egypt, and as a dove out of the land of Assyria; and I will cause them to dwell in their houses, saith Jehovah. 12 Ephraim encompasseth me about with lies, and the house of Israel with deceit; but Judah yet walketh with ·God[*] and with the holy things of truth.

Hebrew: El

Hebrew: El

Joel 3

1 For behold, in those days, and in that time, when I shall turn again the captivity of Judah and Jerusalem, 2 I will also gather all the nations, and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoshaphat, and I will enter into judgment with them there on account of my people and mine inheritance, Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations: and they have parted my land; 3 and they have cast lots for my people, and have given a boy for a harlot, and sold a girl for wine, and have drunk it. 4 Yea also, what have ye to do with me, O Tyre and Zidon, and all the districts of Philistia? Will ye render me a recompence? But if ye recompense me, swiftly and speedily will I bring your recompence upon your own head; 5 because ye have taken my silver and my gold, and have carried into your temples my beautiful pleasant things, 6 and the children of Judah and the children of Jerusalem have ye sold unto the children of the Greeks, that ye might remove them far from their border. 7 Behold, I will raise them up out of the place whither ye have sold them, and will bring your recompence upon your own head. 8 And I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hand of the children of Judah, and they shall sell them to the Sabeans, to a nation far off: for Jehovah hath spoken.

9 Proclaim this among the nations: prepare war, arouse the mighty men, let all the men of war draw near, let them come up. 10 Beat your ploughshares into swords, and your pruning-knives into spears; let the weak say, I am strong. 11 Haste ye and come, all ye nations round about, and gather yourselves together. Thither cause thy mighty ones to come down, O Jehovah. 12 Let the nations rouse themselves, and come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat; for there will I sit to judge all the nations round about. 13 Put in the sickle, for the harvest is ripe: come, get you down, for the press is full, the vats overflow; for their wickedness is great. 14 Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of decision! For the day of Jehovah is at hand in the valley of decision. 15 The sun and the moon shall be darkened, and the stars shall withdraw their shining. 16 And Jehovah will roar from Zion, and utter his voice from Jerusalem; and the heavens and the earth shall shake: and Jehovah will be a shelter for his people, and the refuge of the children of Israel. 17 And ye shall know that I, Jehovah, am your God[*] dwelling in Zion, my holy mountain; and Jerusalem shall be holy, and no strangers shall pass through her any more.

18 And it shall come to pass in that day, that the mountains shall drop down new wine, and the hills shall flow with milk, and all the water-courses of Judah shall flow with waters; and a fountain shall come forth from the house of Jehovah, and shall water the valley of Shittim. 19 Egypt shall be a desolation, and Edom shall be a desolate wilderness, for the violence against the children of Judah, in that they have shed innocent blood in their land. 20 But Judah shall abide for ever, and Jerusalem from generation to generation. 21 And I will purge them from the blood from which I had not purged them: for Jehovah dwelleth in Zion.

Hebrew: Elohim

Amos 1

1 The words of Amos, who was among the herdmen of Tekoa, which he saw concerning Israel in the days of Uzziah king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel, two years before the earthquake. 2 And he said, Jehovah roareth from Zion, and uttereth his voice from Jerusalem; and the pastures of the shepherds mourn, and the top of Carmel withereth.

3 Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Damascus, and for four, I will not revoke my sentence, because they have threshed Gilead with threshing instruments of iron. 4 And I will send a fire into the house of Hazael, and it shall devour the palaces of Ben-Hadad. 5 And I will break the bar of Damascus, and cut off the inhabitant from the valley of Aven, and him that holdeth the sceptre from Beth-Eden; and the people of Syria shall go into captivity unto Kir, saith Jehovah. 6 Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Gazah, and for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they carried away captive the whole captivity, to deliver them up to Edom. 7 And I will send a fire on the wall of Gazah, and it shall devour the palaces thereof. 8 And I will cut off the inhabitant from Ashdod, and him that holdeth the sceptre from Ashkelon, and I will turn my hand against Ekron; and the remnant of the Philistines shall perish, saith the Lord Jehovah. 9 Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Tyre, and for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they delivered up the whole captivity to Edom, and remembered not the brotherly covenant. 10 And I will send a fire on the wall of Tyre, and it shall devour the palaces thereof. 11 Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Edom, and for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because he pursued his brother with the sword, and cast off all pity; and his anger did tear continually, and he kept his wrath for ever. 12 And I will send a fire upon Teman, and it shall devour the palaces of Bozrah. 13 Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of the children of Ammon, and for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they ripped up the women with child of Gilead, that they might enlarge their border. 14 And I will kindle a fire in the wall of Rabbah, and it shall devour the palaces thereof, with shouting in the day of battle, with a tempest in the day of the whirlwind. 15 And their king shall go into captivity, he and his princes together, saith Jehovah.

Amos 2

1 Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Moab, and for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because he burned the bones of the king of Edom into lime. 2 And I will send a fire upon Moab, and it shall devour the palaces of Kerijoth; and Moab shall die with tumult, with shouting, and with the sound of the trumpet. 3 And I will cut off the judge from the midst thereof, and will slay all the princes thereof with him, saith Jehovah. 4 Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Judah, and for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they have despised the law of Jehovah, and have not kept his statutes; and their lies have caused them to err, after which their fathers walked. 5 And I will send a fire upon Judah, and it shall devour the palaces of Jerusalem. 6 Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Israel, and for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they have sold the righteous for silver, and the needy for a pair of shoes; 7 panting after the dust of the earth on the head of the poor, and turning aside the way of the meek; and a man and his father will go in unto the same maid, to profane my holy name. 8 And they lay themselves down by every altar upon clothes taken in pledge, and they drink in the house of their God[*] the wine of the condemned.

9 But I destroyed the Amorite before them, whose height was as the height of the cedars, and he was strong as the oaks; but I destroyed his fruit from above, and his roots from beneath. 10 And I brought you up from the land of Egypt, and led you forty years in the wilderness, to possess the land of the Amorite. 11 And I raised up of your sons for prophets, and of your young men for Nazarites. Is it not even thus, ye children of Israel? saith Jehovah. 12 And ye gave the Nazarites wine to drink; and commanded the prophets, saying, Prophesy not. 13 Behold, I will press upon you, as a cart presseth that is full of sheaves. 14 And flight shall perish from the swift, and the strong shall not strengthen his force, neither shall the mighty deliver his soul. 15 Neither shall he stand that handleth the bow; and the swift of foot shall not escape, and he that rideth the horse shall not deliver his soul; 16 and he that is stout-hearted among the mighty shall flee away naked in that day, saith Jehovah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Amos 3

1 Hear this word that Jehovah hath spoken against you, children of Israel, against the whole family that I brought up from the land of Egypt, saying, 2 You only have I known of all the families of the earth; therefore will I visit upon you all your iniquities. 3 Shall two walk together except they be agreed? 4 Will a lion roar in the forest when he hath no prey? Will a young lion cry out of his den if he have taken nothing? 5 Can a bird fall in a snare upon the earth when no gin is laid for him? Will the snare spring up from the earth when nothing at all hath been taken? 6 Shall a trumpet be blown in the city, and the people not be afraid? Shall there be evil in a city, and Jehovah not have done it? 7 But the Lord Jehovah will do nothing, but he revealeth his secret unto his servants the prophets. 8 The lion hath roared, --who will not fear? The Lord Jehovah hath spoken, --who can but prophesy?

9 Publish in the palaces at Ashdod, and in the palaces in the land of Egypt, and say, Assemble yourselves upon the mountains of Samaria, and behold the great uproar in the midst thereof, and the oppressions that are within her: 10 and they know not to do right, saith Jehovah, who store up violence and plunder in their palaces. 11 Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: An adversary! --even round about the land! And he shall bring down thy strength from thee, and thy palaces shall be pillaged. 12 Thus saith Jehovah: Like as the shepherd rescueth out of the jaw of the lion two legs, or a piece of an ear; so shall the children of Israel be rescued that sit in Samaria in the corner of a couch, and upon the damask of a bed. 13 Hear ye, and testify in the house of Jacob, saith the Lord Jehovah, the God[*] of hosts, 14 that in the day that I shall visit the transgressions of Israel upon him, I will also punish the altars of Bethel; and the horns of the altar shall be cut off, and fall to the ground. 15 And I will smite the winter-house with the summer-house; and the houses of ivory shall perish, and many houses shall have an end, saith Jehovah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Amos 7

1 Thus did the Lord Jehovah shew unto me; and behold, he formed locusts in the beginning of the shooting up of the latter growth, and behold, it was the latter growth after the king's mowings. 2 And it came to pass, when they had wholly eaten the grass of the land, that I said, O Lord Jehovah, forgive, I beseech thee! How shall Jacob arise? for he is small. 3 Jehovah repented for this: It shall not be, said Jehovah. 4 Thus did the Lord Jehovah shew unto me; and behold, the Lord Jehovah called to contend by fire; and it devoured the great deep, and ate up the inheritance. 5 Then said I, O Lord Jehovah, cease, I beseech thee! How shall Jacob arise? for he is small. 6 Jehovah repented for this: This also shall not be, said the Lord Jehovah. 7 Thus did he shew unto me; and behold, the Lord stood upon a wall made by a plumb-line, with a plumb-line in his hand. 8 And Jehovah said unto me, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A plumb-line. And the Lord said, Behold, I will set a plumb-line in the midst of my people Israel: I will not again pass by them any more. 9 And the high places of Isaac shall be desolated, and the sanctuaries of Israel shall be laid waste; and I will arise against the house of Jeroboam with the sword.

10 Then Amaziah the priest of Bethel sent to Jeroboam king of Israel, saying, Amos hath conspired against thee in the midst of the house of Israel: the land is not able to bear all his words. 11 For thus Amos saith: Jeroboam shall die by the sword, and Israel shall certainly go into captivity out of his land. 12 And Amaziah said unto Amos, Thou seer, go, flee away into the land of Judah, and eat bread there, and prophesy there. 13 But prophesy not again any more at Bethel; for it is the king's sanctuary, and it is the house of the kingdom. 14 And Amos answered and said to Amaziah, I was no prophet, neither was I a prophet's son; but I was a herdman, and a gatherer of sycamore fruit. 15 And Jehovah took me as I followed the flock, and Jehovah said unto me, Go, prophesy unto my people Israel. 16 And now hear thou the word of Jehovah: Thou sayest, Prophesy not against Israel, and utter not words against the house of Isaac. 17 Therefore thus saith Jehovah: Thy wife shall be a harlot in the city, and thy sons and thy daughters shall fall by the sword, and thy land shall be divided with the line; and thou shalt die in a land that is unclean; and Israel shall certainly go into captivity, out of his land.

Amos 8

1 Thus did Jehovah shew unto me; and behold, a basket of summer-fruit. 2 And he said, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A basket of summer-fruit. And Jehovah said unto me, The end is come upon my people Israel: I will not again pass by them any more. 3 And the songs of the palace shall be howlings in that day, saith the Lord Jehovah. The dead bodies shall be many; in every place they shall be cast forth. Silence!

4 Hear this, ye that pant after the needy, even to cause to fail the poor of the land, 5 saying, When will the new moon be gone, that we may sell corn? and the sabbath, that we may set forth wheat? making the ephah small and the shekel great, and falsifying the balances for deceit: 6 that we may buy the poor for silver, and the needy for a pair of shoes; and that we may sell the refuse of the wheat. 7 Jehovah hath sworn by the glory of Jacob, Certainly I will never forget any of their works. 8 Shall not the land tremble for this, and every one mourn that dwelleth therein? And it shall wholly rise up like the Nile; and it shall surge and sink down, as the river of Egypt. 9 And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord Jehovah, that I will cause the sun to go down at noon, and I will darken the land in the clear day. 10 And I will turn your feasts into mourning, and all your songs into lamentation; and I will bring up sackcloth upon all loins, and baldness upon every head; and I will make it as the mourning for an only son, and the end thereof as a bitter day.

11 Behold, days come, saith the Lord Jehovah, when I will send a famine in the land; not a famine of bread, nor a thirst for water, but of hearing the words of Jehovah. 12 And they shall wander from sea to sea, and from the north to the east; they shall run to and fro to seek the word of Jehovah, and shall not find it. 13 In that day shall the fair virgins and the young men faint for thirst; 14 they that swear by the sin of Samaria, and say, As thy god, O Dan, liveth! and, As the way of Beer-sheba liveth! even they shall fall, and never rise up again.

Amos 9

1 I saw the Lord standing upon the altar; and he said, Smite the chapiter that the thresholds may shake; and break all of them in pieces, in the head; and I will slay the last of them with the sword: he that fleeth of them shall not get away by flight, and he that escapeth of them shall not be delivered. 2 Though they dig into Sheol, thence shall my hand take them; and though they climb up to the heavens, thence will I bring them down; 3 and though they hide themselves on the top of Carmel, I will search and take them out thence; and though they be hid from my sight in the bottom of the sea, there will I command the serpent, and it shall bite them; 4 and though they go into captivity before their enemies, there will I command the sword, and it shall slay them: and I will set mine eyes upon them for evil, and not for good. 5 And the Lord Jehovah of hosts is he that toucheth the land, and it melteth, and all that dwell therein shall mourn; and it shall wholly rise up like the Nile, and sink down as the river of Egypt. 6 It is he that buildeth his upper chambers in the heavens, and hath founded his vault upon the earth; he that calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth: Jehovah is his name. 7 Are ye not as children of the Ethiopians unto me, O children of Israel? saith Jehovah. Have not I brought up Israel out of the land of Egypt? and the Philistines from Caphtor, and the Syrians from Kir? 8 Behold, the eyes of the Lord Jehovah are upon the sinful kingdom, and I will destroy it from off the face of the earth: only that I will not utterly destroy the house of Jacob, saith Jehovah. 9 For behold, I command, and I will shake the house of Israel to and fro among all the nations, like as one shaketh corn in a sieve; yet shall not the least grain fall upon the earth. 10 All the sinners of my people shall die by the sword, who say, Evil shall not overtake nor befall us.

11 In that day will I raise up the tabernacle of David which is fallen, and close up the breaches thereof; and I will raise up its ruins, and I will build it as in the days of old: 12 that they may possess the remnant of Edom, and all the nations upon whom my name is called, saith Jehovah who doeth this. 13 Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, when the ploughman shall overtake the reaper, and the treader of grapes him that soweth seed; and the mountains shall drop new wine, and all the hills shall melt. 14 And I will turn again the captivity of my people Israel, and they shall build the waste cities, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and drink the wine thereof; and they shall make gardens, and eat the fruit of them. 15 And I will plant them upon their land, and they shall no more be plucked up out of their land which I have given them, saith Jehovah thy God[*] .

Hebrew: Elohim

Obadiah 1

1 The vision of Obadiah. Thus saith the Lord Jehovah concerning Edom: We have heard a report from Jehovah, and an ambassador is sent among the nations. Arise ye, and let us rise up against her in battle. 2 Behold, I have made thee small among the nations; thou art greatly despised. 3 The pride of thy heart hath deceived thee, thou that dwellest in the clefts of the rock, whose habitation is high; --he that saith in his heart, Who shall bring me down to the ground? 4 Though thou exalt thyself as the eagle, and though thou set thy nest among the stars, thence will I bring thee down, saith Jehovah. 5 If thieves had come to thee, if robbers by night, (how art thou cut off!) would they not have stolen till they had had enough? If grape-gatherers had come to thee, would they not have left some gleanings? 6 How is Esau searched! his hidden things sought out! 7 All the men of thy confederacy have pushed thee to the border; the men that were at peace with thee have deceived thee, they have prevailed against thee; they that eat thy bread have laid a snare under thee. There is no understanding in him. 8 Shall I not in that day, saith Jehovah, destroy the wise men out of Edom, and understanding out of the mount of Esau? 9 And thy mighty men, O Teman, shall be dismayed, to the end that every one may be cut off from the mount of Esau by slaughter.

10 Because of violence against thy brother Jacob, shame shall cover thee, and thou shalt be cut off for ever. 11 In the day that thou stoodest on the other side, in the day that strangers carried away captive his substance, and foreigners entered into his gates, and cast lots upon Jerusalem, even thou wast as one of them. 12 But thou shouldest not have looked on the day of thy brother in the day of his disaster; neither shouldest thou have rejoiced over the children of Judah in the day of their destruction; nor have opened wide thy mouth in the day of distress. 13 Thou shouldest not have entered into the gate of my people in the day of their calamity, nor have looked, even thou, on their affliction in the day of their calamity, neither shouldest thou have laid hands on their substance in the day of their calamity; 14 and thou shouldest not have stood on the crossway, to cut off those of his that did escape, nor have delivered up those remaining of him in the day of distress. 15 For the day of Jehovah is near upon all the nations: as thou hast done, it shall be done unto thee: thy recompence shall return upon thine own head. 16 For as ye have drunk upon my holy mountain, so shall all the nations drink continually; yea, they shall drink, and shall swallow down, and they shall be as though they had not been.

17 But upon mount Zion shall there be deliverance, and it shall be holy; and the house of Jacob shall possess their possessions. 18 And the house of Jacob shall be a fire, and the house of Joseph a flame, and the house of Esau for stubble; and they shall kindle in them and devour them; and there shall not be any remaining of the house of Esau: for Jehovah hath spoken it. 19 And they of the south shall possess the mount of Esau; and they of the lowland the Philistines; yea, they shall possess the field of Ephraim and the field of Samaria; and Benjamin shall possess Gilead; 20 and the captives of this host of the children of Israel shall possess what belonged to the Canaanites, unto Zarephath; and the captives of Jerusalem, who were in Sepharad, shall possess the cities of the south. 21 And saviours shall come up on mount Zion, to judge the mount of Esau; and the kingdom shall be Jehovah's.

Micah 1

1 The word of Jehovah that came to Micah the Morasthite in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, which he saw concerning Samaria and Jerusalem. 2 Hear, ye peoples, all of you; hearken, O earth, and all that is therein: and let the Lord Jehovah be witness against you, the Lord from his holy temple! 3 For behold, Jehovah cometh forth out of his place, and will come down, and tread upon the high places of the earth. 4 And the mountains shall be melted under him, and the valleys shall be cleft, as wax before the fire, as waters poured down a steep place. 5 For the transgression of Jacob is all this, and for the sins of the house of Israel. Whence is the transgression of Jacob? is it not from Samaria? And whence are the high places of Judah? are they not from Jerusalem? 6 Therefore will I make Samaria as a heap of the field, as plantings of a vineyard; and I will pour down the stones thereof into the valley, and I will lay bare the foundations thereof. 7 And all her graven images shall be beaten to pieces, and all her harlot-gifts shall be burned with fire, and all her idols will I make a desolation; for of the hire of a harlot hath she gathered them, and to a harlot's hire shall they return.

8 For this will I lament, and I will howl; I will go stripped and naked: I will make a wailing like the jackals, and mourning like the ostriches. 9 For her wounds are incurable; for it is come even unto Judah, it reacheth unto the gate of my people, even to Jerusalem. 10 Tell it not in Gath, weep not at all; at Beth-le-aphrah roll thyself in the dust. 11 Pass away, inhabitress of Shaphir, in nakedness and shame. The inhabitress of Zaanan is not come forth for the lamentation of Beth-ezel: he will take from you its shelter. 12 For the inhabitress of Maroth waited anxiously for good; but evil hath come down from Jehovah unto the gate of Jerusalem. 13 Bind the chariot to the swift steed, O inhabitress of Lachish: she was the beginning of sin to the daughter of Zion; for in thee were found the transgressions of Israel. 14 Therefore shalt thou give parting-gifts to Moresheth-Gath: the houses of Achzib shall be a lie to the kings of Israel. 15 I will yet bring unto thee an heir, O inhabitress of Mareshah; the glory of Israel shall come even unto Adullam. 16 Make thee bald, and poll thee for the children of thy delights; enlarge thy baldness as the eagle, for they are gone into captivity from thee.

Micah 3

1 And I said, Hear, I pray you, ye heads of Jacob, and princes of the house of Israel: Is it not for you to know judgment? 2 Ye who hate the good, and love evil; who pluck off their skin from them, and their flesh from off their bones; 3 and who eat the flesh of my people, and flay their skin from off them, and break their bones, and chop them in pieces as for the pot, and as flesh within the cauldron. 4 Then shall they cry unto Jehovah, but he will not answer them; and he will hide his face from them at that time, according as they have wrought evil in their doings. 5 Thus saith Jehovah concerning the prophets that cause my people to err, that bite with their teeth, and cry, Peace! but whoso putteth not into their mouths they prepare war against him: 6 therefore ye shall have night without a vision; and it shall be dark unto you, without divination; and the sun shall go down upon the prophets, and the day shall be black over them. 7 And the seers shall be ashamed, and the diviners confounded; and they shall all cover their lips, for there will be no answer of God[*]

8 But truly I am filled with power by the Spirit of Jehovah, and with judgment and with might, to declare unto Jacob his transgression, and to Israel his sin. 9 Hear this, I pray you, ye heads of the house of Jacob, and princes of the house of Israel, that abhor judgment, and pervert all equity, 10 that build up Zion with blood, and Jerusalem with unrighteousness. 11 The heads thereof judge for reward, and the priests thereof teach for hire, and the prophets thereof divine for money; yet do they lean upon Jehovah, and say, Is not Jehovah in the midst of us? no evil shall come upon us. 12 Therefore shall Zion for your sake be ploughed as a field, and Jerusalem shall become heaps, and the mountain of the house as the high places of a forest.

Hebrew: Elohim

Micah 6

1 Hear ye now what Jehovah saith: Arise, contend before the mountains, and let the hills hear thy voice. 2 Hear, ye mountains, Jehovah's controversy, and ye, unchanging foundations of the earth; for Jehovah hath a controversy with his people, and he will plead with Israel. 3 O my people, what have I done unto thee? and wherein have I wearied thee? testify against me. 4 For I brought thee up out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed thee out of the house of bondage; and I sent before thee Moses, Aaron, and Miriam. 5 My people, remember now what Balak king of Moab consulted, and what Balaam the son of Beor answered him, from Shittim unto Gilgal, that ye may know the righteousness of Jehovah.

6 Wherewith shall I come before Jehovah, bow myself before the high God[*] Shall I come before him with burnt-offerings, with calves of a year old? 7 Will Jehovah take pleasure in thousands of rams, in ten thousands of rivers of oil? Shall I give my firstborn for my transgression, the fruit of my body for the sin of my soul? 8 He hath shewn thee, O man, what is good: and what doth Jehovah require of thee, but to do justly, and to love goodness, and to walk humbly with thy God[*]

9 Jehovah's voice crieth unto the city, and wisdom looketh on thy name. Hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it. 10 Are there yet treasures of wickedness in the house of the wicked, and the scant measure which is abominable? 11 Shall I be pure with the unjust balances, and with the bag of deceitful weights? 12 For her rich men are full of violence, and her inhabitants speak lies, and their tongue is deceitful in their mouth. 13 Therefore also will I make thee sick in smiting thee; I will make thee desolate because of thy sins. 14 Thou shalt eat, and not be satisfied, and thine emptiness shall remain in the midst of thee; and thou shalt take away, and not save; and what thou savest will I give up to the sword. 15 Thou shalt sow, but thou shalt not reap; thou shalt tread the olives, but thou shalt not anoint thee with oil; and new wine, but shalt not drink wine. 16 For the statutes of Omri are kept, and all the works of the house of Ahab; and ye walk in their counsels: that I should make thee a desolation, and the inhabitants thereof a hissing; and ye shall bear the reproach of my people.

Hebrew: Elohim

Hebrew: Elohim

Nahum 1

1 The burden of Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite.

2 A jealous and avenging ·God[*] is Jehovah: an avenger is Jehovah, and full of fury: Jehovah taketh vengeance on his adversaries, and he reserveth wrath for his enemies. 3 Jehovah is slow to anger, and great in power, and doth not at all clear the guilty: Jehovah, --his way is in the whirlwind and in the storm, and the clouds are the dust of his feet. 4 He rebuketh the sea, and maketh it dry, and drieth up all the rivers: Bashan languisheth, and Carmel, and the flower of Lebanon languisheth. 5 The mountains quake before him, and the hills melt, and the earth is upheaved at his presence, and the world, and all that dwell therein. 6 Who shall stand before his indignation? and who shall abide in the fierceness of his anger? His fury is poured out like fire, and the rocks are broken asunder by him. 7 Jehovah is good, a stronghold in the day of trouble; and he knoweth them that trust in him. 8 But with an overrunning flood he will make a full end of the place thereof, and darkness shall pursue his enemies.

9 What do ye imagine against Jehovah? He will make a full end: trouble shall not rise up the second time. 10 Though they be tangled together as thorns, and be as drenched from their drink, they shall be devoured as dry stubble, completely. 11 Out of thee is gone forth one that imagineth evil against Jehovah, a wicked counsellor. 12 Thus saith Jehovah: Though they be complete in number, and many as they be, even so shall they be cut down, and he shall pass away; and though I have afflicted thee, I will afflict thee no more. 13 And now will I break his yoke from off thee, and will burst thy bonds asunder. 14 And Jehovah hath given commandment concerning thee, that no more of thy name be sown: out of the house of thy god will I cut off the graven image, and the molten image: I will prepare thy grave; for thou art vile. 15 Behold upon the mountains the feet of him that bringeth glad tidings, that publisheth peace! Celebrate thy feasts, Judah, perform thy vows: for the wicked one shall no more pass through thee; he is utterly cut off.

Hebrew: El

Nahum 2

1 He that dasheth in pieces is come up against thy face: keep the fortress, watch the way, make thy loins strong, fortify thy power mightily. 2 For Jehovah hath brought again the glory of Jacob, as the glory of Israel; for the wasters have wasted them, and marred their vine-branches. 3 The shield of his mighty men is made red, the valiant men are in scarlet: the chariots glitter with the sheen of steel, in the day of his preparation, and the spears are brandished. 4 The chariots rush madly in the streets, they justle one against another in the broad ways: the appearance of them is like torches, they run like lightnings. 5 He bethinketh him of his nobles: they stumble in their march; they make haste to the wall thereof, and the shelter is prepared. 6 The gates of the rivers are opened, and the palace melteth away. 7 And it is decreed: she shall be uncovered, she shall be led away, and her maids shall moan as with the voice of doves, drumming upon their breasts. 8 Nineveh hath been like a pool of water, since the day she existed, yet they flee away. ...Stand! Stand! But none looketh back. 9 Plunder the silver, plunder the gold; for there is no end of the splendid store of all precious vessels. 10 She is empty, and void, and waste; and the heart melteth, and the knees smite together, and writhing pain is in all loins, and all their faces grow pale.

11 Where is now the den of the lions, and the feeding-place of the young lions, where the lion, the lioness, and the lion's whelp walked, and none made them afraid? 12 The lion tore in pieces enough for his whelps, and strangled for his lionesses, and filled his holes with prey, and his dens with ravin. 13 Behold, I am against thee, saith Jehovah of hosts: and I will burn her chariots into smoke; and the sword shall devour thy young lions, and I will cut off thy prey from the earth; and the voice of thy messengers shall no more be heard.

Nahum 3

1 Woe to the bloody city! It is all full of lies and violence; the prey departeth not. 2 The crack of the whip, and the noise of the rattling of the wheels, and of the prancing horses, and of the bounding chariots! 3 The horseman springing up, and the glitter of the sword, and the flash of the spear, and a multitude of slain, and a mass of carcases, and no end of corpses: they stumble over their corpses. 4 --Because of the multitude of the fornications of the well-favoured harlot, mistress of sorceries, that selleth nations through her fornications, and families through her sorceries, 5 behold, I am against thee, saith Jehovah of hosts; and I will uncover thy skirts upon thy face, and I will shew the nations thy nakedness, and the kingdoms thy shame. 6 And I will cast abominable filth upon thee, and make thee vile, and will set thee as a gazing stock. 7 And it shall come to pass, that all they that see thee shall flee from thee, and shall say, Nineveh is laid waste! Who will bemoan her? whence shall I seek comforters for thee?

8 Art thou better than No-Amon, that was situate among the rivers, that had the waters round about her, whose rampart was the sea, and of the sea was her wall? 9 Ethiopia was her strength, and Egypt, and it was infinite; Phut and the Libyans were her helpers. 10 She too was carried away, she went into captivity: her infants also were dashed in pieces, at the top of all the streets; and they cast lots for her honourable men, and all her great men were bound with chains. 11 Thou also shalt be drunken: thou shalt be hid; thou also shalt seek a refuge from the enemy. 12 All thy strongholds are like fig-trees with the first-ripe figs: if they be shaken, they even fall into the mouth of the eater. 13 Behold, thy people in the midst of thee are as women: the gates of thy land are set wide open unto thine enemies; the fire devoureth thy bars. 14 Draw thee water for the siege, strengthen thy fortresses; go into the clay, and tread the mortar, make strong the brick-kiln. 15 There shall the fire devour thee; the sword shall cut thee off; it shall devour thee like the cankerworm. Make thyself many as the cankerworm, make thyself many as the locust. 16 Thou hast multiplied thy merchants more than the stars of the heavens; the cankerworm spreadeth himself out and flieth away. 17 Thy chosen men are as the locusts, and thy captains as swarms of grasshoppers, which camp in the hedges in the cold day: when the sun ariseth they flee away, and their place is not known where they are. 18 Thy shepherds slumber, O king of Assyria; thy nobles lie still; thy people are scattered upon the mountains, and no man gathereth them. 19 There is no healing of thy breach; thy wound is grievous; all that hear the report of thee clap the hands over thee; for upon whom hath not thy wickedness passed continually?

Habakkuk 1

1 The burden which Habakkuk the prophet did see. 2 Jehovah, how long shall I cry and thou wilt not hear? I cry out unto thee, Violence! and thou dost not save. 3 Why dost thou cause me to see iniquity, and lookest thou upon grievance? For spoiling and violence are before me; and there is strife, and contention riseth up. 4 Therefore the law is powerless, and justice doth never go forth; for the wicked encompasseth the righteous; therefore judgment goeth forth perverted.

5 See ye among the nations, and behold, and wonder marvellously; for I work a work in your days, which ye will not believe, though it be declared to you. 6 For behold, I raise up the Chaldeans, that bitter and impetuous nation, which marcheth through the breadth of the earth, to possess dwelling-places that are not theirs. 7 They are terrible and dreadful: their judgment and their dignity proceed from themselves. 8 And their horses are swifter than the leopards, and are more agile than the evening wolves; and their horsemen prance proudly, and their horsemen come from afar: they fly as an eagle that hasteth to devour. 9 They come all of them for violence: the crowd of their faces is forwards, and they gather captives as the sand. 10 Yea, he scoffeth at kings, and princes are a scorn unto him; he derideth every stronghold: for he heapeth up dust, and taketh it. 11 Then will his mind change, and he will pass on, and become guilty: this his power is become his god[*]

12 --Art thou not from everlasting, Jehovah my God[*] my Holy One? We shall not die. Jehovah, thou hast ordained him for judgment; and thou, O Rock, hast appointed him for correction. 13 Thou art of purer eyes than to behold evil, and canst not look on mischief: wherefore lookest thou upon them that deal treacherously, and keepest silence when the wicked swalloweth up a man more righteous than he? 14 And thou makest men as the fishes of the sea, as the creeping things, that have no ruler over them. 15 He taketh up all of them with the hook, he catcheth them in his net, and gathereth them into his drag; therefore he rejoiceth and is glad: 16 therefore he sacrificeth unto his net, and burneth incense unto his drag; for by them his portion is become fat, and his meat dainty. 17 Shall he therefore empty his net, and not spare to slay the nations continually?

Hebrew: eloah

Hebrew: Elohim

Habakkuk 3

1 A Prayer of Habakkuk the prophet upon Shigionoth. 2 Jehovah, I heard the report of thee, and I feared. Jehovah, revive thy work in the midst of the years, In the midst of the years make it known: In wrath remember mercy!

3 +God[*] came from Teman, And the Holy One from mount Paran. Selah. His glory covereth the heavens, And the earth is full of his praise. 4 And his brightness was as the light; Rays came forth from his hand; And there was the hiding of his power. 5 Before him went the pestilence, And a burning flame went forth at his feet. 6 He stood, and measured the earth; He beheld, and discomfited the nations; And the eternal mountains were scattered, The everlasting hills gave way: His ways are everlasting. 7 I saw the tents of Cushan in affliction; The curtains of the land of Midian did tremble. 8 Was Jehovah wrathful with the rivers? Was thine anger against the rivers? Was thy rage against the sea, That thou didst ride upon thy horses, Thy chariots of salvation? 9 Thy bow was made naked, The rods of discipline sworn according to thy word. Selah. Thou didst cleave the earth with rivers. 10 The mountains saw thee, they were in travail: Torrents of waters passed by; The deep uttered its voice, Lifted up its hands on high. 11 The sun and moon stood still in their habitation, At the light of thine arrows which shot forth, --At the shining of thy glittering spear. 12 Thou didst march through the land in indignation, Thou didst thresh the nations in anger. 13 Thou wentest forth for the salvation of thy people, For the salvation of thine anointed; Thou didst smite off the head from the house of the wicked, Laying bare the foundation even to the neck. Selah. 14 Thou didst strike through with his own spears the head of his leaders: They came out as a whirlwind to scatter me, Whose exulting was as to devour the afflicted secretly. 15 Thou didst walk through the sea with thy horses, The heap of great waters.

16 I heard, and my belly trembled; My lips quivered at the voice; Rottenness entered into my bones, and I trembled in my place, That I might rest in the day of distress, When their invader shall come up against the people. 17 For though the fig-tree shall not blossom, Neither shall fruit be in the vines; The labour of the olive-tree shall fail, And the fields shall yield no food; The flock shall be cut off from the fold, And there shall be no herd in the stalls: 18 Yet I will rejoice in Jehovah, I will joy in the God[*] of my salvation. 19 Jehovah, the Lord, is my strength, And he maketh my feet like hinds' feet, And he will make me to walk upon my high places. To the chief Musician. On my stringed instruments.

Hebrew: Eloah

Hebrew: Elohim

Zephaniah 1

1 The word of Jehovah that came unto Zephaniah the son of Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of Hezekiah, in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah. 2 I will utterly take away everything from off the face of the ground, saith Jehovah: 3 I will take away man and beast; I will take away the fowl of the heavens and the fishes of the sea, and the stumbling-blocks with the wicked, and I will cut off mankind from off the face of the ground, saith Jehovah. 4 And I will stretch forth my hand upon Judah, and upon all the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and I will cut off the remnant of Baal from this place, the name of the Chemarim with the priests; 5 and them that bow down to the host of the heavens upon the housetops; and them that bow down to Jehovah, that swear by him, and swear by Malcham; 6 and them that turn back from after Jehovah, and that do not seek Jehovah, nor inquire for him.

7 Be silent at the presence of the Lord Jehovah; for the day of Jehovah is at hand; for Jehovah hath prepared a sacrifice, he hath hallowed his guests. 8 And it shall come to pass in the day of Jehovah's sacrifice, that I will punish the princes, and the king's sons, and all such as are clothed with foreign apparel. 9 And in that day will I punish all those that leap over the threshold, who fill their master's house with violence and deceit. 10 And in that day, saith Jehovah, there shall be the noise of a cry from the fish-gate, and a howling from the second quarter, and a great crashing from the hills. 11 Howl, ye inhabitants of Maktesh; for all the people of Canaan are cut down, all they that are laden with silver are cut off. 12 And it shall come to pass at that time, that I will search Jerusalem with lamps, and punish the men that are settled on their lees, that say in their heart, Jehovah will not do good, neither will he do evil. 13 And their wealth shall become a booty, and their houses a desolation; and they shall build houses, and not inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and not drink the wine thereof.

14 The great day of Jehovah is near, it is near, and hasteth greatly. The voice of the day of Jehovah: the mighty man shall cry there bitterly. 15 That day is a day of wrath, a day of trouble and distress, a day of ruin and desolation, a day of darkness and gloom, a day of clouds and gross darkness, 16 a day of the trumpet and alarm, against the fenced cities and against the high battlements. 17 And I will bring distress upon men, and they shall walk like blind men; for they have sinned against Jehovah; and their blood shall be poured out as dust, and their flesh as dung: 18 their silver and their gold shall not be able to deliver them, in the day of Jehovah's wrath; but the whole land shall be devoured by the fire of his jealousy: for a full end, yea, a sudden end, shall he make of all them that dwell in the land.

Haggai 2

1 In the seventh month, on the one and twentieth day of the month, came the word of Jehovah by the prophet Haggai, saying, 2 Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying, 3 Who is left among you that saw this house in its former glory? and how do ye see it now? Is it not as nothing in your eyes? 4 But now be strong, Zerubbabel, saith Jehovah; and be strong, Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest; and be strong, all ye people of the land, saith Jehovah, and work: for I am with you, saith Jehovah of hosts. 5 The word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of Egypt, and my Spirit, remain among you: fear ye not. 6 For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the sea, and the dry land; 7 and I will shake all nations, and the desire of all nations shall come; and I will fill this house with glory, saith Jehovah of hosts. 8 The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, saith Jehovah of hosts. 9 The latter glory of this house shall be greater than the former, saith Jehovah of hosts; and in this place will I give peace, saith Jehovah of hosts.

10 On the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying, 11 Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying, 12 If one bear holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or any food--shall it become holy? And the priests answered and said, No. 13 And Haggai said, If one that is unclean by a dead body touch any of these, is it become unclean? And the priests answered and said, It shall be unclean. 14 Then answered Haggai and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before me, saith Jehovah, and so is every work of their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean. 15 And now, I pray you, consider from this day and onward, from before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of Jehovah, 16 --before those days were, when one came to a heap of twenty measures, there were but ten; when one came to the vat to draw out fifty press-measures, there were but twenty. 17 I smote you with blasting and with mildew and with hail in all the work of your hands; and ye turned not to me, saith Jehovah. 18 Consider, I pray you, from this day and onward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, from the day that the foundation of Jehovah's temple was laid, consider it. 19 Is the seed yet in the barn? yea, the vine, and the fig-tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive-tree have not brought forth: from this day will I bless you.

20 And the word of Jehovah came the second time unto Haggai on the four and twentieth day of the month, saying, 21 Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, I will shake the heavens and the earth; 22 and I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms, and I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations; and I will overthrow the chariots, and those that ride therein; and the horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword of his brother. 23 In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, will I take thee, Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, my servant, saith Jehovah, and will make thee as a signet; for I have chosen thee, saith Jehovah of hosts.

Zechariah 1

1 In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah unto Zechariah the prophet, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, saying, 2 Jehovah hath been very wroth with your fathers. 3 And thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Return unto me, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I will return unto you, saith Jehovah of hosts. 4 Be ye not as your fathers, unto whom the former prophets cried, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Turn ye now from your evil ways, and from your evil doings; but they did not hearken nor attend unto me, saith Jehovah. 5 Your fathers, where are they? and the prophets, do they live for ever? 6 But my words and my statutes, which I commanded my servants the prophets, did they not overtake your fathers? And they turned and said, Like as Jehovah of hosts thought to do unto us, according to our ways and according to our doings, so hath he dealt with us.

7 Upon the four and twentieth day of the eleventh month, which is the month Shebat, in the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah unto Zechariah the prophet, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, saying, 8 I saw by night, and behold, a man riding upon a red horse, and he stood among the myrtle-trees that were in the low valley; and behind him were red, bay, and white horses. 9 And I said, My lord, what are these? And the angel that talked with me said unto me, I will shew thee what these are. 10 And the man that stood among the myrtle-trees answered and said, These are they whom Jehovah hath sent to walk to and fro through the earth. 11 And they answered the angel of Jehovah that stood among the myrtle-trees, and said, We have walked to and fro through the earth, and behold, all the earth sitteth still and is at rest. 12 And the angel of Jehovah answered and said, Jehovah of hosts, how long wilt thou not have mercy on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, against which thou hast had indignation these seventy years? 13 And Jehovah answered the angel that talked with me good words, comforting words. 14 And the angel that talked with me said unto me, Cry, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: I am jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great jealousy, 15 and I am wroth exceedingly with the nations that are at ease; for I was but a little wroth, and they helped forward the affliction. 16 Therefore thus saith Jehovah: I am returned to Jerusalem with mercies: my house shall be built in it, saith Jehovah of hosts, and the line shall be stretched forth upon Jerusalem. 17 Cry further, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: My cities shall yet overflow with prosperity, and Jehovah shall yet comfort Zion, and shall yet choose Jerusalem.

18 And I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and behold four horns. 19 And I said unto the angel that talked with me, What are these? And he said to me, These are the horns which have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem. 20 And Jehovah shewed me four craftsmen. 21 And I said, What come these to do? And he spoke, saying, Those are the horns which scattered Judah, so that no man lifted up his head; but these are come to affright them, to cast out the horns of the nations, which lifted up the horn against the land of Judah to scatter it.

Zechariah 2

1 And I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and behold a man with a measuring line in his hand. 2 And I said, Whither goest thou? And he said unto me, To measure Jerusalem, to see what is the breadth thereof, and what is the length thereof. 3 And behold, the angel that talked with me went forth; and another angel went forth to meet him, 4 and said unto him, Run, speak to this young man, saying, Jerusalem shall be inhabited as towns without walls for the multitude of men and cattle therein; 5 and I, saith Jehovah, I will be unto her a wall of fire round about, and will be the glory in the midst of her.

6 Ho, ho! flee from the land of the north, saith Jehovah; for I have scattered you abroad as the four winds of the heavens, saith Jehovah. 7 Ho! escape, Zion, that dwellest with the daughter of Babylon. 8 For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: After the glory, hath he sent me unto the nations that made you a spoil; for he that toucheth you toucheth the apple of his eye. 9 For behold, I will shake my hand upon them, and they shall become a spoil to those that served them: and ye shall know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me.

10 Sing aloud and rejoice, daughter of Zion; for behold, I come, and I will dwell in the midst of thee, saith Jehovah. 11 And many nations shall join themselves to Jehovah in that day, and shall be unto me for a people; and I will dwell in the midst of thee, and thou shalt know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me unto thee. 12 And Jehovah shall inherit Judah as his portion in the holy land, and shall yet choose Jerusalem. 13 Let all flesh be silent before Jehovah; for he is risen up out of his holy habitation.

Zechariah 6

1 And I lifted up mine eyes again, and saw, and behold, there came four chariots out from between two mountains; and the mountains were mountains of brass. 2 In the first chariot were red horses; and in the second chariot black horses; 3 and in the third chariot white horses; and in the fourth chariot grisled, strong horses. 4 And I spoke and said unto the angel that talked with me, What are these, my lord? 5 And the angel answered and said unto me, These are the four spirits of the heavens, which go forth from standing before the Lord of all the earth. 6 That in which are the black horses goeth forth into the north country; and the white go forth after them; and the grisled go forth towards the south country; 7 and the strong go forth, and seek to go that they may walk to and fro through the earth. And he said, Go, walk to and fro through the earth. And they walked to and fro through the earth. 8 And he cried unto me, and spoke unto me, saying, See, these that go forth towards the north country have quieted my spirit in the north country.

9 And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, 10 Take gifts of them of the captivity, of Heldai, of Tobijah, and of Jedaiah, and come thou the same day, and enter into the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah, whither they are come from Babylon; 11 yea, take silver and gold, and make crowns, and set them upon the head of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest; 12 and speak unto him, saying, Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, saying, Behold a man whose name is the Branch; and he shall grow up from his own place, and he shall build the temple of Jehovah: 13 even he shall build the temple of Jehovah; and he shall bear the glory, and shall sit and rule upon his throne; and he shall be a priest upon his throne; and the counsel of peace shall be between them both. 14 And the crowns shall be for Helem, and for Tobijah, and for Jedaiah, and for Hen the son of Zephaniah, for a memorial in the temple of Jehovah. 15 And they that are far off shall come and build at the temple of Jehovah: and ye shall know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me unto you. And this shall come to pass, if ye will diligently hearken to the voice of Jehovah your God[*] .

Hebrew: Elohim

Zechariah 10

1 Ask of Jehovah rain in the time of the latter rain; Jehovah will make lightnings, and he will give them showers of rain, to every one grass in the field. 2 For the teraphim have spoken vanity, and the diviners have seen a lie, and have told false dreams: they comfort in vain. Therefore they have gone away as a flock, they are in distress, because there is no shepherd. 3 Mine anger is kindled against the shepherds, and I will punish the he-goats; for Jehovah of hosts visiteth his flock, the house of Judah, and maketh them as his majestic horse in the battle. 4 From him shall come forth the corner-stone, from him the nail, from him the battle bow, from him every exactor together.

5 And they shall be as mighty men, treading down the mire of the streets in the battle; and they shall fight, for Jehovah is with them, and the riders on horses shall be put to shame. 6 And I will strengthen the house of Judah, and I will save the house of Joseph, and I will bring them back again; for I will have mercy upon them; and they shall be as though I had not cast them off: for I am Jehovah their God[*] and I will answer them. 7 And they of Ephraim shall be like a mighty man, and their hearts shall rejoice as through wine; and their children shall see it, and rejoice; their heart shall be joyful in Jehovah. 8 I will hiss for them, and gather them; for I have redeemed them: and they shall multiply as they used to multiply. 9 And I will sow them among the peoples, and they shall remember me in far countries; and they shall live with their children and return. 10 And I will bring them again out of the land of Egypt, and gather them out of Assyria; and I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon; and place shall not be found for them. 11 And he shall pass through the sea of affliction, and shall smite the billows in the sea, and all the depths of the Nile shall dry up; and the pride of Assyria shall be brought down, and the sceptre of Egypt shall depart away. 12 And I will strengthen them in Jehovah; and they shall walk in his name, saith Jehovah.

Hebrew: Elohim

Zechariah 11

1 Open thy doors, O Lebanon, that the fire may devour thy cedars. 2 Howl, cypress, for the cedar is fallen; because the noble ones are spoiled. Howl, ye oaks of Bashan; for the strong forest is come down. 3 A voice of howling of the shepherds; for their glory is spoiled: a voice of roaring of young lions; for the pride of Jordan is spoiled.

4 Thus saith Jehovah my God[*] Feed the flock of slaughter, 5 whose possessors slay them without being held guilty; and they that sell them say, Blessed be Jehovah! for I am become rich; and their own shepherds pity them not. 6 For I will no more pity the inhabitants of the land, saith Jehovah, and behold, I will deliver men, every one into his neighbour's hand, and into the hand of his king; and they shall smite the land, and I will not deliver out of their hand. 7 So I fed the flock of slaughter, truly the poor of the flock. And I took unto me two staves; the one I called Beauty, and the other I called Bands; and I fed the flock. 8 And I destroyed three shepherds in one month; and my soul was vexed with them, and their soul also loathed me. 9 And I said, I will not feed you: that which dieth, let it die; and that which perisheth let it perish; and let them which are left eat every one the flesh of another. 10 And I took my staff, Beauty, and cut it asunder, that I might break my covenant which I had made with all the peoples. 11 And it was broken in that day; and so the poor of the flock that gave heed to me knew that it was the word of Jehovah. 12 And I said unto them, If ye think good, give me my hire; and if not, forbear. And they weighed for my hire thirty silver-pieces. 13 And Jehovah said unto me, Cast it unto the potter: a goodly price that I was prized at by them. And I took the thirty silver-pieces, and cast them to the potter in the house of Jehovah. 14 And I cut asunder mine other staff, Bands, to break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.

15 And Jehovah said unto me, Take unto thee yet the instruments of a foolish shepherd. 16 For behold, I will raise up a shepherd in the land, who shall not visit those that are about to perish, neither shall seek that which is strayed away, nor heal that which is wounded, nor feed that which is sound; but he will eat the flesh of the fat, and tear their hoofs in pieces. 17 Woe to the worthless shepherd that leaveth the flock! The sword shall be upon his arm, and upon his right eye; his arm shall be clean dried up, and his right eye utterly darkened.

Hebrew: Elohim

Zechariah 14

1 Behold, the day cometh for Jehovah, and thy spoil shall be divided in the midst of thee. 2 And I will assemble all the nations against Jerusalem to battle; and the city shall be taken, and the houses rifled, and the women ravished; and half of the city shall go forth into captivity; and the rest of the people shall not be cut off from the city. 3 And Jehovah will go forth and fight with those nations, as when he fought in the day of battle. 4 And his feet shall stand in that day upon the mount of Olives, which is before Jerusalem toward the east, and the mount of Olives shall cleave in the midst thereof toward the east and toward the west, --a very great valley; and half of the mountain shall remove toward the north, and half of it toward the south. 5 And ye shall flee by the valley of my mountains; for the valley of the mountains shall reach unto Azal: ye shall even flee, like as ye fled from before the earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah. And Jehovah my God[*] shall come, and all the holy ones with thee. 6 And it shall come to pass in that day, that there shall not be light; the shining shall be obscured. 7 And it shall be one day which is known to Jehovah, not day, and not night; and it shall come to pass, at eventide it shall be light.

8 And it shall come to pass in that day that living waters shall go out from Jerusalem; half of them toward the eastern sea, and half of them toward the hinder sea: in summer and in winter shall it be. 9 And Jehovah shall be king over all the earth: in that day shall there be one Jehovah, and his name one. 10 All the land from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem shall be turned as the Arabah; and Jerusalem shall be lifted up, and shall dwell in her own place, from Benjamin's gate unto the place of the first gate, unto the corner-gate, and from the tower of Hananeel unto the king's winepresses. 11 And men shall dwell in it, and there shall be no more utter destruction; and Jerusalem shall dwell safely. 12 And this shall be the plague wherewith Jehovah will smite all the peoples that have warred against Jerusalem: their flesh shall consume away while they stand upon their feet, and their eyes shall consume away in their holes, and their tongue shall consume away in their mouth. 13 And it shall come to pass in that day that a great panic from Jehovah shall be among them; and they shall lay hold every one on the hand of his neighbour, and his hand shall rise up against the hand of his neighbour. 14 And Judah also shall fight at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the nations round about shall be gathered together--gold, and silver, and garments, in great abundance. 15 And so shall be the plague of the horse, of the mule, of the camel, and of the ass, and of all the beasts that shall be in those camps, as this plague.

16 And it shall come to pass, that all that are left of all the nations which came against Jerusalem shall go up from year to year to worship the King, Jehovah of hosts, and to celebrate the feast of tabernacles. 17 And it shall be, that whoso goeth not up of the families of the earth unto Jerusalem to worship the King, Jehovah of hosts, upon them shall be no rain. 18 And if the family of Egypt go not up, and come not, neither shall it be upon them; there shall be the plague, wherewith Jehovah will smite the nations that go not up to celebrate the feast of tabernacles. 19 This shall be the punishment of Egypt, and the punishment of all the nations that go not up to celebrate the feast of tabernacles. 20 In that day shall there be upon the bells of the horses, HOLINESS UNTO JEHOVAH; and the pots in Jehovah's house shall be like the bowls before the altar. 21 And every pot in Jerusalem and in Judah shall be holiness unto Jehovah of hosts; and all they that sacrifice shall come and take of them, and seethe therein. And in that day there shall be no more a Canaanite in the house of Jehovah of hosts.

Hebrew: Elohim

Malachi 1

1 The burden of the word of Jehovah to Israel by Malachi. 2 I have loved you, saith Jehovah; but ye say, Wherein hast thou loved us? Was not Esau Jacob's brother? saith Jehovah, and I loved Jacob, 3 and I hated Esau; and made his mountains a desolation, and gave his inheritance to the jackals of the wilderness. 4 If Edom say, We are broken down, but we will build again the ruined places, --thus saith Jehovah of hosts: They shall build, but I will throw down; and men shall call them the territory of wickedness, and the people against whom Jehovah hath indignation for ever. 5 And your eyes shall see it, and ye shall say, Jehovah is magnified beyond the border of Israel.

6 A son honoureth his father, and a servant his master: if then I be a father, where is mine honour? and if I be a master, where is my fear? saith Jehovah of hosts unto you, priests, that despise my name. But ye say, Wherein have we despised thy name? 7 Ye offer polluted bread upon mine altar; and ye say, Wherein have we polluted thee? In that ye say, The table of Jehovah is contemptible. 8 And if ye offer the blind for sacrifice, is it not evil? And if ye offer the lame and sick, is it not evil? Present it now unto thy governor: will he be pleased with thee? or will he accept thy person? saith Jehovah of hosts. 9 And now, I pray you, beseech ·God[*] that he will be gracious unto us. This hath been of your hand: will he accept any of your persons? saith Jehovah of hosts. 10 Who is there among you that would even shut the doors? and ye would not kindle fire on mine altar for nothing. I have no delight in you, saith Jehovah of hosts, neither will I accept an oblation at your hand. 11 For from the rising of the sun even unto its setting my name shall be great among the nations; and in every place incense shall be offered unto my name, and a pure oblation: for my name shall be great among the nations, saith Jehovah of hosts. 12 But ye profane it, in that ye say, The table of the Lord is polluted; and the fruit thereof, his food, is contemptible. 13 And ye say, Behold, what a weariness! And ye have puffed at it, saith Jehovah of hosts, and ye bring that which was torn, and the lame, and the sick; thus ye bring the oblation: should I accept this of your hand? saith Jehovah. 14 Yea, cursed be the deceiver, who hath in his flock a male, and voweth and sacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing; for I am a great King, saith Jehovah of hosts, and my name is terrible among the nations.

Hebrew: El

Matthew 1

1 Book of the generation of Jesus Christ, Son of David, Son of Abraham. 2 Abraham begat Isaac; and Isaac begat Jacob, and Jacob begat Juda and his brethren; 3 and Juda begat Phares and Zara of Thamar; and Phares begat Esrom, and Esrom begat Aram, 4 and Aram begat Aminadab, and Aminadab begat Naasson, and Naasson begat Salmon, 5 and Salmon begat Booz of Rachab; and Booz begat Obed of Ruth; and Obed begat Jesse, 6 and Jesse begat David the king. And David begat Solomon, of her that had been the wife of Urias; 7 and Solomon begat Roboam, and Roboam begat Abia, and Abia begat Asa, 8 and Asa begat Josaphat, and Josaphat begat Joram, and Joram begat Ozias, 9 and Ozias begat Joatham, and Joatham begat Achaz, and Achaz begat Ezekias, 10 and Ezekias begat Manasses, and Manasses begat Amon, and Amon begat Josias, 11 and Josias begat Jechonias and his brethren, at the time of the carrying away of Babylon. 12 And after the carrying away of Babylon, Jechonias begat Salathiel, and Salathiel begat Zorobabel, 13 and Zorobabel begat Abiud, and Abiud begat Eliakim, and Eliakim begat Azor, 14 and Azor begat Sadoc, and Sadoc begat Achim, and Achim begat Eliud, 15 and Eliud begat Eliazar, and Eliazar begat Matthan, and Matthan begat Jacob, 16 and Jacob begat Joseph, the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus, who is called Christ. 17 All the generations, therefore, from Abraham to David were fourteen generations; and from David until the carrying away of Babylon, fourteen generations; and from the carrying away of Babylon unto the Christ, fourteen generations.

18 Now the birth of Jesus Christ was thus: His mother, Mary, that is, having been betrothed to Joseph, before they came together, she was found to be with child of the Holy Spirit. 19 But Joseph, her husband, being a righteous man, and unwilling to expose her publicly, purposed to have put her away secretly; 20 but while he pondered on these things, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream, saying, Joseph, son of David, fear not to take to thee Mary, thy wife, for that which is begotten in her is of theHoly Spirit. 21 And she shall bring forth a son, and thou shalt call his name Jesus, for he shall save his people from their sins. 22 Now all this came to pass that that might be fulfilled which was spoken by the Lord, through the prophet, saying, 23 Behold, the virgin shall be with child, and shall bring forth a son, and they shall call his name Emmanuel, which is, being interpreted, 'God with us.' 24 But Joseph, having awoke up from his sleep, did as the angel of the Lord had enjoined him, and took to him his wife, 25 and knew her not until she had brought forth her firstborn son: and he called his name Jesus.

Matthew 2

1 Now Jesus having been born in Bethlehem of Judaea, in the days of Herod the king, behold magi from the east arrived at Jerusalem, saying, 2 Where is the king of the Jews that has been born? for we have seen his star in the east, and have come to do him homage. 3 But Herod the king having heard of it, was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him; 4 and, assembling all the chief priests and scribes of the people, he inquired of them where the Christ should be born. 5 And they said to him, In Bethlehem of Judaea; for thus it is written through the prophet: 6 And thou Bethlehem, land of Juda, art in no wise the least among the governors of Juda; for out of thee shall go forth a leader who shall shepherd my people Israel. 7 Then Herod, having secretly called the magi, inquired of them accurately the time of the star that was appearing; 8 and having sent them to Bethlehem, said, Go, search out accurately concerning the child, and when ye shall have found him bring me back word, so that I also may come and do him homage.

9 And they having heard the king went their way; and lo, the star, which they had seen in the east, went before them until it came and stood over the place where the little child was. 10 And when they saw the star they rejoiced with exceeding great joy. 11 And having come into the house they saw the little child with Mary his mother, and falling down did him homage. And having opened their treasures, they offered to him gifts, gold, and frankincense, and myrrh. 12 And being divinely instructed in a dream not to return to Herod, they departed into their own country another way.

13 Now, they having departed, behold, an angel of the Lord appears in a dream to Joseph, saying, Arise, take to thee the little child and his mother, and flee into Egypt, and be there until I shall tell thee; for Herod will seek the little child to destroy it. 14 And, having arisen, he took to him the little child and his mother by night, and departed into Egypt. 15 And he was there until the death of Herod, that that might be fulfilled which was spoken by the Lord through the prophet, saying, Out of Egypt have I called my son.

16 Then Herod, seeing that he had been mocked by the magi, was greatly enraged; and sent and slew all the boys which were in Bethlehem, and in all its borders, from two years and under, according to the time which he had accurately inquired from the magi. 17 Then was fulfilled that which was spoken through Jeremias the prophet, saying, 18 A voice has been heard in Rama, weeping, and great lamentation: Rachel weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, because they are not.

19 But Herod having died, behold, an angel of the Lord appears in a dream to Joseph in Egypt, saying, 20 Arise, take to thee the little child and its mother, and go into the land of Israel: for they who sought the life of the little child are dead. 21 And he arose and took to him the little child and its mother, and came into the land of Israel; 22 but having heard that 'Archelaus reigns over Judaea, instead of Herod his father,' he was afraid to go there; and having been divinely instructed in a dream, he went away into the parts of Galilee, 23 and came and dwelt in a town called Nazareth; so that that should be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophets, He shall be called a Nazaraene.

Matthew 3

1 Now in those days comes John the baptist, preaching in the wilderness of Judaea, 2 and saying, Repent, for the kingdom of the heavens has drawn nigh. 3 For this is he who has been spoken of through Esaias the prophet, saying, Voice of him that crieth in the wilderness: prepare ye the way of the Lord, make straight his paths. 4 And John himself had his garment of camel's hair, and a leathern girdle about his loins, and his nourishment was locusts and wild honey. 5 Then went out to him Jerusalem, and all Judaea, and all the country round the Jordan, 6 and were baptised by him in the Jordan, confessing their sins.

7 But seeing many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to his baptism, he said to them, Offspring of vipers, who has forewarned you to flee from the coming wrath? 8 Produce therefore fruit worthy of repentance. 9 And do not think to say within yourselves, We have Abraham for our father; for I say unto you, that God is able of these stones to raise up children to Abraham. 10 And already the axe is applied to the root of the trees; every tree therefore not producing good fruit is cut down and cast into the fire. 11 I indeed baptise you with water to repentance, but he that comes after me is mightier than I, whose sandals I am not fit to bear; he shall baptise you with the Holy Spirit and fire; 12 whose winnowing fan is in his hand, and he shall thoroughly purge his threshing-floor, and shall gather his wheat into the garner, but the chaff he will burn with fire unquenchable.

13 Then comes Jesus from Galilee to the Jordan to John, to be baptised of him; 14 but John urgently forbad him, saying, I have need to be baptised of thee; and comest thou to me? 15 But Jesus answering said to him, Suffer it now; for thus it becometh us to fulfil all righteousness. Then he suffers him. 16 And Jesus, having been baptised, went up straightway from the water, and lo, the heavens were opened to him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending as a dove, and coming upon him: 17 and behold, a voice out of the heavens saying, This is my beloved Son, in whom I have found my delight.

Matthew 4

1 Then Jesus was carried up into the wilderness by the Spirit to be tempted of the devil: 2 and having fasted forty days and forty nights, afterwards he hungered. 3 And the tempter coming up to him said, If thou be Son of God, speak, that these stones may become loaves of bread. 4 But he answering said, It is written, Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word which goes out through God's mouth. 5 Then the devil takes him to the holy city, and sets him upon the edge of the temple, 6 and says to him, If thou be Son of God cast thyself down; for it is written, He shall give charge to his angels concerning thee, and on their hands shall they bear thee, lest in anywise thou strike thy foot against a stone. 7 Jesus said to him, It is again written, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God. 8 Again the devil takes him to a very high mountain, and shews him all the kingdoms of the world, and their glory, 9 and says to him, All these things will I give thee if, falling down, thou wilt do me homage. 10 Then says Jesus to him, Get thee away, Satan, for it is written, Thou shalt do homage to the Lord thy God, and him alone shalt thou serve. 11 Then the devil leaves him, and behold, angels came and ministered to him.

12 But having heard that John was delivered up, he departed into Galilee: 13 and having left Nazareth, he went and dwelt at Capernaum, which is on the sea-side in the borders of Zabulon and Nepthalim, 14 that that might be fulfilled which was spoken through Esaias the prophet, saying, 15 Land of Zabulon and land of Nepthalim, way of the sea beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the nations: 16 --the people sitting in darkness has seen a great light, and to those sitting in the country and shadow of death, to them has light sprung up. 17 From that time began Jesus to preach and to say, Repent, for the kingdom of the heavens has drawn nigh.

18 And walking by the sea of Galilee, he saw two brothers, Simon called Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the sea, for they were fishers; 19 and he says to them, Come after me, and I will make you fishers of men. 20 And they, having left their trawl-nets, immediately followed him. 21 And going on thence he saw other two brothers, James the son of Zebedee and John his brother, in the ship with Zebedee their father, mending their trawl-nets, and he called them; 22 and they, having left the ship and their father, immediately followed him.

23 And Jesus went round the whole of Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the glad tidings of the kingdom, and healing every disease and every bodily weakness among the people. 24 And his fame went out into the whole of Syria, and they brought to him all that were ill, suffering under various diseases and pains, and those possessed by demons, and lunatics, and paralytics; and he healed them. 25 And great crowds followed him from Galilee, and Decapolis, and Jerusalem, and Judaea, and beyond the Jordan.

Matthew 5

1 But seeing the crowds, he went up into the mountain, and having sat down, his disciples came to him; 2 and, having opened his mouth, he taught them, saying,

3 Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of the heavens. 4 Blessed they that mourn, for they shall be comforted. 5 Blessed the meek, for they shall inherit the earth. 6 Blessed they who hunger and thirst after righteousness, for they shall be filled. 7 Blessed the merciful, for they shall find mercy. 8 Blessed the pure in heart, for they shall see God. 9 Blessed the peace-makers, for they shall be called sons of God. 10 Blessed they who are persecuted on account of righteousness, for theirs is the kingdom of the heavens. 11 Blessed are ye when they may reproach and persecute you, and say every wicked thing against you, lying, for my sake. 12 Rejoice and exult, for your reward is great in the heavens; for thus have they persecuted the prophets who were before you.

13 Ye are the salt of the earth; but if the salt have become insipid, wherewith shall it be salted? It is no longer fit for anything but to be cast out and to be trodden under foot by men. 14 Ye are the light of the world: a city situated on the top of a mountain cannot be hid. 15 Nor do men light a lamp and put it under the bushel, but upon the lamp-stand, and it shines for all who are in the house. 16 Let your light thus shine before men, so that they may see your upright works, and glorify your Father who is in the heavens.

17 Think not that I am come to make void the law or the prophets; I am not come to make void, but to fulfil. 18 For verily I say unto you, Until the heaven and the earth pass away, one iota or one tittle shall in no wise pass from the law till all come to pass. 19 Whosoever then shall do away with one of these least commandments, and shall teach men so, shall be called least in the kingdom of the heavens; but whosoever shall practise and teach them, he shall be called great in the kingdom of the heavens. 20 For I say unto you, that unless your righteousness surpass that of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no wise enter into the kingdom of the heavens.

21 Ye have heard that it was said to the ancients, Thou shalt not kill; but whosoever shall kill shall be subject to the judgment. 22 But I say unto you, that every one that is lightly angry with his brother shall be subject to the judgment; but whosoever shall say to his brother, Raca, shall be subject to be called before the sanhedrim; but whosoever shall say, Fool, shall be subject to the penalty of the hell of fire. 23 If therefore thou shouldest offer thy gift at the altar, and there shouldest remember that thy brother has something against thee, 24 leave there thy gift before the altar, and first go, be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift. 25 Make friends with thine adverse party quickly, whilst thou art in the way with him; lest some time the adverse party deliver thee to the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the officer, and thou be cast into prison. 26 Verily I say to thee, Thou shalt in no wise come out thence till thou hast paid the last farthing.

27 Ye have heard that it has been said, Thou shalt not commit adultery. 28 But I say unto you, that every one who looks upon a woman to lust after her has already committed adultery with her in his heart. 29 But if thy right eye be a snare to thee, pluck it out and cast it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members perish, and not thy whole body be cast into hell. 30 And if thy right hand be a snare to thee, cut it off and cast it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members perish, and not thy whole body be cast into hell. 31 It has been said too, Whosoever shall put away his wife, let him give her a letter of divorce. 32 But I say unto you, that whosoever shall put away his wife, except for cause of fornication, makes her commit adultery, and whosoever marries one that is put away commits adultery.

33 Again, ye have heard that it has been said to the ancients, Thou shalt not forswear thyself, but shalt render to the Lord what thou hast sworn. 34 But I say unto you, Do not swear at all; neither by the heaven, because it is the throne of God; 35 nor by the earth, because it is the footstool of his feet; nor by Jerusalem, because it is the city of the great King. 36 Neither shalt thou swear by thy head, because thou canst not make one hair white or black. 37 But let your word be Yea, yea; Nay, nay; but what is more than these is from evil.

38 Ye have heard that it has been said, Eye for eye and tooth for tooth. 39 But I say unto you, not to resist evil; but whoever shall strike thee on thy right cheek, turn to him also the other; 40 and to him that would go to law with thee and take thy body coat, leave him thy cloak also. 41 And whoever will compel thee to go one mile, go with him two. 42 To him that asks of thee give, and from him that desires to borrow of thee turn not away.

43 Ye have heard that it has been said, Thou shalt love thy neighbour and hate thine enemy. 44 But I say unto you, Love your enemies, bless those who curse you, do good to those who hate you, and pray for those who insult you and persecute you, 45 that ye may be the sons of your Father who is in the heavens; for he makes his sun rise on evil and good, and sends rain on just and unjust. 46 For if ye should love those who love you, what reward have ye? Do not also the tax-gatherers the same? 47 And if ye should salute your brethren only, what do ye extraordinary? Do not also the Gentiles the same? 48 Be ye therefore perfect as your heavenly Father is perfect.

Matthew 6

1 Take heed not to do your alms before men to be seen of them, otherwise ye have no reward with your Father who is in the heavens. 2 When therefore thou doest alms, sound not a trumpet before thee, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, so that they may have glory from men. Verily I say unto you, They have their reward. 3 But thou, when thou doest alms, let not thy left hand know what thy right hand does; 4 so that thine alms may be in secret, and thy Father who sees in secret will render it to thee.

5 And when thou prayest, thou shalt not be as the hypocrites; for they love to pray standing in the synagogues and in the corners of the streets so that they should appear to men. Verily I say unto you, They have their reward. 6 But thou, when thou prayest, enter into thy chamber, and having shut thy door, pray to thy Father who is in secret, and thy Father who sees in secret will render it to thee. 7 But when ye pray, use not vain repetitions, as those who are of the nations: for they think they shall be heard through their much speaking. 8 Be not ye therefore like them, for your Father knows of what things ye have need before ye beg anything of him.

9 Thus therefore pray ye: Our Father who art in the heavens, let thy name be sanctified, 10 let thy kingdom come, let thy will be done as in heaven so upon the earth; 11 give us to-day our needed bread, 12 and forgive us our debts, as we also forgive our debtors, 13 and lead us not into temptation, but save us from evil. 14 For if ye forgive men their offences, your heavenly Father also will forgive you yours, 15 but if ye do not forgive men their offences, neither will your Father forgive your offences.

16 And when ye fast, be not as the hypocrites, downcast in countenance; for they disfigure their faces, so that they may appear fasting to men: verily I say unto you, They have their reward. 17 But thou, when fasting, anoint thy head and wash thy face, 18 so that thou mayest not appear fasting unto men, but to thy Father who is in secret; and thy Father who sees in secret shall render it to thee.

19 Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon the earth, where moth and rust spoils, and where thieves dig through and steal; 20 but lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust spoils, and where thieves do not dig through nor steal; 21 for where thy treasure is, there will be also thy heart. 22 The lamp of the body is the eye; if therefore thine eye be single, thy whole body will be light: 23 but if thine eye be wicked, thy whole body will be dark. If therefore the light that is in thee be darkness, how great the darkness! 24 No one can serve two masters; for either he will hate the one and will love the other, or he will hold to the one and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon.

25 For this cause I say unto you, Do not be careful about your life, what ye should eat and what ye should drink; nor for your body what ye should put on. Is not the life more than food, and the body than raiment? 26 Look at the birds of the heaven, that they sow not, nor reap, nor gather into granaries, and your heavenly Father nourishes them. Are ye not much more excellent than they? 27 But which of you by carefulness can add to his growth one cubit? 28 And why are ye careful about clothing? Observe with attention the lilies of the field, how they grow: they toil not, neither do they spin; 29 but I say unto you, that not even Solomon in all his glory was clothed as one of these. 30 But if God so clothe the herbage of the field, which is to-day, and to-morrow is cast into the oven, will he not much rather you, O ye of little faith? 31 Be not therefore careful, saying, What shall we eat? or What shall we drink? or What shall we put on? 32 for all these things the nations seek after; for your heavenly Father knows that ye have need of all these things. 33 But seek ye first the kingdom of God and his righteousness, and all these things shall be added unto you. 34 Be not careful therefore for the morrow, for the morrow shall be careful about itself. Sufficient to the day is its own evil.

Matthew 7

1 Judge not, that ye may not be judged; 2 for with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged; and with what measure ye mete, it shall be measured to you. 3 But why lookest thou on the mote that is in the eye of thy brother, but observest not the beam that is in thine eye? 4 Or how wilt thou say to thy brother, Allow me, I will cast out the mote from thine eye; and behold, the beam is in thine eye? 5 Hypocrite, cast out first the beam out of thine eye, and then thou wilt see clearly to cast out the mote out of the eye of thy brother. 6 Give not that which is holy to the dogs, nor cast your pearls before the swine, lest they trample them with their feet, and turning round rend you.

7 Ask, and it shall be given to you. Seek, and ye shall find. Knock, and it shall be opened to you. 8 For every one that asks receives; and he that seeks finds; and to him that knocks it shall be opened. 9 Or what man is there of you who, if his son shall ask of him a loaf of bread, will give him a stone; 10 and if he ask a fish, will give him a serpent? 11 If therefore ye, being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much rather shall your Father who is in the heavens give good things to them that ask of him?

12 Therefore all things whatever ye desire that men should do to you, thus do ye also do to them; for this is the law and the prophets. 13 Enter in through the narrow gate, for wide the gate and broad the way that leads to destruction, and many are they who enter in through it. 14 For narrow the gate and straitened the way that leads to life, and they are few who find it.

15 But beware of false prophets, which come to you in sheep's clothing, but within are ravening wolves. 16 By their fruits ye shall know them. Do men gather a bunch of grapes from thorns, or from thistles figs? 17 So every good tree produces good fruits, but the worthless tree produces bad fruits. 18 A good tree cannot produce bad fruits, nor a worthless tree produce good fruits. 19 Every tree not producing good fruit is cut down and cast into the fire. 20 By their fruits then surely ye shall know them.

21 Not every one who says to me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of the heavens, but he that does the will of my Father who is in the heavens. 22 Many shall say to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied through thy name, and through thy name cast out demons, and through thy name done many works of power? 23 and then will I avow unto them, I never knew you. Depart from me, workers of lawlessness. 24 Whoever therefore hears these my words and does them, I will liken him to a prudent man, who built his house upon the rock; 25 and the rain came down, and the streams came, and the winds blew and fell upon that house, and it did not fall, for it had been founded upon the rock. 26 And every one who hears these my words and does not do them, he shall be likened to a foolish man, who built his house upon the sand; 27 and the rain came down, and the streams came, and the winds blew and beat upon that house, and it fell, and its fall was great. 28 And it came to pass, when Jesus had finished these words, the crowds were astonished at his doctrine, 29 for he taught them as having authority, and not as their scribes.

Matthew 8

1 And when he had come down from the mountain, great crowds followed him. 2 And behold, a leper came up to him and did him homage, saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou art able to cleanse me. 3 And he stretched out his hand and touched him, saying, I will; be cleansed. And immediately his leprosy was cleansed. 4 And Jesus says to him, See thou tell no man, but go, shew thyself to the priest, and offer the gift which Moses ordained, for a testimony to them.

5 And when he had entered into Capernaum, a centurion came to him, beseeching him, 6 and saying, Lord, my servant lies paralytic in the house, suffering grievously. 7 And Jesus says to him, I will come and heal him. 8 And the centurion answered and said, Lord, I am not fit that thou shouldest enter under my roof; but only speak a word, and my servant shall be healed. 9 For I also am a man under authority, having under me soldiers, and I say to this one, Go, and he goes; and to another, Come, and he comes; and to my bondman, Do this, and he does it. 10 And when Jesus heard it, he wondered, and said to those who followed, Verily I say unto you, Not even in Israel have I found so great faith. 11 But I say unto you, that many shall come from the rising and setting sun, and shall lie down at table with Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob in the kingdom of the heavens; 12 but the sons of the kingdom shall be cast out into the outer darkness: there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth. 13 And Jesus said to the centurion, Go, and as thou hast believed, be it to thee. And his servant was healed in that hour.

14 And when Jesus had come to Peter's house, he saw his mother-in-law laid down and in a fever; 15 and he touched her hand, and the fever left her, and she arose and served him. 16 And when the evening was come, they brought to him many possessed by demons, and he cast out the spirits with a word, and healed all that were ill; 17 so that that should be fulfilled which was spoken through Esaias the prophet, saying, Himself took our infirmities and bore our diseases.

18 And Jesus, seeing great crowds around him, commanded to depart to the other side. 19 And a scribe came up and said to him, Teacher, I will follow thee whithersoever thou mayest go. 20 And Jesus says to him, The foxes have holes, and the birds of the heaven roosting-places; but the Son of man has not where he may lay his head. 21 But another of his disciples said to him, Lord, suffer me first to go away and bury my father. 22 But Jesus said to him, Follow me, and leave the dead to bury their own dead.

23 And he went on board ship and his disciples followed him; 24 and behold, the water became very agitated on the sea, so that the ship was covered by the waves; but he slept. 25 And the disciples came and awoke him, saying, Lord save: we perish. 26 And he says to them, Why are ye fearful, O ye of little faith? Then, having arisen, he rebuked the winds and the sea, and there was a great calm. 27 But the men were astonished, saying, What sort of man is this, that even the winds and the sea obey him?

28 And there met him, when he came to the other side, to the country of the Gergesenes, two possessed by demons, coming out of the tombs, exceeding dangerous, so that no one was able to pass by that way. 29 And behold, they cried out, saying, What have we to do with thee, Son of God? hast thou come here before the time to torment us? 30 Now there was, a great way off from them, a herd of many swine feeding; 31 and the demons besought him, saying, If thou cast us out, send us away into the herd of swine. 32 And he said to them, Go. And they, going out, departed into the herd of swine; and lo, the whole herd of swine rushed down the steep slope into the sea, and died in the waters. 33 But they that fed them fled, and went away into the city and related everything, and what had happened as to those possessed by demons. 34 And behold, the whole city went out to meet Jesus; and when they saw him, they begged him to go away out of their coasts.

Matthew 9

1 And going on board the ship, he passed over and came to his own city. 2 And behold, they brought to him a paralytic, laid upon a bed; and Jesus, seeing their faith, said to the paralytic, Be of good courage, child; thy sins are forgiven. 3 And behold, certain of the scribes said to themselves, This man blasphemes. 4 And Jesus, seeing their thoughts, said, Why do ye think evil things in your hearts? 5 For which is easier: to say, Thy sins are forgiven; or to say, Rise up and walk? 6 But that ye may know that the Son of man has power on earth to forgive sins, (then he says to the paralytic,) Rise up, take up thy bed and go to thy house. 7 And he rose up and went to his house. 8 But the crowds seeing it, were in fear, and glorified God who gave such power to men.

9 And Jesus, passing on thence, saw a man sitting at the tax-office, called Matthew, and says to him, Follow me. And he rose up and followed him. 10 And it came to pass, as he lay at table in the house, that behold, many tax-gatherers and sinners came and lay at table with Jesus and his disciples. 11 And the Pharisees seeing it, said to his disciples, Why does your teacher eat with tax-gatherers and sinners? 12 But Jesus hearing it, said, They that are strong have not need of a physician, but those that are ill. 13 But go and learn what that is--I will have mercy and not sacrifice; for I have not come to call righteous men but sinners.

14 Then come to him the disciples of John, saying, Why do we and the Pharisees often fast, but thy disciples fast not? 15 And Jesus said to them, Can the sons of the bridechamber mourn so long as the bridegroom is with them? But days will come when the bridegroom will have been taken away from them, and then they will fast. 16 But no one puts a patch of new cloth on an old garment, for its filling up takes from the garment and a worse rent takes place. 17 Nor do men put new wine into old skins, otherwise the skins burst and the wine is poured out, and the skins will be destroyed; but they put new wine into new skins, and both are preserved together.

18 As he spoke these things to them, behold, a ruler coming in did homage to him, saying, My daughter has by this died; but come and lay thy hand upon her and she shall live. 19 And Jesus rose up and followed him, and so did his disciples. 20 And behold, a woman, who had had a bloody flux for twelve years, came behind and touched the hem of his garment; 21 for she said within herself, If I should only touch his garment I shall be healed. 22 But Jesus turning and seeing her, said, Be of good courage, daughter; thy faith has healed thee. And the woman was healed from that hour. 23 And when Jesus was come to the house of the ruler, and saw the flute-players and the crowd making a tumult, 24 he said, Withdraw, for the damsel is not dead, but sleeps. And they derided him. 25 But when the crowd had been put out, he went in and took her hand; and the damsel rose up. 26 And the fame of it went out into all that land.

27 And as Jesus passed on thence, two blind men followed him, crying and saying, Have mercy on us, Son of David. 28 And when he was come to the house, the blind men came to him. And Jesus says to them, Do ye believe that I am able to do this? They say to him, Yea, Lord. 29 Then he touched their eyes, saying, According to your faith, be it unto you. 30 And their eyes were opened; and Jesus charged them sharply, saying, See, let no man know it. 31 But they, when they were gone out, spread his name abroad in all that land. 32 But as these were going out, behold, they brought to him a dumb man possessed by a demon. 33 And the demon having been cast out, the dumb spake. And the crowds were astonished, saying, It has never been seen thus in Israel. 34 But the Pharisees said, He casts out the demons through the prince of the demons.

35 And Jesus went round all the cities and the villages, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the glad tidings of the kingdom, and healing every disease and every bodily weakness. 36 But when he saw the crowds he was moved with compassion for them, because they were harassed, and cast away as sheep not having a shepherd. 37 Then saith he to his disciples, The harvest is great and the workmen are few; 38 supplicate therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he send forth workmen unto his harvest.

Matthew 10

1 And having called to him his twelve disciples, he gave them power over unclean spirits, so that they should cast them out, and heal every disease and every bodily weakness. 2 Now the names of the twelve apostles are these: first, Simon, who was called Peter, and Andrew his brother; James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother; 3 Philip and Bartholomew; Thomas, and Matthew the tax-gatherer; James the son of Alphaeus, and Lebbaeus, who was surnamed Thaddaeus; 4 Simon the Cananaean, and Judas the Iscariote, who also delivered him up.

5 These twelve Jesus sent out when he had charged them, saying, Go not off into the way of the nations, and into a city of Samaritans enter ye not; 6 but go rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. 7 And as ye go, preach, saying, The kingdom of the heavens has drawn nigh. 8 Heal the infirm, raise the dead, cleanse lepers, cast out demons: ye have received gratuitously, give gratuitously. 9 Do not provide yourselves with gold, or silver, or brass, for your belts, 10 nor scrip for the way, nor two body coats, nor sandals, nor a staff: for the workman is worthy of his nourishment. 11 But into whatsoever city or village ye enter, inquire who in it is worthy, and there remain till ye go forth. 12 And as ye enter into a house salute it. 13 And if the house indeed be worthy, let your peace come upon it; but if it be not worthy, let your peace return to you. 14 And whosoever shall not receive you, nor hear your words, as ye go forth out of that house or city, shake off the dust of your feet. 15 Verily I say unto you, It shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrha in judgment-day than for that city.

16 Behold, I send you as sheep in the midst of wolves; be therefore prudent as the serpents, and guileless as the doves. 17 But beware of men; for they will deliver you up to sanhedrims, and scourge you in their synagogues; 18 and ye shall be brought before rulers and kings for my sake, for a testimony to them and to the nations. 19 But when they deliver you up, be not careful how or what ye shall speak; for it shall be given to you in that hour what ye shall speak. 20 For ye are not the speakers, but the Spirit of your Father which speaks in you. 21 But brother shall deliver up brother to death, and father child; and children shall rise up against parents and shall put them to death; 22 and ye shall be hated of all on account of my name. But he that has endured to the end, he shall be saved. 23 But when they persecute you in this city, flee to the other; for verily I say to you, Ye shall not have completed the cities of Israel until the Son of man be come. 24 The disciple is not above his teacher, nor the bondman above his lord. 25 It is sufficient for the disciple that he should become as his teacher, and the bondman as his lord. If they have called the master of the house Beelzebub, how much more those of his household? 26 Fear them not therefore; for there is nothing covered which shall not be revealed, and secret which shall not be known. 27 What I say to you in darkness speak in the light, and what ye hear in the ear preach upon the houses. 28 And be not afraid of those who kill the body, but cannot kill the soul; but fear rather him who is able to destroy both soul and body in hell. 29 Are not two sparrows sold for a farthing? and one of them shall not fall to the ground without your Father; 30 but of you even the hairs of the head are all numbered. 31 Fear not therefore; ye are better than many sparrows. 32 Every one therefore who shall confess me before men, I also will confess him before my Father who is in the heavens. 33 But whosoever shall deny me before men, him will I also deny before my Father who is in the heavens. 34 Do not think that I have come to send peace upon the earth: I have not come to send peace, but a sword. 35 For I have come to set a man at variance with his father, and the daughter with her mother, and the daughter-in-law with her mother-in-law; 36 and they of his household shall be a man's enemies. 37 He who loves father or mother above me is not worthy of me; and he who loves son or daughter above me is not worthy of me. 38 And he who does not take up his cross and follow after me is not worthy of me. 39 He that finds his life shall lose it, and he who has lost his life for my sake shall find it. 40 He that receives you receives me, and he that receives me receives him that sent me. 41 He that receives a prophet in the name of a prophet, shall receive a prophet's reward; and he that receives a righteous man in the name of a righteous man, shall receive a righteous man's reward. 42 And whosoever shall give to drink to one of these little ones a cup of cold water only, in the name of a disciple, verily I say unto you, he shall in no wise lose his reward.

Matthew 11

1 And it came to pass when Jesus had finished commanding his twelve disciples, he departed thence to teach and preach in their cities. 2 But John, having heard in the prison the works of the Christ, sent by his disciples, 3 and said to him, Art thou the coming one? or are we to wait for another? 4 And Jesus answering said to them, Go, report to John what ye hear and see. 5 Blind men see and lame walk; lepers are cleansed, and deaf hear; and dead are raised, and poor have glad tidings preached to them: 6 and blessed is whosoever shall not be offended in me.

7 But as they went away, Jesus began to say to the crowds concerning John, What went ye out into the wilderness to see? a reed moved about by the wind? 8 But what went ye out to see? a man clothed in delicate raiment? behold, those who wear delicate things are in the houses of kings. 9 But what went ye out to see? a prophet? Yea, I say to you, and more than a prophet: 10 this is he of whom it is written, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face, who shall prepare thy way before thee. 11 Verily I say to you, that there is not arisen among the born of women a greater than John the baptist. But he who is a little one in the kingdom of the heavens is greater than he. 12 But from the days of John the baptist until now, the kingdom of the heavens is taken by violence, and the violent seize on it. 13 For all the prophets and the law have prophesied unto John. 14 And if ye will receive it, this is Elias, who is to come. 15 He that has ears to hear, let him hear.

16 But to whom shall I liken this generation? It is like children sitting in the markets, which, calling to their companions, 17 say, We have piped to you, and ye have not danced: we have mourned to you, and ye have not wailed. 18 For John has come neither eating nor drinking, and they say, He has a demon. 19 The Son of man has come eating and drinking, and they say, Behold, a man that is eating and wine-drinking, a friend of tax-gatherers, and of sinners: --and wisdom has been justified by her children. 20 Then began he to reproach the cities in which most of his works of power had taken place, because they had not repented. 21 Woe to thee, Chorazin! woe to thee Bethsaida! for if the works of power which have taken place in you, had taken place in Tyre and Sidon, they had long ago repented in sackcloth and ashes. 22 But I say to you, that it shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon in judgment-day than for you. 23 And thou, Capernaum, who hast been raised up to heaven, shalt be brought down even to hades. For if the works of power which have taken place in thee, had taken place in Sodom, it had remained until this day. 24 But I say to you, that it shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom in judgment-day than for thee.

25 At that time, Jesus answering said, I praise thee, Father, Lord of the heaven and of the earth, that thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them to babes. 26 Yea, Father, for thus has it been well-pleasing in thy sight. 27 All things have been delivered to me by my Father, and no one knows the Son but the Father, nor does any one know the Father, but the Son, and he to whom the Son may be pleased to reveal him. 28 Come to me, all ye who labour and are burdened, and I will give you rest. 29 Take my yoke upon you, and learn from me; for I am meek and lowly in heart; and ye shall find rest to your souls; 30 for my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.

Matthew 12

1 At that time Jesus went on the sabbath through the cornfields; and his disciples were hungry, and began to pluck the ears and to eat. 2 But the Pharisees, seeing it, said to him, Behold, thy disciples are doing what is not lawful to do on sabbath. 3 But he said to them, Have ye not read what David did when he was hungry, and they that were with him? 4 How he entered into the house of God, and ate the shewbread, which it was not lawful for him to eat, nor for those with him, but for the priests only? 5 Or have ye not read in the law that on the sabbaths the priests in the temple profane the sabbath, and are blameless? 6 But I say unto you, that there is here what is greater than the temple. 7 But if ye had known what is: I will have mercy and not sacrifice, ye would not have condemned the guiltless. 8 For the Son of man is Lord of the sabbath. 9 And, going away from thence, he came into their synagogue. 10 And behold, there was a man having his hand withered. And they asked him, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath? that they might accuse him. 11 But he said to them, What man shall there be of you who has one sheep, and if this fall into a pit on the sabbath, will not lay hold of it and raise it up? 12 How much better then is a man than a sheep! So that it is lawful to do well on the sabbath. 13 Then he says to the man, Stretch out thy hand. And he stretched it out, and it was restored sound as the other.

14 But the Pharisees, having gone out, took counsel against him, how they might destroy him. 15 But Jesus knowing it, withdrew thence, and great crowds followed him; and he healed them all: 16 and charged them strictly that they should not make him publicly known: 17 that that might be fulfilled which was spoken through Esaias the prophet, saying, 18 Behold my servant, whom I have chosen, my beloved, in whom my soul has found its delight. I will put my Spirit upon him, and he shall shew forth judgment to the nations. 19 He shall not strive or cry out, nor shall any one hear his voice in the streets; 20 a bruised reed shall he not break, and smoking flax shall he not quench, until he bring forth judgment unto victory; 21 and on his name shall the nations hope.

22 Then was brought to him one possessed by a demon, blind and dumb, and he healed him, so that the dumb man spake and saw. 23 And all the crowds were amazed and said, Is this man the Son of David? 24 But the Pharisees, having heard it, said, This man does not cast out demons, but by Beelzebub, prince of demons. 25 But he, knowing their thoughts, said to them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation, and every city or house divided against itself will not subsist. 26 And if Satan casts out Satan, he is divided against himself; how then shall his kingdom subsist? 27 And if I cast out demons by Beelzebub, your sons, by whom do they cast them out? For this reason they shall be your judges. 28 But if I by the Spirit of God cast out demons, then indeed the kingdom of God is come upon you. 29 Or how can any one enter into the house of the strong man and plunder his goods, unless first he bind the strong man? and then he will plunder his house. 30 He that is not with me is against me, and he that gathers not with me scatters. 31 For this reason I say unto you, Every sin and injurious speaking shall be forgiven to men, but speaking injuriously of the Spirit shall not be forgiven to men. 32 And whosoever shall have spoken a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him; but whosoever shall speak against the Holy Spirit, it shall not be forgiven him, neither in this age nor in the coming one. 33 Either make the tree good, and its fruit good; or make the tree corrupt, and its fruit corrupt. For from the fruit the tree is known. 34 Offspring of vipers! how can ye speak good things, being wicked? For of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks. 35 The good man out of the good treasure brings forth good things; and the wicked man out of the wicked treasure brings forth wicked things. 36 But I say unto you, that every idle word which men shall say, they shall render an account of it in judgment-day: 37 for by thy words thou shalt be justified, and by thy words thou shalt be condemned.

38 Then answered him some of the scribes and Pharisees, saying, Teacher, we desire to see a sign from thee. 39 But he, answering, said to them, A wicked and adulterous generation seeks after a sign, and a sign shall not be given to it save the sign of Jonas the prophet. 40 For even as Jonas was in the belly of the great fish three days and three nights, thus shall the Son of man be in the heart of the earth three days and three nights. 41 Ninevites shall stand up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for they repented at the preaching of Jonas; and behold, more than Jonas is here. 42 A queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it; for she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and behold, more than Solomon is here. 43 But when the unclean spirit has gone out of the man, he goes through dry places, seeking rest, and does not find it. 44 Then he says, I will return to my house whence I came out; and having come, he finds it unoccupied, swept, and adorned. 45 Then he goes and takes with himself seven other spirits worse than himself, and entering in, they dwell there; and the last condition of that man becomes worse than the first. Thus shall it be to this wicked generation also.

46 But while he was yet speaking to the crowds, behold, his mother and his brethren stood without, seeking to speak to him. 47 Then one said unto him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren are standing without, seeking to speak to thee. 48 But he answering said to him that spoke to him, Who is my mother, and who are my brethren? 49 And, stretching out his hand to his disciples, he said, Behold my mother and my brethren; 50 for whosoever shall do the will of my Father who is in the heavens, he is my brother, and sister, and mother.

Matthew 13

1 And that same day Jesus went out from the house and sat down by the sea. 2 And great crowds were gathered together to him, so that going on board ship himself he sat down, and the whole crowd stood on the shore. 3 And he spoke to them many things in parables, saying, Behold, the sower went out to sow: 4 and as he sowed, some grains fell along the way, and the birds came and devoured them; 5 and others fell upon the rocky places where they had not much earth, and immediately they sprang up out of the ground because of not having any depth of earth, 6 but when the sun rose they were burned up, and because of not having any root were dried up; 7 and others fell upon the thorns, and the thorns grew up and choked them; 8 and others fell upon the good ground, and produced fruit, one a hundred, one sixty, and one thirty. 9 He that has ears, let him hear. 10 And the disciples came up and said to him, Why speakest thou to them in parables? 11 And he answering said to them, Because to you it is given to know the mysteries of the kingdom of the heavens, but to them it is not given; 12 for whoever has, to him shall be given, and he shall be caused to be in abundance; but he who has not, even what he has shall be taken away from him. 13 For this cause I speak to them in parables, because seeing they do not see, and hearing they do not hear nor understand; 14 and in them is filled up the prophecy of Esaias, which says, Hearing ye shall hear and shall not understand, and beholding ye shall behold and not see; 15 for the heart of this people has grown fat, and they have heard heavily with their ears, and they have closed their eyes as asleep, lest they should see with the eyes, and hear with the ears, and understand with the heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them. 16 But blessed are your eyes because they see, and your ears because they hear; 17 for verily I say unto you, that many prophets and righteous men have desired to see the things which ye behold and did not see them, and to hear the things which ye hear and did not hear them. 18 Ye, therefore, hear the parable of the sower. 19 From every one who hears the word of the kingdom and does not understand it, the wicked one comes and catches away what was sown in his heart: this is he that is sown by the wayside. 20 But he that is sown on the rocky places--this is he who hears the word and immediately receives it with joy, 21 but has no root in himself, but is for a time only; and when tribulation or persecution happens on account of the word, he is immediately offended. 22 And he that is sown among the thorns--this is he who hears the word, and the anxious care of this life, and the deceit of riches choke the word, and he becomes unfruitful. 23 But he that is sown upon the good ground--this is he who hears and understands the word, who bears fruit also, and produces, one a hundred, one sixty, and one thirty.

24 Another parable set he before them, saying, The kingdom of the heavens has become like a man sowing good seed in his field; 25 but while men slept, his enemy came and sowed darnel amongst the wheat, and went away. 26 But when the blade shot up and produced fruit, then appeared the darnel also. 27 And the bondmen of the householder came up and said to him, Sir, hast thou not sown good seed in thy field? whence then has it darnel? 28 And he said to them, A man that is an enemy has done this. And the bondmen said to him, Wilt thou then that we should go and gather it up? 29 But he said, No; lest in gathering the darnel ye should root up the wheat with it. 30 Suffer both to grow together unto the harvest, and in time of the harvest I will say to the harvestmen, Gather first the darnel, and bind it into bundles to burn it; but the wheat bring together into my granary. 31 Another parable set he before them, saying, The kingdom of the heavens is like a grain of mustard seed which a man took and sowed in his field; 32 which is less indeed than all seeds, but when it is grown is greater than herbs, and becomes a tree, so that the birds of heaven come and roost in its branches. 33 He spoke another parable to them: The kingdom of the heavens is like leaven, which a woman took and hid in three measures of meal until it had been all leavened. 34 All these things Jesus spoke to the crowds in parables, and without a parable he did not speak to them, 35 so that that should be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophet, saying, I will open my mouth in parables; I will utter things hidden from the world's foundation. 36 Then, having dismissed the crowds, he went into the house; and his disciples came to him, saying, Expound to us the parable of the darnel of the field. 37 But he answering said, He that sows the good seed is the Son of man, 38 and the field is the world; and the good seed, these are the sons of the kingdom, but the darnel are the sons of the evil one; 39 and the enemy who has sowed it is the devil; and the harvest is the completion of the age, and the harvestmen are angels. 40 As then the darnel is gathered and is burned in the fire, thus it shall be in the completion of the age. 41 The Son of man shall send his angels, and they shall gather out of his kingdom all offences, and those that practise lawlessness; 42 and they shall cast them into the furnace of fire; there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth. 43 Then the righteous shall shine forth as the sun in the kingdom of their Father. He that has ears, let him hear.

44 The kingdom of the heavens is like a treasure hid in the field, which a man having found has hid, and for the joy of it goes and sells all whatever he has, and buys that field. 45 Again, the kingdom of the heavens is like a merchant seeking beautiful pearls; 46 and having found one pearl of great value, he went and sold all whatever he had and bought it. 47 Again, the kingdom of the heavens is like a seine which has been cast into the sea, and which has gathered together of every kind, 48 which, when it has been filled, having drawn up on the shore and sat down, they gathered the good into vessels and cast the worthless out. 49 Thus shall it be in the completion of the age: the angels shall go forth and sever the wicked from the midst of the just, 50 and shall cast them into the furnace of fire; there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth. 51 Jesus says to them, Have ye understood all these things? They say to him, Yea, Lord. 52 And he said to them, For this reason every scribe discipled to the kingdom of the heavens is like a man that is a householder who brings out of his treasure things new and old.

53 And it came to pass when Jesus had finished these parables he withdrew thence. 54 And having come into his own country, he taught them in their synagogue, so that they were astonished, and said, Whence has this man this wisdom and these works of power? 55 Is not this the son of the carpenter? Is not his mother called Mary, and his brethren James, and Joseph, and Simon, and Judas? 56 And his sisters, are they not all with us? Whence then has this man all these things? 57 And they were offended in him. And Jesus said to them, A prophet is not without honour, unless in his country and in his house. 58 And he did not there many works of power, because of their unbelief.

Matthew 14

1 At that time Herod the tetrarch heard of the fame of Jesus, 2 and said to his servants, This is John the baptist: he is risen from the dead, and because of this these works of power display their force in him. 3 For Herod had seized John, and had bound him and put him in prison on account of Herodias the wife of Philip his brother. 4 For John said to him, It is not lawful for thee to have her. 5 And while desiring to kill him, he feared the crowd, because they held him for a prophet. 6 But when Herod's birthday was celebrated, the daughter of Herodias danced before them, and pleased Herod; 7 whereupon he promised with oath to give her whatsoever she should ask. 8 But she, being set on by her mother, says, Give me here upon a dish the head of John the baptist. 9 And the king was grieved; but on account of the oaths, and those lying at table with him, he commanded it to be given. 10 And he sent and beheaded John in the prison; 11 and his head was brought upon a dish, and was given to the damsel, and she carried it to her mother. 12 And his disciples came and took the body and buried it, and came and brought word to Jesus.

13 And Jesus, having heard it, went away thence by ship to a desert place apart. And the crowds having heard of it followed him on foot from the cities. 14 And going out he saw a great crowd, and was moved with compassion about them, and healed their infirm. 15 But when even was come, his disciples came to him saying, The place is desert, and much of the day time already gone by; dismiss the crowds, that they may go into the villages and buy food for themselves. 16 But Jesus said to them, They have no need to go: give ye them to eat. 17 But they say to him, We have not here save five loaves and two fishes. 18 And he said, Bring them here to me. 19 And having commanded the crowds to recline upon the grass, having taken the five loaves and the two fishes, he looked up to heaven, and blessed: and having broken the loaves, he gave themto the disciples, and the disciples gave them to the crowds. 20 And all ate and were filled, and they took up what was over and above of fragments twelve hand-baskets full. 21 But those that had eaten were about five thousand men, besides women and children.

22 And immediately he compelled the disciples to go on board ship, and to go on before him to the other side, until he should have dismissed the crowds. 23 And having dismissed the crowds, he went up into the mountain apart to pray. And when even was come, he was alone there, 24 but the ship was already in the middle of the sea tossed by the waves, for the wind was contrary. 25 But in the fourth watch of the night he went off to them, walking on the sea. 26 And the disciples, seeing him walking on the sea, were troubled, saying, It is an apparition. And they cried out through fear. 27 But Jesus immediately spoke to them, saying, Take courage; it is I: be not afraid. 28 And Peter answering him said, Lord, if it be thou, command me to come to thee upon the waters. 29 And he said, Come. And Peter, having descended from the ship, walked upon the waters to go to Jesus. 30 But seeing the wind strong he was afraid; and beginning to sink he cried out, saying, Lord, save me. 31 And immediately Jesus stretched out his hand and caught hold of him, and says to him, O thou of little faith, why didst thou doubt? 32 And when they had gone up into the ship, the wind fell. 33 But those in the ship came and did homage to him, saying, Truly thou art God's Son.

34 And having crossed over they came to the land of Gennesaret. 35 And when the men of that place recognised him, they sent to that whole country around, and they brought to him all that were ill, 36 and besought him that they might only touch the hem of his garment; and as many as touched were made thoroughly well.

Matthew 15

1 Then the scribes and Pharisees from Jerusalem come up to Jesus, saying, 2 Why do thy disciples transgress what has been delivered by the ancients? for they do not wash their hands when they eat bread. 3 But he answering said to them, Why do ye also transgress the commandment of God on account of your traditional teaching? 4 For God commanded saying, Honour father and mother; and, He that speaks ill of father or mother, let him die the death. 5 But ye say, Whosoever shall say to his father or mother, It is a gift, whatsoever it be by which received from me thou wouldest be profited: 6 and he shall in no wise honour his father or his mother; and ye have made void the commandment of God on account of your traditional teaching. 7 Hypocrites! well has Esaias prophesied about you, saying, 8 This people honour me with the lips, but their heart is far away from me; 9 but in vain do they worship me, teaching as teachings commandments of men.

10 And having called to him the crowd, he said to them, Hear and understand: 11 Not what enters into the mouth defiles the man; but what goes forth out of the mouth, this defiles the man. 12 Then his disciples, coming up, said to him, Dost thou know that the Pharisees, having heard this word, have been offended? 13 But he answering said, Every plant which my heavenly Father has not planted shall be rooted up. 14 Leave them alone; they are blind leaders of blind: but if blind lead blind, both will fall into a ditch. 15 And Peter answering said to him, Expound to us this parable. 16 But he said, Are ye also still without intelligence? 17 Do ye not yet apprehend, that everything that enters into the mouth finds its way into the belly, and is cast forth into the draught? 18 but the things which go forth out of the mouth come out of the heart, and those defile man. 19 For out of the heart come forth evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, false witnessings, blasphemies; 20 these are the things which defile man; but the eating with unwashen hands does not defile man.

21 And Jesus, going forth from thence, went away into the parts of Tyre and Sidon; 22 and lo, a Canaanitish woman, coming out from those borders, cried to him saying, Have pity on me, Lord, Son of David; my daughter is miserably possessed by a demon. 23 But he did not answer her a word. And his disciples came to him and asked him, saying, Dismiss her, for she cries after us. 24 But he answering said, I have not been sent save to the lost sheep of Israel's house. 25 But she came and did him homage, saying, Lord, help me. 26 But he answering said, It is not well to take the bread of the children and cast it to the dogs. 27 But she said, Yea, Lord; for even the dogs eat of the crumbs which fall from the table of their masters. 28 Then Jesus answering said to her, O woman, thy faith is great. Be it to thee as thou desirest. And her daughter was healed from that hour.

29 And Jesus, going away from thence, came towards the sea of Galilee, and he went up into the mountain and sat down there; 30 and great crowds came to him, having with them lame, blind, dumb, crippled, and many others, and they cast them at his feet, and he healed them: 31 so that the crowds wondered, seeing dumb speaking, crippled sound, lame walking, and blind seeing; and they glorified the God of Israel. 32 But Jesus, having called his disciples to him, said, I have compassion on the crowd, because they have stayed with me already three days and they have not anything they can eat, and I would not send them away fasting lest they should faint on the way. 33 And his disciples say to him, Whence should we have so many loaves in the wilderness as to satisfy so great a crowd? 34 And Jesus says to them, How many loaves have ye? But they said, Seven, and a few small fishes. 35 And he commanded the crowds to lie down on the ground; 36 and having taken the seven loaves and the fishes, having given thanks, he broke them and gave them to his disciples, and the disciples to the crowd. 37 And all ate and were filled; and they took up what was over and above of the fragments seven baskets full; 38 but they that ate were four thousand men, besides women and children. 39 And, having dismissed the crowds, he went on board ship and came to the borders of Magadan.

Matthew 16

1 And the Pharisees and Sadducees, coming to him, asked him, tempting him, to shew them a sign out of heaven. 2 But he answering said to them, When evening is come, ye say, Fine weather, for the sky is red; 3 and in the morning, A storm to-day, for the sky is red and lowering; ye know how to discern the face of the sky, but ye cannot the signs of the times. 4 A wicked and adulterous generation seeks after a sign, and a sign shall not be given to it save the sign of Jonas. And he left them and went away.

5 And when his disciples were come to the other side, they had forgotten to take bread. 6 And Jesus said to them, See and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees. 7 And they reasoned among themselves, saying, Because we have taken no bread. 8 And Jesus knowing it, said, Why reason ye among yourselves, O ye of little faith, because ye have taken no bread? 9 Do ye not yet understand nor remember the five loaves of the five thousand, and how many hand-baskets ye took up? 10 nor the seven loaves of the four thousand, and how many baskets ye took up? 11 How do ye not understand that it was not concerning bread I said to you, Beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees? 12 Then they comprehended that he did not speak of being beware of the leaven of bread, but of the doctrine of the Pharisees and Sadducees.

13 But when Jesus was come into the parts of Caesarea-Philippi, he demanded of his disciples, saying, Who do men say that I the Son of man am? 14 And they said, Some, John the baptist; and others, Elias; and others again, Jeremias or one of the prophets. 15 He says to them, But ye, who do ye say that I am? 16 And Simon Peter answering said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God. 17 And Jesus answering said to him, Blessed art thou, Simon Bar-jona, for flesh and blood has not revealed it to thee, but my Father who is in the heavens. 18 And I also, I say unto thee that thou art Peter, and on this rock I will build my assembly, and hades' gates shall not prevail against it. 19 And I will give to thee the keys of the kingdom of the heavens; and whatsoever thou mayest bind upon the earth shall be bound in the heavens; and whatsoever thou mayest loose on the earth shall be loosed in the heavens. 20 Then he enjoined on his disciples that they should say to no man that he was the Christ.

21 From that time Jesus began to shew to his disciples that he must go away to Jerusalem, and suffer many things from the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and the third day be raised. 22 And Peter taking him to him began to rebuke him, saying, God be favourable to thee, Lord; this shall in no wise be unto thee. 23 But turning round, he said to Peter, Get away behind me, Satan; thou art an offence to me, for thy mind is not on the things that are of God, but on the things that are of men.

24 Then Jesus said to his disciples, If any one desires to come after me, let him deny himself and take up his cross and follow me. 25 For whosoever shall desire to save his life shall lose it; but whosoever shall lose his life for my sake shall find it. 26 For what does a man profit, if he should gain the whole world and suffer the loss of his soul? or what shall a man give in exchange for his soul? 27 For the Son of man is about to come in the glory of his Father with his angels, and then he will render to each according to his doings. 28 Verily I say unto you, There are some of those standing here that shall not taste of death at all until they shall have seen the Son of man coming in his kingdom.

Matthew 17

1 And after six days Jesus takes with him Peter, and James, and John his brother, and brings them up into a high mountain apart. 2 And he was transfigured before them. And his face shone as the sun, and his garments became white as the light; 3 and lo, Moses and Elias appeared to them talking with him. 4 And Peter answering said to Jesus, Lord, it is good we should be here. If thou wilt, let us make here three tabernacles: for thee one, and for Moses one, and one for Elias. 5 While he was still speaking, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them, and lo, a voice out of the cloud, saying, This is my beloved Son, in whom I have found my delight: hear him. 6 And the disciples hearing it fell upon their faces, and were greatly terrified. 7 And Jesus coming to them touched them, and said, Rise up, and be not terrified. 8 And lifting up their eyes, they saw no one but Jesus alone. 9 And as they descended from the mountain, Jesus charged them, saying, Tell the vision to no one, until the Son of man be risen up from among the dead. 10 And his disciples demanded of him saying, Why then say the scribes that Elias must first have come? 11 And he answering said to them, Elias indeed comes first and will restore all things. 12 But I say unto you that Elias has already come, and they have not known him, but have done unto him whatever they would. Thus also the Son of man is about to suffer from them. 13 Then the disciples understood that he spoke to them of John the baptist.

14 And when they came to the crowd, a man came to him, falling on his knees before him, and saying, 15 Lord, have mercy on my son, for he is lunatic, and suffers sorely; for often he falls into the fire and often into the water. 16 And I brought him to thy disciples, and they were not able to heal him. 17 And Jesus answering said, O unbelieving and perverted generation, how long shall I be with you? how long shall I bear with you? Bring him here to me. 18 And Jesus rebuked him, and the demon went out from him, and the boy was healed from that hour. 19 Then the disciples, coming to Jesus apart, said to him, Why were not we able to cast him out? 20 And he says to them, Because of your unbelief; for verily I say unto you, If ye have faith as a grain of mustard seed, ye shall say to this mountain, Be transported hence there, and it shall transport itself; and nothing shall be impossible to you. 21 But this kind does not go out but by prayer and fasting.

22 And while they abode in Galilee, Jesus said to them, The Son of man is about to be delivered up into the hands of men, 23 and they shall kill him; and the third day he shall be raised up. And they were greatly grieved.

24 And when they came to Capernaum, those who received the didrachmas came to Peter and said, Does your teacher not pay the didrachmas? 25 He says, Yes. And when he came into the house, Jesus anticipated him, saying, What dost thou think, Simon? the kings of the earth, from whom do they receive custom or tribute? from their own sons or from strangers? 26 Peter says to him, From strangers. Jesus said to him, Then are the sons free. 27 But that we may not be an offence to them, go to the sea and cast a hook, and take the first fish that comes up, and when thou hast opened its mouth thou wilt find a stater; take that and give it to them for me and thee.

Matthew 18

1 In that hour the disciples came to Jesus saying, Who then is greatest in the kingdom of the heavens? 2 And Jesus having called a little child to him, set it in their midst, 3 and said, Verily I say to you, Unless ye are converted and become as little children, ye will not at all enter into the kingdom of the heavens. 4 Whoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child, he is the greatest in the kingdom of the heavens; 5 and whosoever shall receive one such little child in my name, receives me. 6 But whosoever shall offend one of these little ones who believe in me, it were profitable for him that a great millstone had been hanged upon his neck and he be sunk in the depths of the sea.

7 Woe to the world because of offences! For it must needs be that offences come; yet woe to that man by whom the offence comes! 8 And if thy hand or thy foot offend thee, cut it off and cast it from thee; it is good for thee to enter into life lame or maimed, rather than having two hands or two feet to be cast into eternal fire. 9 And if thine eye offend thee, pluck it out and cast it from thee; it is good for thee to enter into life one-eyed, rather than having two eyes to be cast into the hell of fire. 10 See that ye do not despise one of these little ones; for I say unto you that their angels in the heavens continually behold the face of my Father who is in the heavens. 11 For the Son of man has come to save that which was lost. 12 What think ye? If a certain man should have a hundred sheep, and one of them be gone astray, does he not, leaving the ninety and nine on the mountains, go and seek the one that has gone astray? 13 And if it should come to pass that he find it, verily I say unto you, he rejoices more because of it than because of the ninety and nine not gone astray. 14 So it is not the will of your Father who is in the heavens that one of these little ones should perish.

15 But if thy brother sin against thee, go, reprove him between thee and him alone. If he hear thee, thou hast gained thy brother. 16 But if he do not hear thee, take with thee one or two besides, that every matter may stand upon the word of two witnesses or of three. 17 But if he will not listen to them, tell it to the assembly; and if also he will not listen to the assembly, let him be to thee as one of the nations and a tax-gatherer. 18 Verily I say to you, Whatsoever ye shall bind on the earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatsoever ye shall loose on the earth shall be loosed in heaven. 19 Again I say to you, that if two of you shall agree on the earth concerning any matter, whatsoever it may be that they shall ask, it shall come to them from my Father who is in the heavens. 20 For where two or three are gathered together unto my name, there am I in the midst of them.

21 Then Peter came to him and said, Lord, how often shall my brother sin against me and I forgive him? until seven times? 22 Jesus says to him, I say not to thee until seven times, but until seventy times seven. 23 For this cause the kingdom of the heavens has become like a king who would reckon with his bondmen. 24 And having begun to reckon, one debtor of ten thousand talents was brought to him. 25 But he not having anything to pay, his lord commanded him to be sold, and his wife, and his children, and everything that he had, and that payment should be made. 26 The bondman therefore falling down did him homage, saying, Lord, have patience with me and I will pay thee all. 27 And the lord of that bondman, being moved with compassion, loosed him and forgave him the loan. 28 But that bondman having gone out, found one of his fellow-bondmen who owed him a hundred denarii. And having seized him, he throttled him, saying, Pay me if thou owest anything. 29 His fellow-bondman therefore, having fallen down at his feet, besought him, saying, Have patience with me, and I will pay thee. 30 But he would not, but went away and cast him into prison, until he should pay what was owing. 31 But his fellow-bondmen, having seen what had taken place, were greatly grieved, and went and recounted to their lord all that had taken place. 32 Then his lord, having called him to him, says to him, Wicked bondman! I forgave thee all that debt because thou besoughtest me; 33 shouldest not thou also have had compassion on thy fellow-bondman, as I also had compassion on thee? 34 And his lord being angry delivered him to the tormentors till he paid all that was owing to him. 35 Thus also my heavenly Father shall do to you if ye forgive not from your hearts every one his brother.

Matthew 19

1 And it came to pass, when Jesus had finished these words, he withdrew from Galilee, and came to the coasts of Judaea beyond the Jordan; 2 and great crowds followed him, and he healed them there.

3 And the Pharisees came to him tempting him, and saying, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife for every cause? 4 But he answering said to them, Have ye not read that he who made them, from the beginning made them male and female, 5 and said, On account of this a man shall leave father and mother, and shall be united to his wife, and the two shall be one flesh? 6 so that they are no longer two, but one flesh. What therefore God has joined together, let not man separate. 7 They say to him, Why then did Moses command to give a letter of divorce and to send her away? 8 He says to them, Moses, in view of your hardheartedness, allowed you to put away your wives; but from the beginning it was not thus. 9 But I say unto you, that whosoever shall put away his wife, not for fornication, and shall marry another, commits adultery; and he who marries one put away commits adultery. 10 His disciples say to him, If the case of the man be so with his wife, it is not good to marry. 11 And he said to them, All cannot receive this word, but those to whom it has been given; 12 for there are eunuchs which have been born thus from their mother's womb; and there are eunuchs who have been made eunuchs of men; and there are eunuchs who have made eunuchs of themselves for the sake of the kingdom of the heavens. He that is able to receive it, let him receive it.

13 Then there were brought to him little children that he might lay his hands on them and pray; but the disciples rebuked them. 14 But Jesus said, Suffer little children, and do not hinder them from coming to me; for the kingdom of the heavens is of such: 15 and having laid his hands upon them, he departed thence.

16 And lo, one coming up said to him, Teacher, what good thing shall I do that I may have life eternal? 17 And he said to him, What askest thou me concerning goodness? one is good. But if thou wouldest enter into life, keep the commandments. 18 He says to him, Which? And Jesus said, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness, 19 Honour thy father and thy mother, and Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. 20 The young man says to him, All these have I kept; what lack I yet? 21 Jesus said to him, If thou wouldest be perfect, go, sell what thou hast and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven; and come, follow me. 22 But the young man, having heard the word, went away grieved, for he had large possessions.

23 And Jesus said to his disciples, Verily I say unto you, A rich man shall with difficulty enter into the kingdom of the heavens; 24 and again I say unto you, It is easier for a camel to enter a needle's eye than a rich man into the kingdom of God. 25 And when the disciples heard it they were exceedingly astonished, saying, Who then can be saved? 26 But Jesus, looking on them, said to them, With men this is impossible; but with God all things are possible. 27 Then Peter answering said to him, Behold, we have left all things and have followed thee; what then shall happen to us? 28 And Jesus said to them, Verily I say unto you, That ye who have followed me, in the regeneration when the Son of man shall sit down upon his throne of glory, ye also shall sit on twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel. 29 And every one who has left houses, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my name's sake, shall receive a hundredfold, and shall inherit life eternal. 30 But many first shall be last, and last first.

Matthew 20

1 For the kingdom of the heavens is like a householder who went out with the early morn to hire workmen for his vineyard. 2 And having agreed with the workmen for a denarius the day, he sent them into his vineyard. 3 And having gone out about the third hour, he saw others standing in the market-place idle; 4 and to them he said, Go also ye into the vineyard, and whatsoever may be just I will give you. And they went their way. 5 Again, having gone out about the sixth and ninth hour, he did likewise. 6 But about the eleventh hour, having gone out, he found others standing, and says to them, Why stand ye here all the day idle? 7 They say to him, Because no man has hired us. He says to them, Go also ye into the vineyard and whatsoever may be just ye shall receive. 8 But when the evening was come, the lord of the vineyard says to his steward, Call the workmen and pay them their wages, beginning from the last even to the first. 9 And when they who came to work about the eleventh hour came, they received each a denarius. 10 And when the first came, they supposed that they would receive more, and they received also themselves each a denarius. 11 And on receiving it they murmured against the master of the house, 12 saying, These last have worked one hour, and thou hast made them equal to us, who have borne the burden of the day and the heat. 13 But he answering said to one of them, My friend, I do not wrong thee. Didst thou not agree with me for a denarius? 14 Take what is thine and go. But it is my will to give to this last even as to thee: 15 is it not lawful for me to do what I will in my own affairs? Is thine eye evil because I am good? 16 Thus shall the last be first, and the first last; for many are called ones, but few chosen ones.

17 And Jesus, going up to Jerusalem, took the twelve disciples with him apart in the way, and said to them, 18 Behold we go up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man will be delivered up to the chief priests and scribes, and they will condemn him to death; 19 and they will deliver him up to the nations to mock and to scourge and to crucify, and the third day he shall rise again.

20 Then came to him the mother of the sons of Zebedee, with her sons, doing homage, and asking something of him. 21 And he said to her, What wilt thou? She says to him, Speak the word that these my two sons may sit, one on thy right hand and one on thy left in thy kingdom. 22 And Jesus answering said, Ye know not what ye ask. Can ye drink the cup which I am about to drink? They say to him, We are able. 23 And he says to them, Ye shall drink indeed my cup, but to sit on my right hand and on my left, is not mine to give, but to those for whom it is prepared of my Father. 24 And the ten, having heard of it, were indignant about the two brothers. 25 But Jesus having called them to him, said, Ye know that the rulers of the nations exercise lordship over them, and the great exercise authority over them. 26 It shall not be thus amongst you, but whosoever will be great among you, shall be your servant; 27 and whosoever will be first among you, let him be your bondman; 28 as indeed the Son of man did not come to be served, but to serve, and to give his life a ransom for many.

29 And as they went out from Jericho a great crowd followed him. 30 And lo, two blind men, sitting by the wayside, having heard that Jesus was passing by, cried out saying, Have mercy on us, Lord, Son of David. 31 But the crowd rebuked them, that they might be silent. But they cried out the more, saying, Have mercy on us, Lord, Son of David. 32 And Jesus, having stopped, called them and said, What will ye that I shall do to you? 33 They say to him, Lord, that our eyes may be opened. 34 And Jesus, moved with compassion, touched their eyes; and immediately their eyes had sight restored to them, and they followed him.

Matthew 21

1 And when they drew near to Jerusalem and came to Bethphage, at the mount of Olives, then Jesus sent two disciples, 2 saying to them, Go into the village over against you, and immediately ye will find an ass tied, and a colt with it; loose them and lead them to me. 3 And if any one say anything to you, ye shall say, The Lord has need of them, and straightway he will send them. 4 But all this came to pass, that that might be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophet, saying, 5 Say to the daughter of Zion, Behold thy King cometh to thee, meek, and mounted upon an ass, and upon a colt the foal of an ass. 6 But the disciples, having gone and done as Jesus had ordered them, 7 brought the ass and the colt and put their garments upon them, and he sat on them. 8 But a very great crowd strewed their own garments on the way, and others kept cutting down branches from the trees and strewing them on the way. 9 And the crowds who went before him and who followed cried, saying, Hosanna to the Son of David; blessed be he who comes in the name of the Lord; hosanna in the highest. 10 And as he entered into Jerusalem, the whole city was moved, saying, Who is this? 11 And the crowds said, This is Jesus the prophet who is from Nazareth of Galilee.

12 And Jesus entered into the temple of God, and cast out all that sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the money-changers and the seats of those that sold the doves. 13 And he says to them, It is written, My house shall be called a house of prayer, but ye have made it a den of robbers. 14 And blind and lame came to him in the temple, and he healed them. 15 And when the chief priests and the scribes saw the wonders which he wrought, and the children crying in the temple and saying, Hosanna to the Son of David, they were indignant, 16 and said to him, Hearest thou what these say? And Jesus says to them, Yea; have ye never read, Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings thou hast perfected praise? 17 And leaving them he went forth out of the city to Bethany, and there he passed the night.

18 But early in the morning, as he came back into the city, he hungered. 19 And seeing one fig-tree in the way, he came to it and found on it nothing but leaves only. And he says to it, Let there be never more fruit of thee for ever. And the fig-tree was immediately dried up. 20 And when the disciples saw it, they wondered, saying, How immediately is the fig-tree dried up! 21 And Jesus answering said to them, Verily I say unto you, If ye have faith, and do not doubt, not only shall ye do what is done to the fig-tree, but even if ye should say to this mountain, Be thou taken away and be thou cast into the sea, it shall come to pass. 22 And all things whatsoever ye shall ask in prayer, believing, ye shall receive.

23 And when he came into the temple, the chief priests and the elders of the people came to him as he was teaching, saying, By what authority doest thou these things? and who gave thee this authority? 24 And Jesus answering said to them, I also will ask you one thing, which if ye tell me, I also will tell you by what authority I do these things: 25 The baptism of John, whence was it? of heaven or of men? And they reasoned among themselves, saying, If we should say, Of heaven, he will say to us, Why then have ye not believed him? 26 but if we should say, Of men, we fear the crowd, for all hold John for a prophet. 27 And answering Jesus they said, We do not know. He also said to them, Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.

28 But what think ye? A man had two children, and coming to the first he said, Child, go to-day, work in my vineyard. 29 And he answering said, I will not; but afterwards repenting himself he went. 30 And coming to the second he said likewise; and he answering said, I go, sir, and went not. 31 Which of the two did the will of the father? They say to him, The first. Jesus says to them, Verily I say unto you that the tax-gatherers and the harlots go into the kingdom of God before you. 32 For John came to you in the way of righteousness, and ye believed him not; but the tax-gatherers and the harlots believed him; but ye when ye saw it repented not yourselves afterwards to believe him.

33 Hear another parable: There was a householder who planted a vineyard, and made a fence round it, and dug a winepress in it, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and left the country. 34 But when the time of fruit drew near, he sent his bondmen to the husbandmen to receive his fruits. 35 And the husbandmen took his bondmen, and beat one, killed another, and stoned another. 36 Again he sent other bondmen more than the first, and they did to them in like manner. 37 And at last he sent to them his son, saying, They will have respect for my son. 38 But the husbandmen, seeing the son, said among themselves, This is the heir; come, let us kill him and possess his inheritance. 39 And they took him, and cast him forth out of the vineyard, and killed him. 40 When therefore the lord of the vineyard comes, what shall he do to those husbandmen? 41 They say to him, He will miserably destroy those evil men, and let out the vineyard to other husbandmen, who shall render him the fruits in their seasons. 42 Jesus says to them, Have ye never read in the scriptures, The stone which they that builded rejected, this has become the corner-stone: this is of the Lord, and it is wonderful in our eyes? 43 Therefore I say to you, that the kingdom of God shall be taken from you and shall be given to a nation producing the fruits of it. 44 And he that falls on this stone shall be broken, but on whomsoever it shall fall, it shall grind him to powder. 45 And the chief priests and the Pharisees, having heard his parables, knew that he spoke about them. 46 And seeking to lay hold of him, they were afraid of the crowds, because they held him for a prophet.

Matthew 22

1 And Jesus answering spoke to them again in parables, saying, 2 The kingdom of the heavens has become like a king who made a wedding feast for his son, 3 and sent his bondmen to call the persons invited to the wedding feast, and they would not come. 4 Again he sent other bondmen, saying, Say to the persons invited, Behold, I have prepared my dinner; my oxen and my fatted beasts are killed, and all things ready; come to the wedding feast. 5 But they made light of it, and went, one to his own land, and another to his commerce. 6 And the rest, laying hold of his bondmen, ill-treated and slew them. 7 And when the king heard of it he was wroth, and having sent his forces, destroyed those murderers and burned their city. 8 Then he says to his bondmen, The wedding feast is ready, but those invited were not worthy; 9 go therefore into the thoroughfares of the highways, and as many as ye shall find invite to the wedding feast. 10 And those bondmen went out into the highways, and brought together all as many as they found, both evil and good; and the wedding feast was furnished with guests. 11 And the king, having gone in to see the guests, beheld there a man not clothed with a wedding garment. 12 And he says to him, My friend, how camest thou in here not having on a wedding garment? But he was speechless. 13 Then said the king to the servants, Bind him feet and hands, and take him away, and cast him out into the outer darkness: there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth. 14 For many are called ones, but few chosen ones.

15 Then went the Pharisees and held a council how they might ensnare him in speaking. 16 And they send out to him their disciples with the Herodians, saying, Teacher, we know that thou art true and teachest the way of God in truth, and carest not for any one, for thou regardest not men's person; 17 tell us therefore what thou thinkest: Is it lawful to give tribute to Caesar, or not? 18 But Jesus, knowing their wickedness, said, Why tempt ye me, hypocrites? 19 Shew me the money of the tribute. And they presented to him a denarius. 20 And he says to them, Whose is this image and superscription? 21 They say to him, Caesar's. Then he says to them, Pay then what is Caesar's to Caesar, and what is God's to God. 22 And when they heard him, they wondered, and left him, and went away.

23 On that day came to him Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection; and they demanded of him, 24 saying, Teacher, Moses said, If any one die, not having children, his brother shall marry his wife and shall raise up seed to his brother. 25 Now there were with us seven brethren; and the first having married died, and not having seed, left his wife to his brother. 26 In like manner also the second and the third, unto the seven. 27 And last of all the woman also died. 28 In the resurrection therefore of which of the seven shall she be wife, for all had her? 29 And Jesus answering said to them, Ye err, not knowing the scriptures nor the power of God. 30 For in the resurrection they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are as angels of God in heaven. 31 But concerning the resurrection of the dead, have ye not read what was spoken to you by God, saying, 32 I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? God is not God of the dead, but of the living. 33 And when the crowds heard it they were astonished at his doctrine.

34 But the Pharisees, having heard that he had put the Sadducees to silence, were gathered together. 35 And one of them, a lawyer, demanded, tempting him, and saying, 36 Teacher, which is the great commandment in the law? 37 And he said to him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy understanding. 38 This is the great and first commandment. 39 And the second is like it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. 40 On these two commandments the whole law and the prophets hang.

41 And the Pharisees being gathered together, Jesus demanded of them, 42 saying, What think ye concerning the Christ? whose son is he? They say to him, David's. 43 He says to them, How then does David in Spirit call him Lord, saying, 44 The Lord said to my Lord, Sit on my right hand until I put thine enemies under thy feet? 45 If therefore David call him Lord, how is he his son? 46 And no one was able to answer him a word, nor did any one dare from that day to question him any more.

Matthew 23

1 Then Jesus spoke to the crowds and to his disciples, 2 saying, The scribes and the Pharisees have set themselves down in Moses' seat: 3 all things therefore, whatever they may tell you, do and keep. But do not after their works, for they say and do not, 4 but bind burdens heavy and hard to bear, and lay them on the shoulders of men, but will not move them with their finger. 5 And all their works they do to be seen of men: for they make broad their phylacteries and enlarge the borders of their garments, 6 and love the chief place in feasts and the first seats in the synagogues, 7 and salutations in the market-places, and to be called of men, Rabbi, Rabbi. 8 But ye, be not ye called Rabbi; for one is your instructor, and all ye are brethren. 9 And call not any one your father upon the earth; for one is your Father, he who is in the heavens. 10 Neither be called instructors, for one is your instructor, the Christ. 11 But the greatest of you shall be your servant. 12 And whoever shall exalt himself shall be humbled, and whoever shall humble himself shall be exalted.

13 But woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, for ye shut up the kingdom of the heavens before men; for ye do not enter, nor do ye suffer those that are entering to go in.[*] 15 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, for ye compass the sea and the dry land to make one proselyte, and when he is become such, ye make him twofold more the son of hell than yourselves. 16 Woe to you, blind guides, who say, Whosoever shall swear by the temple, it is nothing; but whosoever shall swear by the gold of the temple, he is a debtor. 17 Fools and blind, for which is greater, the gold, or the temple which sanctifies the gold? 18 And, Whosoever shall swear by the altar, it is nothing; but whosoever shall swear by the gift that is upon it is a debtor. 19 Fools and blind ones, for which is greater, the gift, or the altar which sanctifies the gift? 20 He therefore that swears by the altar swears by it and by all things that are upon it. 21 And he that swears by the temple swears by it and by him that dwells in it. 22 And he that swears by heaven swears by the throne of God and by him that sits upon it. 23 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, for ye pay tithes of mint and anise and cummin, and ye have left aside the weightier matters of the law, judgment and mercy and faith: these ye ought to have done and not have left those aside. 24 Blind guides, who strain out the gnat, but drink down the camel. 25 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, for ye make clean the outside of the cup and of the dish, but within they are full of rapine and intemperance. 26 Blind Pharisee, make clean first the inside of the cup and of the dish, that their outside also may become clean. 27 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, for ye are like whited sepulchres, which appear beautiful outwardly, but within are full of dead men's bones and all uncleanness. 28 Thus also ye, outwardly ye appear righteous to men, but within are full of hypocrisy and lawlessness. 29 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, for ye build the sepulchres of the prophets and adorn the tombs of the just, 30 and ye say, If we had been in the days of our fathers we would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets. 31 So that ye bear witness of yourselves that ye are sons of those who slew the prophets: 32 and ye, fill ye up the measure of your fathers. 33 Serpents, offspring of vipers, how should ye escape the judgment of hell?

34 Therefore, behold, I send unto you prophets, and wise men, and scribes; and some of them ye will kill and crucify, and some of them ye will scourge in your synagogues, and will persecute from city to city; 35 so that all righteous blood shed upon the earth should come upon you, from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zacharias son of Barachias, whom ye slew between the temple and the altar. 36 Verily I say unto you, All these things shall come upon this generation. 37 Jerusalem, Jerusalem, the city that kills the prophets and stones those that are sent unto her, how often would I have gathered thy children as a hen gathers her chickens under her wings, and ye would not! 38 Behold, your house is left unto you desolate; 39 for I say unto you, Ye shall in no wise see me henceforth until ye say, Blessed be he that comes in the name of the Lord.

Verse 14 of A.V. is not in the best MSS.

Matthew 24

1 And Jesus went forth and went away from the temple, and his disciples came to him to point out to him the buildings of the temple. 2 And he answering said to them, Do ye not see all these things? Verily I say to you, Not a stone shall be left here upon a stone which shall not be thrown down. 3 And as he was sitting upon the mount of Olives the disciples came to him privately, saying, Tell us, when shall these things be, and what is the sign of thy coming and the completion of the age?

4 And Jesus answering said to them, See that no one mislead you. 5 For many shall come in my name, saying, I am the Christ, and they shall mislead many. 6 But ye will hear of wars and rumours of wars. See that ye be not disturbed; for all these things must take place, but it is not yet the end. 7 For nation shall rise up against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; and there shall be famines and pestilences, and earthquakes in divers places. 8 But all these are the beginning of throes. 9 Then shall they deliver you up to tribulation, and shall kill you; and ye will be hated of all the nations for my name's sake. 10 And then will many be offended, and will deliver one another up, and hate one another; 11 and many false prophets shall arise and shall mislead many; 12 and because lawlessness shall prevail, the love of the most shall grow cold; 13 but he that has endured to the end, he shall be saved. 14 And these glad tidings of the kingdom shall be preached in the whole habitable earth, for a witness to all the nations, and then shall come the end. 15 When therefore ye shall see the abomination of desolation, which is spoken of through Daniel the prophet, standing in what is a holy place, (he that reads let him understand,) 16 then let those who are in Judaea flee to the mountains; 17 let not him that is on the house come down to take the things out of his house; 18 and let not him that is in the field turn back to take his garment. 19 But woe to those that are with child, and those that give suck in those days. 20 But pray that your flight may not be in winter time nor on sabbath: 21 for then shall there be great tribulation, such as has not been from the beginning of the world until now, nor ever shall be; 22 and if those days had not been cut short, no flesh had been saved; but on account of the elect those days shall be cut short. 23 Then if any one say to you, Behold, here is the Christ, or here, believe it not. 24 For there shall arise false Christs, and false prophets, and shall give great signs and wonders, so as to mislead, if possible, even the elect. 25 Behold, I have told you beforehand. 26 If therefore they say to you, Behold, he is in the desert, go not forth; behold, he is in the inner chambers, do not believe it. 27 For as the lightning goes forth from the east and shines to the west, so shall be the coming of the Son of man. 28 For wherever the carcase is, there will be gathered the eagles. 29 But immediately after the tribulation of those days the sun shall be darkened, and the moon not give her light, and the stars shall fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens shall be shaken. 30 And then shall appear the sign of the Son of man in heaven; and then shall all the tribes of the land lament, and they shall see the Son of man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory. 31 And he shall send his angels with a great sound of trumpet, and they shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from the one extremity of the heavens to the other extremity of them.

32 But learn the parable from the fig-tree: When already its branch becomes tender and produces leaves, ye know that the summer is near. 33 Thus also ye, when ye see all these things, know that it is near, at the doors. 34 Verily I say to you, This generation will not have passed away until all these things shall have taken place. 35 The heaven and the earth shall pass away, but my words shall in no wise pass away. 36 But of that day and hour no one knows, not even the angels of the heavens, but my Father alone. 37 But as the days of Noe, so also shall be the coming of the Son of man. 38 For as they were in the days which were before the flood, eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, until the day on which Noe entered into the ark, 39 and they knew not till the flood came and took all away; thus also shall be the coming of the Son of man. 40 Then two shall be in the field, one is taken and one is left; 41 two women grinding at the mill, one is taken and one is left. 42 Watch therefore, for ye know not in what hour your Lord comes. 43 But know this, that if the master of the house had known in what watch the thief was coming, he would have watched and not have suffered his house to be dug through into. 44 Wherefore ye also, be ye ready, for in that hour that ye think not the Son of man comes. 45 Who then is the faithful and prudent bondman whom his lord has set over his household, to give them food in season? 46 Blessed is that bondman whom his lord on coming shall find doing thus. 47 Verily I say unto you, that he will set him over all his substance. 48 But if that evil bondman should say in his heart, My lord delays to come, 49 and begin to beat his fellow-bondmen, and eat and drink with the drunken; 50 the lord of that bondman shall come in a day when he does not expect it, and in an hour he knows not of, 51 and shall cut him in two and appoint his portion with the hypocrites: there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth.

Matthew 25

1 Then shall the kingdom of the heavens be made like to ten virgins that having taken their torches, went forth to meet the bridegroom. 2 And five of them were prudent and five foolish. 3 They that were foolish took their torches and did not take oil with them; 4 but the prudent took oil in their vessels with their torches. 5 Now the bridegroom tarrying, they all grew heavy and slept. 6 But in the middle of the night there was a cry, Behold, the bridegroom; go forth to meet him. 7 Then all those virgins arose and trimmed their torches. 8 And the foolish said to the prudent, Give us of your oil, for our torches are going out. 9 But the prudent answered saying, We cannot, lest it might not suffice for us and for you. Go rather to those that sell, and buy for yourselves. 10 But as they went away to buy, the bridegroom came, and the ones that were ready went in with him to the wedding feast, and the door was shut. 11 Afterwards come also the rest of the virgins, saying, Lord, Lord, open to us; 12 but he answering said, Verily I say unto you, I do not know you. 13 Watch therefore, for ye know not the day nor the hour.

14 For it is as if a man going away out of a country called his own bondmen and delivered to them his substance. 15 And to one he gave five talents, to another two, and to another one; to each according to his particular ability, and immediately went away out of the country. 16 And he that had received the five talents went and trafficked with them, and made five other talents. 17 In like manner also he that had received the two, he also gained two others. 18 But he that had received the one went and dug in the earth, and hid the money of his lord. 19 And after a long time the lord of those bondmen comes and reckons with them. 20 And he that had received the five talents came to him and brought five other talents, saying, My lord, thou deliveredst me five talents; behold, I have gained five other talents besides them. 21 His lord said to him, Well, good and faithful bondman, thou wast faithful over a few things, I will set thee over many things: enter into the joy of thy lord. 22 And he also that had received the two talents came to him and said, My lord, thou deliveredst me two talents; behold, I have gained two other talents besides them. 23 His lord said to him, Well, good and faithful bondman, thou wast faithful over a few things, I will set thee over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord. 24 And he also that had received the one talent coming to him said, My lord, I knew thee that thou art a hard man, reaping where thou hadst not sowed, and gathering from where thou hadst not scattered, 25 and being afraid I went away and hid thy talent in the earth; behold, thou hast that which is thine. 26 And his lord answering said to him, Wicked and slothful bondman, thou knewest that I reap where I had not sowed, and gather from where I had not scattered; 27 thou oughtest then to have put my money to the money-changers, and when I came I should have got what is mine with interest. 28 Take therefore the talent from him, and give it to him that has the ten talents: 29 for to every one that has shall be given, and he shall be in abundance; but from him that has not, that even which he has shall be taken from him. 30 And cast out the useless bondman into the outer darkness; there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth.

31 But when the Son of man comes in his glory, and all the angels with him, then shall he sit down upon his throne of glory, 32 and all the nations shall be gathered before him; and he shall separate them from one another, as the shepherd separates the sheep from the goats; 33 and he will set the sheep on his right hand, and the goats on his left. 34 Then shall the King say to those on his right hand, Come, blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the world's foundation: 35 for I hungered, and ye gave me to eat; I thirsted, and ye gave me to drink; I was a stranger, and ye took me in; 36 naked, and ye clothed me; I was ill, and ye visited me; I was in prison, and ye came to me. 37 Then shall the righteous answer him saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungering, and nourished thee; or thirsting, and gave thee to drink? 38 and when saw we thee a stranger, and took thee in; or naked, and clothed thee? 39 and when saw we thee ill, or in prison, and came to thee? 40 And the King answering shall say to them, Verily, I say to you, Inasmuch as ye have done it to one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it to me. 41 Then shall he say also to those on the left, Go from me, cursed, into eternal fire, prepared for the devil and his angels: 42 for I hungered, and ye gave me not to eat; I thirsted, and ye gave me not to drink; 43 I was a stranger, and ye took me not in; naked, and ye did not clothe me; ill, and in prison, and ye did not visit me. 44 Then shall they also answer saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungering, or thirsting, or a stranger, or naked, or ill, or in prison, and have not ministered to thee? 45 Then shall he answer them saying, Verily I say to you, Inasmuch as ye have not done it to one of these least, neither have ye done it to me. 46 And these shall go away into eternal punishment, and the righteous into life eternal.

Matthew 26

1 And it came to pass when Jesus had finished all these sayings, he said to his disciples, 2 Ye know that after two days the passover takes place, and the Son of man is delivered up to be crucified. 3 Then the chief priests and the elders of the people were gathered together to the palace of the high priest who was called Caiaphas, 4 and took counsel together in order that they might seize Jesus by subtlety and kill him; 5 but they said, Not in the feast, that there be not a tumult among the people.

6 But Jesus being in Bethany, in Simon the leper's house, 7 a woman, having an alabaster flask of very precious ointment, came to him and poured it out upon his head as he lay at table. 8 But the disciples seeing it became indignant, saying, To what end was this waste? 9 for this might have been sold for much and been given to the poor. 10 But Jesus knowing it said to them, Why do ye trouble the woman? for she has wrought a good work toward me. 11 For ye have the poor always with you, but me ye have not always. 12 For in pouring out this ointment on my body, she has done it for my burying. 13 Verily I say to you, Wheresoever these glad tidings may be preached in the whole world, that also which this woman has done shall be spoken of for a memorial of her.

14 Then one of the twelve, he who was called Judas Iscariote, went to the chief priests 15 and said, What are ye willing to give me, and I will deliver him up to you? And they appointed to him thirty pieces of silver. 16 And from that time he sought a good opportunity that he might deliver him up.

17 Now on the first day of the feast of unleavened bread, the disciples came to Jesus, saying, Where wilt thou that we prepare for thee to eat the passover? 18 And he said, Go into the city unto such a one, and say to him, The Teacher says, My time is near, I will keep the passover in thy house with my disciples. 19 And the disciples did as Jesus had directed them, and they prepared the passover. 20 And when the evening was come he lay down at table with the twelve. 21 And as they were eating he said, Verily I say to you, that one of you shall deliver me up. 22 And being exceedingly grieved they began to say to him, each of them, Is it I, Lord? 23 But he answering said, He that dips his hand with me in the dish, he it is who shall deliver me up. 24 The Son of man goes indeed, according as it is written concerning him, but woe to that man by whom the Son of man is delivered up; it were good for that man if he had not been born. 25 And Judas, who delivered him up, answering said, Is it I, Rabbi? He says to him, Thou hast said.

26 And as they were eating, Jesus, having taken the bread and blessed, broke it and gave it to the disciples, and said, Take, eat: this is my body. 27 And having taken the cup and given thanks, he gave it to them, saying, Drink ye all of it. 28 For this is my blood, that of the new covenant, that shed for many for remission of sins. 29 But I say to you, that I will not at all drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine, until that day when I drink it new with you in the kingdom of my Father. 30 And having sung a hymn, they went out to the mount of Olives.

31 Then saith Jesus to them, All ye shall be offended in me during this night. For it is written, I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock shall be scattered abroad. 32 But after that I shall be risen, I will go before you to Galilee. 33 And Peter answering said to him, If all shall be offended in thee, I will never be offended. 34 Jesus said to him, Verily I say to thee, that during this night, before the cock shall crow, thou shalt deny me thrice. 35 Peter says to him, If I should needs die with thee, I will in no wise deny thee. Likewise said all the disciples also.

36 Then Jesus comes with them to a place called Gethsemane, and says to the disciples, Sit here until I go away and pray yonder. 37 And taking with him Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, he began to be sorrowful and deeply depressed. 38 Then he says to them, My soul is very sorrowful even unto death; remain here and watch with me. 39 And going forward a little he fell upon his face, praying and saying, My Father, if it be possible let this cup pass from me; but not as I will, but as thou wilt. 40 And he comes to the disciples and finds them sleeping, and says to Peter, Thus ye have not been able to watch one hour with me? 41 Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation: the spirit indeed is ready, but the flesh weak. 42 Again going away a second time he prayed saying, My Father, if this cannot pass from me unless I drink it, thy will be done. 43 And coming he found them again sleeping, for their eyes were heavy. 44 And leaving them, he went away again and prayed the third time, saying the same thing. 45 Then he comes to the disciples and says to them, Sleep on now and take your rest; behold, the hour has drawn nigh, and the Son of man is delivered up into the hands of sinners. 46 Arise, let us go; behold, he that delivers me up has drawn nigh.

47 And while he was yet speaking, behold, Judas, one of the twelve, came, and with him a great crowd with swords and sticks from the chief priests and elders of the people. 48 Now he that delivered him up had given them a sign, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, he it is: seize him. 49 And immediately coming up to Jesus he said, Hail, Rabbi, and covered him with kisses. 50 But Jesus said to him, My friend, for what purpose art thou come? Then coming up they laid hands upon Jesus and seized him. 51 And behold, one of those with Jesus stretched out his hand and drew his sword, and smiting the bondman of the high priest took off his ear. 52 Then saith Jesus to him, Return thy sword to its place; for all who take the sword shall perish by the sword. 53 Or thinkest thou that I cannot now call upon my Father, and he will furnish me more than twelve legions of angels? 54 How then should the scriptures be fulfilled that thus it must be? 55 In that hour Jesus said to the crowds, Are ye come out as against a robber with swords and sticks to take me? I sat daily with you teaching in the temple, and ye did not seize me. 56 But all this is come to pass that the scriptures of the prophets may be fulfilled. Then all the disciples left him and fled.

57 Now they that had seized Jesus led him away to Caiaphas the high priest, where the scribes and the elders were assembled. 58 And Peter followed him at a distance, even to the palace of the high priest, and entering in sat with the officers to see the end. 59 And the chief priests and the elders and the whole sanhedrim sought false witness against Jesus, so that they might put him to death. 60 And they found none, though many false witnesses came forward. But at the last two false witnesses came forward 61 and said, He said, I am able to destroy the temple of God, and in three days build it. 62 And the high priest standing up said to him, Answerest thou nothing? What do these witness against thee? 63 But Jesus was silent. And the high priest answering said to him, I adjure thee by the living God that thou tell us if thou art the Christ the Son of God. 64 Jesus says to him, Thou hast said. Moreover, I say to you, From henceforth ye shall see the Son of man sitting at the right hand of power, and coming on the clouds of heaven. 65 Then the high priest rent his clothes, saying, He has blasphemed: what need have we any more of witnesses? behold, now ye have heard the blasphemy. 66 What think ye? And they answering said, He is liable to the penalty of death. 67 Then they spit in his face, and buffeted him, and some struck him with the palms of their hand, 68 saying, Prophesy to us, Christ, Who is it who struck thee?

69 But Peter sat without in the palace-court; and a maid came to him, saying, And thou wast with Jesus the Galilaean. 70 But he denied before all, saying, I do not know what thou sayest. 71 And when he had gone out into the entrance, another maid saw him, and says to those there, This man also was with Jesus the Nazaraean. 72 And again he denied with an oath: I do not know the man. 73 And after a little, those who stood there, coming to him, said to Peter, Truly thou too art of them, for also thy speech makes thee manifest. 74 Then he began to curse and to swear, I know not the man. And immediately the cock crew. 75 And Peter remembered the word of Jesus, who had said to him, Before the cock crow thou shalt deny me thrice. And he went forth without, and wept bitterly.

Matthew 27

1 And when it was morning all the chief priests and the elders of the people took counsel against Jesus so that they might put him to death. 2 And having bound him they led him away, and delivered him up to Pontius Pilate, the governor. 3 Then Judas, who delivered him up, seeing that he had been condemned, filled with remorse, returned the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and the elders, 4 saying, I have sinned in having delivered up guiltless blood. But they said, What is that to us? see thou to that. 5 And having cast down the pieces of silver in the temple, he left the place, and went away and hanged himself. 6 And the chief priests took the pieces of silver and said, It is not lawful to cast them into the Corban, since it is the price of blood. 7 And having taken counsel, they bought with them the field of the potter for a burying-ground for strangers. 8 Wherefore that field has been called Blood-field unto this day. 9 Then was fulfilled that which was spoken through Jeremias the prophet, saying, And I took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of him that was set a price on, whom they who were of the sons of Israel had set a price on, 10 and they gave them for the field of the potter, according as the Lord commanded me.

11 But Jesus stood before the governor. And the governor questioned him, saying, Art thou the King of the Jews? And Jesus said to him, Thou sayest. 12 And when he was accused of the chief priests and the elders, he answered nothing. 13 Then says Pilate to him, Hearest thou not how many things they witness against thee? 14 And he answered him not so much as one word, so that the governor wondered exceedingly. 15 Now at the feast the governor was accustomed to release one prisoner to the crowd, whom they would. 16 And they had then a notable prisoner, named Barabbas. 17 They therefore being gathered together, Pilate said to them, Whom will ye that I release to you, Barabbas, or Jesus who is called Christ? 18 For he knew that they had delivered him up through envy. 19 But, as he was sitting on the judgment-seat, his wife sent to him, saying, Have thou nothing to do with that righteous man; for I have suffered to-day many things in a dream because of him. 20 But the chief priests and the elders persuaded the crowds that they should beg for Barabbas, and destroy Jesus. 21 And the governor answering said to them, Which of the two will ye that I release unto you? And they said, Barabbas. 22 Pilate says to them, What then shall I do with Jesus, who is called Christ? They all say, Let him be crucified. 23 And the governor said, What evil then has he done? But they cried more than ever, saying, Let him be crucified. 24 And Pilate, seeing that it availed nothing, but that rather a tumult was arising, having taken water, washed his hands before the crowd, saying, I am guiltless of the blood of this righteous one: see ye to it. 25 And all the people answering said, His blood be on us and on our children.

26 Then he released to them Barabbas; but Jesus, having scourged him, he delivered up that he might be crucified. 27 Then the soldiers of the governor, having taken Jesus with them to the praetorium, gathered against him the whole band, 28 and having taken off his garment, put on him a scarlet cloak; 29 and having woven a crown out of thorns, they put it on his head, and a reed in his right hand; and, bowing the knee before him, they mocked him, saying, Hail, King of the Jews! 30 And having spit upon him, they took the reed and beat him on his head. 31 And when they had mocked him, they took the cloak off him, and put his own clothes on him, and led him away to crucify. 32 And as they went forth they found a man of Cyrene, Simon by name; him they compelled to go with them that he might bear his cross.

33 And having come to a place called Golgotha, which means Place of a skull, 34 they gave to him to drink vinegar mingled with gall; and having tasted it, he would not drink. 35 And having crucified him, they parted his clothes amongst themselves, casting lots. 36 And sitting down, they kept guard over him there. 37 And they set up over his head his accusation written: This is Jesus, the King of the Jews. 38 Then are crucified with him two robbers, one on the right hand and one on the left. 39 But the passers-by reviled him, shaking their heads 40 and saying, Thou that destroyest the temple and buildest it in three days, save thyself. If thou art Son of God, descend from the cross. 41 And in like manner the chief priests also, mocking, with the scribes and elders, said, 42 He saved others, himself he cannot save. He is King of Israel: let him descend now from the cross, and we will believe on him. 43 He trusted upon God; let him save him now if he will have him. For he said, I am Son of God. 44 And the robbers also who had been crucified with him cast the same reproaches on him. 45 Now from the sixth hour there was darkness over the whole land until the ninth hour; 46 but about the ninth hour Jesus cried out with a loud voice, saying, Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani? that is, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? 47 And some of those who stood there, when they heard it, said, This man calls for Elias. 48 And immediately one of them running and getting a sponge, having filled it with vinegar and fixed it on a reed, gave him to drink. 49 But the rest said, Let be; let us see if Elias comes to save him.

50 And Jesus, having again cried with a loud voice, gave up the ghost. 51 And lo, the veil of the temple was rent in two from the top to the bottom, and the earth was shaken, and the rocks were rent, 52 and the tombs were opened; and many bodies of the saints fallen asleep arose, 53 and going out of the tombs after his arising, entered into the holy city and appeared unto many. 54 But the centurion, and they who were with him on guard over Jesus, seeing the earthquake and the things that took place, feared greatly, saying, Truly this man was Son of God. 55 And there were there many women beholding from afar off, who had followed Jesus from Galilee ministering to him, 56 among whom was Mary of Magdala, and Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of the sons of Zebedee.

57 Now when even was come there came a rich man of Arimathaea, his name Joseph, who also himself was a disciple to Jesus. 58 He, going to Pilate, begged the body of Jesus. Then Pilate commanded the body to be given up. 59 And Joseph having got the body, wrapped it in a clean linen cloth, 60 and laid it in his new tomb which he had hewn in the rock; and having rolled a great stone to the door of the tomb, went away. 61 But Mary of Magdala was there, and the other Mary, sitting opposite the sepulchre. 62 Now on the morrow, which is after the preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees came together to Pilate, 63 saying, Sir, we have called to mind that that deceiver said when he was still alive, After three days I arise. 64 Command therefore that the sepulchre be secured until the third day, lest his disciples should come and steal him away, and say to the people, He is risen from the dead; and the last error shall be worse than the first. 65 And Pilate said to them, Ye have a watch: go, secure it as well as ye know how. 66 And they went and secured the sepulchre, having sealed the stone, with the watch besides.

Matthew 28

1 Now late on sabbath, as it was the dusk of the next day after sabbath, came Mary of Magdala and the other Mary to look at the sepulchre. 2 And behold, there was a great earthquake; for an angel of the Lord, descending out of heaven, came and rolled away the stone and sat upon it. 3 And his look was as lightning, and his clothing white as snow. 4 And for fear of him the guards trembled and became as dead men. 5 And the angel answering said to the women, Fear not ye, for I know that ye seek Jesus the crucified one. 6 He is not here, for he is risen, as he said. Come, see the place where the Lord lay. 7 And go quickly and say to his disciples that he is risen from the dead; and behold, he goes before you into Galilee, there shall ye see him. Behold, I have told you. 8 And going out quickly from the tomb with fear and great joy, they ran to bring his disciples word. 9 And as they went to bring his disciples word, behold also, Jesus met them, saying, Hail! And they coming up took him by the feet, and did him homage. 10 Then Jesus says to them, Fear not; go, bring word to my brethren that they go into Galilee, and there they shall see me.

11 And as they went, behold, some of the watch went into the city, and brought word to the chief priests of all that had taken place. 12 And having assembled with the elders, and having taken counsel, they gave a large sum of money to the soldiers, 13 saying, Say that his disciples coming by night stole him while we were sleeping. 14 And if this should come to the hearing of the governor, we will persuade him, and save you from all anxiety. 15 And they took the money and did as they had been taught. And this report is current among the Jews until this day.

16 But the eleven disciples went into Galilee to the mountain which Jesus had appointed them. 17 And when they saw him, they did homage to him: but some doubted. 18 And Jesus coming up spoke to them, saying, All power has been given me in heaven and upon earth. 19 Go therefore and make disciples of all the nations, baptising them to the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit; 20 teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have enjoined you. And behold, I am with you all the days, until the completion of the age.

Mark 1

1 Beginning of the glad tidings of Jesus Christ, Son of God; 2 as it is written in Isaiah the prophet, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face, who shall prepare thy way. 3 Voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare the way of the Lord, make his paths straight. 4 There came John baptising in the wilderness, and preaching the baptism of repentance for remission of sins. 5 And there went out to him all the district of Judaea, and all they of Jerusalem, and were baptised by him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins. 6 And John was clothed in camel's hair, and a leathern girdle about his loins, and ate locusts and wild honey. 7 And he preached, saying, There comes he that is mightier than I after me, the thong of whose sandals I am not fit to stoop down and unloose. 8 I indeed have baptised you with water, but he shall baptise you with the Holy Spirit.

9 And it came to pass in those days that Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and was baptised by John at the Jordan. 10 And straightway going up from the water, he saw the heavens parting asunder, and the Spirit, as a dove, descending upon him. 11 And there came a voice out of the heavens: Thou art my beloved Son, in thee I have found my delight. 12 And immediately the Spirit drives him out into the wilderness. 13 And he was in the wilderness forty days tempted by Satan, and was with the wild beasts; and the angels ministered to him.

14 But after John was delivered up, Jesus came into Galilee preaching the glad tidings of the kingdom of God, 15 and saying, The time is fulfilled and the kingdom of God has drawn nigh; repent and believe in the glad tidings. 16 And walking by the sea of Galilee, he saw Simon, and Andrew, Simon's brother, casting out a net in the sea, for they were fishers. 17 And Jesus said to them, Come after me, and I will make you become fishers of men; 18 and straightway leaving their trawl-nets they followed him. 19 And going on thence a little, he saw James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, and these were in the ship repairing the trawl-nets; 20 and straightway he called them; and leaving their father Zebedee in the ship with the hired servants, they went away after him. 21 And they go into Capernaum. And straightway on the sabbath he entered into the synagogue and taught. 22 And they were astonished at his doctrine, for he taught them as having authority, and not as the scribes.

23 And there was in their synagogue a man possessed by an unclean spirit, and he cried out 24 saying, Eh! what have we to do with thee, Jesus, Nazarene? Art thou come to destroy us? I know thee who thou art, the holy one of God. 25 And Jesus rebuked him, saying, Hold thy peace and come out of him. 26 And the unclean spirit, having torn him, and uttered a cry with a loud voice, came out of him. 27 And all were amazed, so that they questioned together among themselves, saying, What is this? what new doctrine is this? for with authority he commands even the unclean spirits, and they obey him. 28 And his fame went out straightway into the whole region of Galilee around.

29 And straightway going out of the synagogue, they came with James and John into the house of Simon and Andrew. 30 And the mother-in-law of Simon lay in a fever. And straightway they speak to him about her. 31 And he went up to her and raised her up, having taken her by the hand, and straightway the fever left her, and she served them. 32 But evening being come, when the sun had gone down, they brought to him all that were suffering, and those possessed by demons; 33 and the whole city was gathered together at the door. 34 And he healed many suffering from various diseases; and he cast out many demons, and did not suffer the demons to speak because they knew him. 35 And rising in the morning long before day, he went out and went away into a desert place, and there prayed. 36 And Simon and those with him went after him: 37 and having found him, they say to him, All seek thee. 38 And he says to them, Let us go elsewhere into the neighbouring country towns, that I may preach there also, for for this purpose am I come forth. 39 And he was preaching in their synagogues in the whole of Galilee, and casting out demons.

40 And there comes to him a leper, beseeching him, and falling on his knees to him, and saying to him, If thou wilt thou canst cleanse me. 41 But Jesus, moved with compassion, having stretched out his hand, touched him, and says to him, I will, be thou cleansed. 42 And as he spoke straightway the leprosy left him, and he was cleansed. 43 And having sharply charged him, he straightway sent him away, 44 and says to him, See thou say nothing to any one, but go, shew thyself to the priest, and offer for thy cleansing what Moses ordained, for a testimony to them. 45 But he, having gone forth, began to proclaim it much, and to spread the matter abroad, so that he could no longer enter openly into the city, but was without in desert places, and they came to him from every side.

Mark 2

1 And he entered again into Capernaum after several days, and it was reported that he was at the house; 2 and straightway many were gathered together, so that there was no longer any room, not even at the door; and he spoke the word to them. 3 And there come to him men bringing a paralytic, borne by four; 4 and, not being able to get near to him on account of the crowd, they uncovered the roof where he was, and having dug it up they let down the couch on which the paralytic lay. 5 But Jesus, seeing their faith, says to the paralytic, Child, thy sins are forgiven thee. 6 But certain of the scribes were there sitting, and reasoning in their hearts, 7 Why does this man thus speak? he blasphemes. Who is able to forgive sins except God alone? 8 And straightway Jesus, knowing in his spirit that they are reasoning thus within themselves, said to them, Why reason ye these things in your hearts? 9 Which is easier, to say to the paralytic, Thy sins are forgiven thee; or to say, Arise, and take up thy couch and walk? 10 But that ye may know that the Son of man has power on earth to forgive sins, he says to the paralytic, 11 To thee I say, Arise, take up thy couch and go to thine house. 12 And he rose up straightway, and, having taken up his couch, went out before them all, so that all were amazed, and glorified God, saying, We never saw it thus.

13 And he went out again by the sea, and all the crowd came to him, and he taught them. 14 And passing by, he saw Levi the son of Alphaeus sitting at the tax-office, and says to him, Follow me. And he rose up and followed him. 15 And it came to pass as he lay at table in his house, that many tax-gatherers and sinners lay at table with Jesus and his disciples; for they were many, and they followed him. 16 And the scribes and the Pharisees, seeing him eating with sinners and tax-gatherers, said to his disciples, Why is it that he eats and drinks with tax-gatherers and sinners? 17 And Jesus having heard it says to them, They that are strong have not need of a physician, but those who are ill. I have not come to call righteous men, but sinners.

18 And the disciples of John and the Pharisees were fasting; and they come and say to him, Why do the disciples of John and the disciples of the Pharisees fast, but thy disciples fast not? 19 And Jesus said to them, Can the sons of the bride-chamber fast while the bridegroom is with them? As long as they have the bridegroom with them they cannot fast. 20 But days will come when the bridegroom shall have been taken away from them, and then shall they fast in that day. 21 No one sews a patch of new cloth on an old garment: otherwise its new filling-up takes from the old stuff, and there is a worse rent. 22 And no one puts new wine into old skins; otherwise the wine bursts the skins, and the wine is poured out, and the skins will be destroyed; but new wine is to be put into new skins. 23 And it came to pass that he went on the sabbath through the cornfields; and his disciples began to walk on, plucking the ears. 24 And the Pharisees said to him, Behold, why do they on the sabbath what is not lawful? 25 And he said to them, Have ye never read what David did when he had need and hungered, he and those with him, 26 how he entered into the house of God, in the section of Abiathar the high priest, and ate the shew-bread, which it is not lawful unless for the priests to eat, and gave even to those that were with him? 27 And he said to them, The sabbath was made on account of man, not man on account of the sabbath; 28 so that the Son of man is lord of the sabbath also.

Mark 3

1 And he entered again into the synagogue; and there was there a man having his hand dried up. 2 And they watched him if he would heal him on the sabbath, that they might accuse him. 3 And he says to the man who had his hand dried up, Rise up and come into the midst. 4 And he says to them, Is it lawful on the sabbath to do good or to do evil, to save life or to kill? But they were silent. 5 And looking round upon them with anger, distressed at the hardening of their heart, he says to the man, Stretch out thy hand. And he stretched it out, and his hand was restored. 6 And the Pharisees going out straightway with the Herodians took counsel against him, how they might destroy him. 7 And Jesus withdrew with his disciples to the sea; and a great multitude from Galilee followed him, and from Judaea, 8 and from Jerusalem, and from Idumaea and beyond the Jordan; and they of around Tyre and Sidon, a great multitude, having heard what things he did, came to him. 9 And he spoke to his disciples, in order that a little ship should wait upon him on account of the crowd, that they might not press upon him. 10 For he healed many, so that they beset him that they might touch him, as many as had plagues. 11 And the unclean spirits, when they beheld him, fell down before him, and cried saying, Thou art the Son of God. 12 And he rebuked them much, that they might not make him manifest.

13 And he goes up into the mountain, and calls whom he himself would, and they went to him. 14 And he appointed twelve that they might be with him, and that he might send them to preach, 15 and to have power to heal diseases, and to cast out demons. 16 And he gave to Simon the surname of Peter; 17 and James the son of Zebedee, and John the brother of James, and he gave them the surname of Boanerges, that is, Sons of thunder; 18 and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James the son of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus, and Simon the Cananaean, 19 and Judas Iscariote, who also delivered him up. And they come to the house. 20 And again a crowd comes together, so that they cannot even eat bread. 21 And his relatives having heard of it went out to lay hold on him, for they said, He is out of his mind.

22 And the scribes who had come down from Jerusalem said, He has Beelzebub, and, By the prince of the demons he casts out demons. 23 And having called them to him, he said to them in parables, How can Satan cast out Satan? 24 And if a kingdom has become divided against itself, that kingdom cannot subsist. 25 And if a house has become divided against itself, that house cannot subsist. 26 And if Satan rise up against himself, and is divided, he cannot subsist, but has an end. 27 But no one can, having entered into his house, plunder the goods of the strong man unless he first bind the strong man, and then he will plunder his house. 28 Verily I say unto you, that all sins shall be forgiven to the sons of men, and all the injurious speeches with which they may speak injuriously; 29 but whosoever shall speak injuriously against the Holy Spirit, to eternity has no forgiveness; but lies under the guilt of an everlasting sin; 30 --because they said, He has an unclean spirit.

31 And his brethren and his mother come, and standing without sent to him calling him. 32 And a crowd sat around him. And they said to him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren seek thee without. 33 And he answered them, saying, Who is my mother or my brethren? 34 And looking around in a circuit at those that were sitting around him, he says, Behold my mother and my brethren: 35 for whosoever shall do the will of God, he is my brother, and sister, and mother.

Mark 4

1 And again he began to teach by the sea. And a great crowd was gathered together to him, so that going on board ship he sat in the sea, and all the crowd were close to the sea on the land. 2 And he taught them many things in parables. And he said to them in his doctrine, 3 Hearken: Behold, the sower went forth to sow. 4 And it came to pass as he sowed, one fell by the wayside, and the birds came and devoured it. 5 And another fell on the rocky ground, where it had not much earth, and immediately it sprung up out of the ground because it had no depth of earth; 6 and when the sun arose it was burnt up, and because of its not having any root, it withered. 7 And another fell among the thorns, and the thorns grew up and choked it, and it yielded no fruit. 8 And another fell into the good ground, and yielded fruit, growing up and increasing; and bore, one thirty, and one sixty, and one a hundred. 9 And he said, He that has ears to hear, let him hear. 10 And when he was alone, those about him with the twelve asked him as to the parables. 11 And he said to them, To you is given to know the mystery of the kingdom of God; but to them who are without, all things are done in parables, 12 that beholding they may behold and not see, and hearing they may hear and not understand, lest it may be, they should be converted and they should be forgiven. 13 And he says to them, Do ye not know this parable? and how will ye be acquainted with all the parables? 14 The sower sows the word: 15 and these are they by the wayside where the word is sown, and when they hear, immediately Satan comes and takes away the word that was sown in them. 16 And these are they in like manner who are sown upon the rocky places, who when they hear the word, immediately receive it with joy, 17 and they have no root in themselves, but are for a time: then, tribulation arising, or persecution on account of the word, immediately they are offended. 18 And others are they who are sown among the thorns: these are they who have heard the word, 19 and the cares of life, and the deceitfulness of riches, and the lusts of other things, entering in, choke the word, and it becomes unfruitful. 20 And these are they who have been sown on the good ground, such as hear the word and receive it, and bear fruit; one thirty, and one sixty, and one a hundred fold.

21 And he said to them, Does the lamp come that it should be put under the bushel or under the couch? Is it not that it should be set upon the lamp-stand? 22 For there is nothing hidden which shall not be made manifest; nor does any secret thing take place, but that it should come to light. 23 If any one have ears to hear, let him hear. 24 And he said to them, Take heed what ye hear; with what measure ye mete, it shall be meted to you; and there shall be more added to you. 25 For whosoever has, to him shall be given; and he who has not, even what he has shall be taken from him. 26 And he said, Thus is the kingdom of God, as if a man should cast the seed upon the earth, 27 and should sleep and rise up night and day, and the seed should sprout and grow, he does not know how. 28 The earth bears fruit of itself, first the blade, then an ear, then full corn in the ear. 29 But when the fruit is produced, immediately he sends the sickle, for the harvest is come. 30 And he said, How should we liken the kingdom of God, or with what comparison should we compare it? 31 As to a grain of mustard seed, which, when it is sown upon the earth, is less than all seeds which are upon the earth, 32 and when it has been sown, mounts up and becomes greater than all herbs, and produces great branches, so that the birds of heaven can roost under its shadow. 33 And with many such parables he spoke the word to them, as they were able to hear, 34 but without a parable spoke he not to them; and in private he explained all things to his disciples.

35 And on that day, when evening was come, he says to them, Let us go over to the other side: 36 and having sent away the crowd, they take him with them, as he was, in the ship. But other ships also were with him. 37 And there comes a violent gust of wind, and the waves beat into the ship, so that it already filled. 38 And he was in the stern sleeping on the cushion. And they awake him up and say to him, Teacher, dost thou not care that we are perishing? 39 And awaking up he rebuked the wind, and said to the sea, Silence; be mute. And the wind fell, and there was a great calm. 40 And he said to them, Why are ye thus fearful? how is it ye have not faith? 41 And they feared with great fear, and said one to another, Who then is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?

Mark 5

1 And they came to the other side of the sea, to the country of the Gadarenes. 2 And immediately on his going out of the ship there met him out of the tombs a man possessed by an unclean spirit, 3 who had his dwelling in the tombs; and no one was able to bind him, not even with chains; 4 because he had been often bound with fetters and chains, and the chains had been torn asunder by him, and the fetters were shattered; and no one was able to subdue him. 5 And continually night and day, in the tombs and in the mountains, he was crying and cutting himself with stones. 6 But seeing Jesus from afar off, he ran and did him homage, 7 and crying with a loud voice he says, What have I to do with thee, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I adjure thee by God, torment me not. 8 For he said to him, Come forth, unclean spirit, out of the man. 9 And he asked him, What is thy name? And he says to him, Legion is my name, because we are many. 10 And he besought him much that he would not send them away out of the country. 11 Now there was there just at the mountain a great herd of swine feeding; 12 and they besought him, saying, Send us into the swine that we may enter into them. 13 And Jesus immediately allowed them. And the unclean spirits going out entered into the swine, and the herd rushed down the steep slope, into the sea (about two thousand), and were choked in the sea. 14 And those that were feeding them fled and reported it in the city and in the country. And they went out to see what it was that had taken place. 15 And they come to Jesus, and they see the possessed of demons sitting and clothed and sensible, him that had had the legion: and they were afraid. 16 And they that had seen it related to them how it had happened to the man possessed by demons, and concerning the swine. 17 And they began to beg him to depart from their coasts. 18 And as he went on board ship, the man that had been possessed by demons besought him that he might be with him. 19 And he suffered him not, but says to him, Go to thine home to thine own people, and tell them how great things the Lord has done for thee, and has had mercy on thee. 20 And he went away and began to proclaim in the Decapolis how great things Jesus had done for him; and all wondered.

21 And Jesus having passed over in the ship again to the other side, a great crowd gathered to him; and he was by the sea. 22 And behold there comes one of the rulers of the synagogue, by name Jairus, and seeing him, falls down at his feet; 23 and he besought him much, saying, My little daughter is at extremity; I pray that thou shouldest come and lay thy hands upon her so that she may be healed, and may live. 24 And he went with him, and a large crowd followed him and pressed on him. 25 And a certain woman who had had a flux of blood twelve years, 26 and had suffered much under many physicians, and had spent everything she had and had found no advantage from it, but had rather got worse, 27 having heard concerning Jesus, came in the crowd behind and touched his clothes; 28 for she said, If I shall touch but his clothes I shall be healed. 29 And immediately her fountain of blood was dried up, and she knew in her body that she was cured from the scourge. 30 And immediately Jesus, knowing in himself the power that had gone out of him, turning round in the crowd said, Who has touched my clothes? 31 And his disciples said to him, Thou seest the crowd pressing on thee, and sayest thou, Who touched me? 32 And he looked round about to see her who had done this. 33 But the woman, frightened and trembling, knowing what had taken place in her, came and fell down before him, and told him all the truth. 34 And he said to her, Daughter, thy faith has healed thee; go in peace, and be well of thy scourge.

35 While he was yet speaking, they come from the ruler of the synagogue's house, saying, Thy daughter has died, why troublest thou the teacher any further? 36 But Jesus immediately, having heard the word spoken, says to the ruler of the synagogue, Fear not; only believe. 37 And he suffered no one to accompany him save Peter and James, and John the brother of James. 38 And he comes to the house of the ruler of the synagogue, and sees the tumult, and people weeping and wailing greatly. 39 And entering in he says to them, Why do ye make a tumult and weep? the child has not died, but sleeps. 40 And they derided him. But he, having put them all out, takes with him the father of the child, and the mother, and those that were with him, and enters in where the child was lying. 41 And having laid hold of the hand of the child, he says to her, Talitha koumi, which is, interpreted, Damsel, I say to thee, Arise. 42 And immediately the damsel arose and walked, for she was twelve years old. And they were astonished with great astonishment. 43 And he charged them much that no one should know this; and he desired that something should be given her to eat.

Mark 6

1 And he went out thence and came to his own country, and his disciples follow him. 2 And when sabbath was come he began to teach in the synagogue, and many hearing were amazed, saying, Whence has this man these things? and what is the wisdom that is given to him, and such works of power are done by his hands? 3 Is not this the carpenter, the son of Mary, and brother of James, and Joses, and Judas, and Simon? and are not his sisters here with us? And they were offended in him. 4 But Jesus said to them, A prophet is not despised save in his own country, and among his kinsmen, and in his own house. 5 And he could not do any work of power there, save that laying his hands on a few infirm persons he healed them. 6 And he wondered because of their unbelief. And he went round the villages in a circuit, teaching.

7 And he calls the twelve to him; and he began to send them out two and two, and gave to them power over the unclean spirits; 8 and he commanded them that they should take nothing for the way, save a staff only; no scrip, no bread, no money in their belt; 9 but be shod with sandals, and put not on two body-coats. 10 And he said to them, Wheresoever ye shall enter into a house, there remain till ye shall go thence. 11 And whatsoever place shall not receive you nor hear you, departing thence, shake off the dust which is under your feet for a testimony to them. 12 And they went forth and preached that they should repent; 13 and they cast out many demons, and anointed with oil many infirm, and healed them.

14 And Herod the king heard of him (for his name had become public), and said, John the baptist is risen from among the dead, and on this account works of power are wrought by him. 15 And others said, It is Elias; and others said, It is a prophet, as one of the prophets. 16 But Herod when he heard it said, John whom I beheaded, he it is; he is risen from among the dead. 17 For the same Herod had sent and seized John, and had bound him in prison on account of Herodias, the wife of Philip his brother, because he had married her. 18 For John said to Herod, It is not lawful for thee to have the wife of thy brother. 19 But Herodias kept it in her mind against him, and wished to kill him, and could not: 20 for Herod feared John knowing that he was a just and holy man, and kept him safe; and having heard him, did many things, and heard him gladly. 21 And a holiday being come, when Herod, on his birthday, made a supper to his grandees, and to the chiliarchs, and the chief men of Galilee; 22 and the daughter of the same Herodias having come in, and danced, pleased Herod and those that were with him at table; and the king said to the damsel, Ask of me whatsoever thou wilt and I will give it thee. 23 And he swore to her, Whatsoever thou shalt ask me I will give thee, to half of my kingdom. 24 And she went out, and said to her mother, What should I ask? And she said, The head of John the baptist. 25 And immediately going in with haste to the king, she asked saying, I desire that thou give me directly upon a dish the head of John the baptist. 26 And the king, while made very sorry, on account of the oaths and those lying at table with him would not break his word with her. 27 And immediately the king, having sent one of the guard, ordered his head to be brought. And he went out and beheaded him in the prison, 28 and brought his head upon a dish, and gave it to the damsel, and the damsel gave it to her mother. 29 And his disciples having heard it, came and took up his body, and laid it in a tomb.

30 And the apostles are gathered together to Jesus. And they related to him all things, both what they had done and what they had taught. 31 And he said to them, Come ye yourselves apart into a desert place and rest a little. For those coming and those going were many, and they had not leisure even to eat. 32 And they went away apart into a desert place by ship. 33 And many saw them going, and recognised them, and ran together there on foot, out of all the cities, and got there before them. 34 And on leaving the ship Jesus saw a great crowd, and he was moved with compassion for them, because they were as sheep not having a shepherd. And he began to teach them many things. 35 And when it was already late in the day, his disciples coming to him say, The place is desert, and it is already late in the day; 36 send them away that they may go into the country and villages around, and buy themselves bread, for they have not anything they can eat. 37 And he answering said to them, Give ye them to eat. And they say to him, Shall we go and buy two hundred denarii worth of bread and give them to eat? 38 And he says to them, How many loaves have ye? Go and see. And when they knew they say, Five, and two fishes. 39 And he ordered them to make them all sit down by companies on the green grass. 40 And they sat down in ranks by hundreds and by fifties. 41 And having taken the five loaves and the two fishes, looking up to heaven, he blessed, and broke the loaves, and gave them to his disciples that they might set them before them. And the two fishes he divided among all. 42 And they all ate and were satisfied. 43 And they took up of fragments the fillings of twelve hand-baskets, and of the fishes. 44 And those that ate of the loaves were five thousand men.

45 And immediately he compelled his disciples to go on board ship, and to go on before to the other side to Bethsaida, while he sends the crowd away. 46 And, having dismissed them, he departed into the mountain to pray. 47 And when evening was come, the ship was in the midst of the sea, and he alone upon the land. 48 And seeing them labouring in rowing, for the wind was contrary to them, about the fourth watch of the night he comes to them walking on the sea, and would have passed them by. 49 But they, seeing him walking on the sea, thought that it was an apparition, and cried out. 50 For all saw him and were troubled. And immediately he spoke with them, and says to them, Be of good courage: it is I; be not afraid. 51 And he went up to them into the ship, and the wind fell. And they were exceedingly beyond measure astonished in themselves and wondered; 52 for they understood not through the loaves: for their heart was hardened. 53 And having passed over, they came to the land of Gennesaret and made the shore. 54 And on their coming out of the ship, immediately recognising him, 55 they ran through that whole country around, and began to carry about those that were ill on couches, where they heard that he was. 56 And wherever he entered into villages, or cities, or the country, they laid the sick in the market-places, and besought him that they might touch if it were only the hem of his garment; and as many as touched him were healed.

Mark 7

1 And the Pharisees and some of the scribes, coming from Jerusalem, are gathered together to him, 2 and seeing some of his disciples eat bread with defiled, that is, unwashed, hands, 3 (for the Pharisees and all the Jews, unless they wash their hands diligently, do not eat, holding what has been delivered by the ancients; 4 and on coming from the market-place, unless they are washed, they do not eat; and there are many other things which they have received to hold, the washing of cups and vessels, and brazen utensils, and couches), 5 then the Pharisees and the scribes ask him, Why do thy disciples not walk according to what has been delivered by the ancients, but eat the bread with defiled hands? 6 But he answering said to them, Well did Esaias prophesy concerning you hypocrites, as it is written, This people honour me with their lips, but their heart is far away from me. 7 But in vain do they worship me, teaching as their teachings commandments of men. 8 For, leaving the commandment of God, ye hold what is delivered by men to keep--washings of vessels and cups, and many other such like things ye do. 9 And he said to them, Well do ye set aside the commandment of God, that ye may observe what is delivered by yourselves to keep. 10 For Moses said, Honour thy father and thy mother; and, he who speaks ill of father or mother, let him surely die. 11 But ye say, If a man say to his father or his mother, It is corban (that is, gift), whatsoever thou mightest have profit from me by... 12 And ye no longer suffer him to do anything for his father or his mother; 13 making void the word of God by your traditional teaching which ye have delivered; and many such like things ye do. 14 And having called again the crowd, he said to them, Hear me, all of you, and understand: 15 There is nothing from outside a man entering into him which can defile him; but the things which go out from him, those it is which defile the man. 16 If any one have ears to hear, let him hear. 17 And when he went indoors from the crowd, his disciples asked him concerning the parable. 18 And he says to them, Are ye also thus unintelligent? Do ye not perceive that all that is outside entering into the man cannot defile him, 19 because it does not enter into his heart but into his belly, and goes out into the draught, purging all meats? 20 And he said, That which goes forth out of the man, that defiles the man. 21 For from within, out of the heart of men, go forth evil thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murders, 22 thefts, covetousness, wickednesses, deceit, licentiousness, a wicked eye, injurious language, haughtiness, folly; 23 all these wicked things go forth from within and defile the man.

24 And he rose up and went away thence into the borders of Tyre and Sidon; and having entered into a house he would not have any one know it, and he could not be hid. 25 But immediately a woman, whose little daughter had an unclean spirit, having heard of him, came and fell at his feet 26 (and the woman was a Greek, Syrophenician by race), and asked him that he would cast the demon out of her daughter. 27 But Jesus said to her, Suffer the children to be first filled; for it is not right to take the children's bread and cast it to the dogs. 28 But she answered and says to him, Yea, Lord; for even the dogs under the table eat of the children's crumbs. 29 And he said to her, Because of this word, go thy way, the demon is gone out of thy daughter. 30 And having gone away to her house she found the demon gone out, and her daughter lying on the bed.

31 And again having left the borders of Tyre and Sidon, he came to the sea of Galilee, through the midst of the coasts of Decapolis. 32 And they bring to him a deaf man who could not speak right, and they beseech him that he might lay his hand on him. 33 And having taken him away from the crowd apart, he put his fingers to his ears; and having spit, he touched his tongue; 34 and looking up to heaven he groaned, and says to him, Ephphatha, that is, Be opened. 35 And immediately his ears were opened, and the band of his tongue was loosed and he spoke right. 36 And he charged them that they should speak to no one of it. But so much the more he charged them, so much the more abundantly they proclaimed it; 37 and they were astonished above measure, saying, He does all things well; he makes both the deaf to hear, and the speechless to speak.

Mark 8

1 In those days, there being again a great crowd, and they having nothing that they could eat, having called his disciples to him, he says to them, 2 I have compassion on the crowd, because they have stayed with me already three days and they have not anything they can eat, 3 and if I should dismiss them to their home fasting, they will faint on the way; for some of them are come from far. 4 And his disciples answered him, Whence shall one be able to satisfy these with bread here in a desert place? 5 And he asked them, How many loaves have ye? And they said, Seven. 6 And he commanded the crowd to sit down on the ground. And having taken the seven loaves, he gave thanks, and broke them and gave them to his disciples, that they might set them before them; and they set them before the crowd. 7 And they had a few small fishes, and having blessed them, he desired these also to be set before them. 8 And they ate and were satisfied. And they took up of fragments that remained seven baskets. 9 And they that had eaten were about four thousand; and he sent them away.

10 And immediately going on board ship with his disciples, he came into the parts of Dalmanutha. 11 And the Pharisees went out and began to dispute against him, seeking from him a sign from heaven, tempting him. 12 And groaning in his spirit, he says, Why does this generation seek a sign? Verily I say unto you, A sign shall in no wise be given to this generation. 13 And he left them, and going again on board ship, went away to the other side. 14 And they forgot to take bread, and save one loaf, they had not any with them in the ship. 15 And he charged them, saying, Take heed, beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the leaven of Herod. 16 And they reasoned with one another, saying, It is because we have no bread. 17 And Jesus knowing it, says to them, Why reason ye because ye have no bread? Do ye not yet perceive nor understand? Have ye your heart yet hardened? 18 Having eyes, see ye not? and having ears, hear ye not? and do ye not remember? 19 When I broke the five loaves for the five thousand, how many hand-baskets full of fragments took ye up? They say to him, Twelve. 20 And when the seven for the four thousand, the filling of how many baskets of fragments took ye up? And they said, Seven. 21 And he said to them, How do ye not yet understand?

22 And he comes to Bethsaida; and they bring him a blind man, and beseech him that he might touch him. 23 And taking hold of the hand of the blind man he led him forth out of the village, and having spit upon his eyes, he laid his hands upon him, and asked him if he beheld anything. 24 And having looked up, he said, I behold men, for I see them, as trees, walking. 25 Then he laid his hands again upon his eyes, and he saw distinctly, and was restored and saw all things clearly. 26 And he sent him to his house, saying, Neither enter into the village, nor tell it to any one in the village.

27 And Jesus went forth and his disciples, into the villages of Caesarea-Philippi. And by the way he asked his disciples, saying unto them, Who do men say that I am? 28 And they answered him, saying, John the baptist; and others, Elias; but others, One of the prophets. 29 And he asked them, But ye, who do ye say that I am? And Peter answering says to him, Thou art the Christ. 30 And he charged them straitly, in order that they should tell no man about him. 31 And he began to teach them that the Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected of the elders and of the chief priests and of the scribes, and be killed, and after three days rise again. 32 And he spoke the thing openly. And Peter, taking him to him, began to rebuke him. 33 But he, turning round and seeing his disciples, rebuked Peter, saying, Get away behind me, Satan, for thy mind is not on the things that are of God, but on the things that are of men. 34 And having called the crowd with his disciples, he said to them, Whoever desires to come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross and follow me. 35 For whosoever shall desire to save his life shall lose it, but whosoever shall lose his life for my sake and the gospel's shall save it. 36 For what shall it profit a man if he gain the whole world and suffer the loss of his soul? 37 for what should a man give in exchange for his soul? 38 For whosoever shall be ashamed of me and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, of him shall the Son of man also be ashamed when he shall come in the glory of his Father with the holy angels.

Mark 9

1 And he said to them, Verily I say unto you, There are some of those standing here that shall not taste death until they shall have seen the kingdom of God come in power. 2 And after six days Jesus takes with him Peter and James and John, and takes them up on a high mountain by themselves apart. And he was transfigured before them: 3 and his garments became shining, exceeding white as snow, such as fuller on earth could not whiten them. 4 And there appeared to them Elias with Moses, and they were talking with Jesus. 5 And Peter answering says to Jesus, Rabbi, it is good that we should be here; and let us make three tabernacles, for thee one, and for Moses one, and for Elias one. 6 For he knew not what he should say, for they were filled with fear. 7 And there came a cloud overshadowing them, and there came a voice out of the cloud, This is my beloved Son: hear him. 8 And suddenly having looked around, they no longer saw any one, but Jesus alone with themselves. 9 And as they descended from the mountain, he charged them that they should relate to no one what they had seen, unless when the Son of man should be risen from among the dead. 10 And they kept that saying, questioning among themselves, what rising from among the dead was. 11 And they asked him saying, Why do the scribes say that Elias must first have come? 12 And he answering said to them, Elias indeed, having first come, restores all things; and how is it written of the Son of man that he must suffer much, and be set at nought: 13 but I say unto you that Elias also is come, and they have done to him whatever they would, as it is written of him.

14 And when he came to the disciples he saw a great crowd around them, and scribes disputing against them. 15 And immediately all the crowd seeing him were amazed, and running to him, saluted him. 16 And he asked them, What do ye question with them about? 17 And one out of the crowd answered him, Teacher, I brought to thee my son, who has a dumb spirit; 18 and wheresoever it seizes him it tears him, and he foams and gnashes his teeth, and he is withering away. And I spoke to thy disciples, that they might cast him out, and they could not. 19 But he answering them says, O unbelieving generation! how long shall I be with you? how long shall I bear with you? bring him to me. 20 And they brought him to him. And seeing him the spirit immediately tore him; and falling upon the earth he rolled foaming. 21 And he asked his father, How long a time is it that it has been like this with him? And he said, From childhood; 22 and often it has cast him both into fire and into waters that it might destroy him: but if thou couldst do anything, be moved with pity on us, and help us. 23 And Jesus said to him, The 'if thou couldst' is if thou couldst believe: all things are possible to him that believes. 24 And immediately the father of the young child crying out said with tears, I believe, help mine unbelief. 25 But Jesus, seeing that the crowd was running up together, rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to him, Thou dumb and deaf spirit, I command thee, come out of him, and enter no more into him. 26 And having cried out and torn him much, he came out; and he became as if dead, so that the most said, He is dead. 27 But Jesus, having taken hold of him by the hand, lifted him up, and he arose. 28 And when he was entered into the house, his disciples asked him privately, Wherefore could not we cast him out? 29 And he said to them, This kind can go out by nothing but by prayer and fasting.

30 And going forth from thence they went through Galilee; and he would not that any one knew it; 31 for he taught his disciples and said to them, The Son of man is delivered into men's hands, and they shall kill him; and having been killed, after three days he shall rise again. 32 But they understood not the saying, and feared to ask him. 33 And he came to Capernaum, and being in the house, he asked them, Of what were ye reasoning by the way? 34 And they remained silent, for by the way they had been reasoning with one another who was greatest. 35 And sitting down he called the twelve; and he says to them, If any one would be first, he shall be last of all, and minister of all. 36 And taking a little child he set it in their midst, and having taken it in his arms he said to them, 37 Whosoever shall receive one of such little children in my name, receives me; and whosoever shall receive me, does not receive me, but him who sent me. 38 And John answered him saying, Teacher, we saw some one casting out demons in thy name, who does not follow us, and we forbad him, because he does not follow us. 39 But Jesus said, Forbid him not; for there is no one who shall do a miracle in my name, and be able soon after to speak ill of me; 40 for he who is not against us is for us.

41 For whosoever shall give you a cup of water to drink in my name, because ye are Christ's, verily I say unto you, he shall in no wise lose his reward. 42 And whosoever shall be a snare to one of the little ones who believe in me, it were better for him if a millstone were hung about his neck, and he cast into the sea. 43 And if thy hand serve as a snare to thee, cut it off: it is better for thee to enter into life maimed, than having thy two hands to go away into hell, into the fire unquenchable; 44 where their worm dies not, and the fire is not quenched. 45 And if thy foot serve as a snare to thee, cut it off: it is better for thee to enter into life lame, than having thy two feet to be cast into hell, into the fire unquenchable; 46 where their worm dies not, and the fire is not quenched. 47 And if thine eye serve as a snare to thee, cast it out: it is better for thee to enter into the kingdom of God with one eye, rather than having two eyes to be cast into the hell of fire, 48 where their worm dies not, and the fire is not quenched. 49 For every one shall be salted with fire, and every sacrifice shall be salted with salt. 50 Salt is good, but if the salt is become saltless, wherewith will ye season it? Have salt in yourselves, and be at peace with one another.

Mark 10

1 And rising up thence he comes into the coasts of Judaea, and the other side of the Jordan. And again crowds come together to him, and, as he was accustomed, again he taught them. 2 And Pharisees coming to him asked him, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife? (tempting him). 3 But he answering said to them, What did Moses command you? 4 And they said, Moses allowed to write a bill of divorce, and to put away. 5 And Jesus answering said to them, In view of your hard-heartedness he wrote this commandment for you; 6 but from the beginning of the creation God made them male and female. 7 For this cause a man shall leave his father and mother and shall be united to his wife, 8 and the two shall be one flesh: so that they are no longer two but one flesh. 9 What therefore God has joined together, let not man separate. 10 And again in the house the disciples asked him concerning this. 11 And he says to them, Whosoever shall put away his wife and shall marry another, commits adultery against her. 12 And if a woman put away her husband and shall marry another, she commits adultery.

13 And they brought little children to him that he might touch them. But the disciples rebuked those that brought them. 14 But Jesus seeing it, was indignant, and said to them, Suffer the little children to come to me; forbid them not; for of such is the kingdom of God. 15 Verily I say to you, Whosoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child, shall in no wise enter into it. 16 And having taken them in his arms, having laid his hands on them, he blessed them.

17 And as he went forth into the way, a person ran up to him, and kneeling to him asked him, Good Teacher, what shall I do that I may inherit eternal life? 18 But Jesus said to him, Why callest thou me good? no one is good but one, that is God. 19 Thou knowest the commandments: Do not commit adultery, Do not kill, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Do not defraud, Honour thy father and mother. 20 And he answering said to him, Teacher, all these things have I kept from my youth. 21 And Jesus looking upon him loved him, and said to him, One thing lackest thou: go, sell whatever thou hast and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven; and come, follow me, taking up the cross. 22 But he, sad at the word, went away grieved, for he had large possessions. 23 And Jesus looking around says to his disciples, How difficultly shall they that have riches enter into the kingdom of God! 24 And the disciples were amazed at his words. And Jesus again answering says to them, Children, how difficult it is that those who trust in riches should enter into the kingdom of God! 25 It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God. 26 And they were exceedingly astonished, saying to one another, And who can be saved? 27 But Jesus looking on them says, With men it is impossible, but not with God; for all things are possible with God. 28 Peter began to say to him, Behold, we have left all things and have followed thee. 29 Jesus answering said, Verily I say to you, There is no one who has left house, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my sake and for the sake of the gospel, 30 that shall not receive a hundredfold now in this time: houses, and brethren, and sisters, and mothers, and children, and lands, with persecutions, and in the coming age life eternal. 31 But many first shall be last, and the last first.

32 And they were in the way going up to Jerusalem, and Jesus was going on before them; and they were amazed, and were afraid as they followed. And taking the twelve again to him, he began to tell them what was going to happen to him: 33 Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man shall be delivered up to the chief priests and to the scribes, and they shall condemn him to death, and shall deliver him up to the nations: 34 and they shall mock him, and shall scourge him, and shall spit upon him, and shall kill him; and after three days he shall rise again. 35 And there come to him James and John, the sons of Zebedee, saying to him, Teacher, we would that whatsoever we may ask thee, thou wouldst do it for us. 36 And he said to them, What would ye that I should do for you? 37 And they said to him, Give to us that we may sit, one on thy right hand, and one on thy left hand, in thy glory. 38 And Jesus said to them, Ye do not know what ye ask. Are ye able to drink the cup which I drink, or be baptised with the baptism that I am baptised with? 39 And they said to him, We are able. And Jesus said to them, The cup that I drink ye will drink and with the baptism that I am baptised with ye will be baptised, 40 but to sit on my right hand or on my left is not mine to give, but for those for whom it is prepared. 41 And the ten having heard of it, began to be indignant about James and John. 42 But Jesus having called them to him, says to them, Ye know that those who are esteemed to rule over the nations exercise lordship over them; and their great men exercise authority over them; 43 but it is not thus among you; but whosoever would be great among you, shall be your minister; 44 and whosoever would be first of you shall be bondman of all. 45 For also the Son of man did not come to be ministered to, but to minister, and give his life a ransom for many.

46 And they come to Jericho, and as he was going out from Jericho, and his disciples and a large crowd, the son of Timaeus, Bartimaeus, the blind man, sat by the wayside begging. 47 And having heard that it was Jesus the Nazaraean, he began to cry out and to say, O Son of David, Jesus, have mercy on me. 48 And many rebuked him, that he might be silent; but he cried so much the more, Son of David, have mercy on me. 49 And Jesus, standing still, desired him to be called. And they call the blind man, saying to him, Be of good courage, rise up, he calls thee. 50 And, throwing away his garment, he started up and came to Jesus. 51 And Jesus answering says to him, What wilt thou that I shall do to thee? And the blind man said to him, Rabboni, that I may see. 52 And Jesus said to him, Go, thy faith has healed thee. And he saw immediately, and followed him in the way.

Mark 11

1 And when they draw near to Jerusalem, to Bethphage and Bethany, at the mount of Olives, he sends two of his disciples, 2 and says to them, Go into the village which is over against you, and immediately on entering into it ye will find a colt tied, upon which no child of man has ever sat: loose it and lead it here. 3 And if any one say to you, Why do ye this? say, The Lord has need of it; and straightway he sends it hither. 4 And they departed, and found a colt bound to the door without at the crossway, and they loose him. 5 And some of those who stood there said to them, What are ye doing, loosing the colt? 6 And they said to them as Jesus had commanded. And they let them do it. 7 And they led the colt to Jesus, and cast their clothes upon it, and he sat on it; 8 and many strewed their clothes on the way, and others cut down branches from the trees and went on strewing them on the way. 9 And those going on before and those following cried out, Hosanna! blessed be he that comes in the Lord's name. 10 Blessed be the coming kingdom of our father David. Hosanna in the highest! 11 And he entered into Jerusalem and into the temple; and having looked round on all things, the hour being already late, he went out to Bethany with the twelve.

12 And on the morrow, when they were gone out of Bethany, he hungered. 13 And seeing from afar off a fig-tree which had leaves, he came, if perhaps he might find something on it. And having come up to it he found nothing but leaves, for it was not the time of figs. 14 And answering he said to it, Let no one eat fruit of thee any more for ever. And his disciples heard it. 15 And they come to Jerusalem, and entering into the temple, he began to cast out those who sold and who bought in the temple, and he overthrew the tables of the moneychangers and the seats of the dove-sellers, 16 and suffered not that any one should carry any package through the temple. 17 And he taught saying to them, Is it not written, My house shall be called a house of prayer for all the nations? but ye have made it a den of robbers. 18 And the chief priests and the scribes heard it, and they sought how they might destroy him; for they feared him, because all the crowd were astonished at his doctrine. 19 And when it was evening he went forth without the city. 20 And passing by early in the morning they saw the fig-tree dried up from the roots. 21 And Peter, remembering what Jesus had said, says to him, Rabbi, see, the fig-tree which thou cursedst is dried up. 22 And Jesus answering says to them, Have faith in God. 23 Verily I say to you, that whosoever shall say to this mountain, Be thou taken away and cast into the sea, and shall not doubt in his heart, but believe that what he says takes place, whatever he shall say shall come to pass for him. 24 For this reason I say to you, All things whatsoever ye pray for and ask, believe that ye receive it, and it shall come to pass for you. 25 And when ye stand praying, forgive if ye have anything against any one, that your Father also who is in the heavens may forgive you your offences. 26 But if ye do not forgive, neither will your Father who is in the heavens forgive your offences.

27 And they come again to Jerusalem. And as he walked about in the temple, the chief priests and the scribes and the elders come to him, 28 and they say to him, By what authority doest thou these things? and who gave thee this authority, that thou shouldest do these things? 29 And Jesus answering said to them, I also will ask you one thing, and answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things: 30 The baptism of John, was it of heaven, or of men? answer me. 31 And they reasoned with themselves, saying, If we should say, Of heaven, he will say, Why then have ye not believed him? 32 but should we say, Of men--they feared the people; for all held of John that he was truly a prophet. 33 And they answering say to Jesus, We do not know. And Jesus answering says to them, Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.

Mark 12

1 And he began to say to them in parables, A man planted a vineyard, and made a fence round it and dug a wine-vat, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and left the country. 2 And he sent a bondman to the husbandmen at the season, that he might receive from the husbandmen of the fruit of the vineyard. 3 But they took him, and beat him, and sent him away empty. 4 And again he sent to them another bondman; and at him they threw stones, and struck him on the head, and sent him away with insult. 5 And again he sent another, and him they killed; and many others, beating some and killing some. 6 Having yet therefore one beloved son, he sent also him to them the last, saying, They will have respect for my son. 7 But those husbandmen said to one another, This is the heir: come, let us kill him and the inheritance will be ours. 8 And they took him and killed him, and cast him forth out of the vineyard. 9 What therefore shall the lord of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the husbandmen, and will give the vineyard to others. 10 Have ye not even read this scripture, The stone which they that builded rejected, this has become the corner-stone: 11 this is of the Lord, and it is wonderful in our eyes? 12 And they sought to lay hold of him, and they feared the crowd; for they knew that he had spoken the parable of them. And they left him and went away.

13 And they send to him certain of the Pharisees and of the Herodians, that they might catch him in speaking. 14 And they come and say to him, Teacher, we know that thou art true, and carest not for any one; for thou regardest not men's person, but teachest the way of God with truth: Is it lawful to give tribute to Caesar or not? 15 Should we give, or should we not give? But he knowing their hypocrisy said unto them, Why tempt ye me? Bring me a denarius that I may see it. 16 And they brought it. And he says to them, Whose is this image and superscription? And they said to him, Caesar's. 17 And Jesus answering said to them, Pay what is Caesar's to Caesar, and what is God's to God. And they wondered at him.

18 And Sadducees come to him, that say there is no resurrection; and they demanded of him saying, 19 Teacher, Moses wrote to us that if any one's brother die, and leave a wife behind, and leave no children, that his brother shall take his wife, and raise up seed to his brother. 20 There were seven brethren; and the first took a wife, and dying did not leave seed; 21 and the second took her and died, and neither did he leave seed; and the third likewise. 22 And the seven took her and did not leave seed. Last of all the woman also died. 23 In the resurrection, when they shall rise again, of which of them shall she be wife, for the seven had her as wife? 24 And Jesus answering said to them, Do not ye therefore err, not knowing the scriptures, nor the power of God? 25 For when they rise from among the dead they neither marry, nor are given in marriage, but are as angels who are in the heavens. 26 But concerning the dead that they rise, have ye not read in the book of Moses, in the section of the bush, how God spoke to him, saying, I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? 27 He is not the God of the dead, but of the living. Ye therefore greatly err.

28 And one of the scribes who had come up, and had heard them reasoning together, perceiving that he had answered them well, demanded of him, Which is the first commandment of all? 29 And Jesus answered him, The first commandment of all is, Hear, Israel: the Lord our God is one Lord; 30 and thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thine understanding, and with all thy strength. This is the first commandment. 31 And a second like it is this: Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. There is not another commandment greater than these. 32 And the scribe said to him, Right, teacher; thou hast spoken according to the truth. For he is one, and there is none other besides him; 33 and to love him with all the heart, and with all the intelligence, and with all the soul, and with all the strength, and to love one's neighbour as one's self, is more than all the burnt-offerings and sacrifices. 34 And Jesus, seeing that he had answered intelligently, said to him, Thou art not far from the kingdom of God. And no one dared question him any more.

35 And Jesus answering said as he was teaching in the temple, How do the scribes say that the Christ is son of David? 36 for David himself said speaking in the Holy Spirit, The Lord said to my Lord, Sit on my right hand until I put thine enemies as footstool of thy feet. 37 David himself therefore calls him Lord, and whence is he his son? And the mass of the people heard him gladly. 38 And he said to them in his doctrine, Beware of the scribes, who like to walk about in long robes, and salutations in the marketplaces, 39 and first seats in the synagogues, and first places at suppers; 40 who devour the houses of widows, and as a pretext make long prayers. These shall receive a severer judgment.

41 And Jesus, having sat down opposite the treasury, saw how the crowd was casting money into the treasury; and many rich cast in much. 42 And a poor widow came and cast in two mites, which is a farthing. 43 And having called his disciples to him he said to them, Verily I say unto you, This poor widow has cast in more than all who have cast into the treasury: 44 for all have cast in of that which they had in abundance, but she of her destitution has cast in all that she had, the whole of her living.

Mark 13

1 And as he was going out of the temple, one of his disciples says to him, Teacher, see what stones and what buildings! 2 And Jesus answering said to him, Seest thou these great buildings? not a stone shall be left upon a stone, which shall not be thrown down. 3 And as he sat on the mount of Olives opposite the temple, Peter and James and John and Andrew asked him privately, 4 Tell us, when shall these things be, and what is the sign when all these things are going to be fulfilled?

5 And Jesus answering them began to say, Take heed lest any one mislead you. 6 For many shall come in my name, saying, It is I, and shall mislead many. 7 But when ye shall hear of wars and rumours of wars, be not disturbed, for this must happen, but the end is not yet. 8 For nation shall rise up against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; and there shall be earthquakes in different places, and there shall be famines and troubles: these things are the beginnings of throes. 9 But ye, take heed to yourselves, for they shall deliver you up to sanhedrims and to synagogues: ye shall be beaten and brought before rulers and kings for my sake, for a testimony to them; 10 and the gospel must first be preached to all the nations. 11 But when they shall lead you away to deliver you up, be not careful beforehand as to what ye shall say, nor prepare your discourse: but whatsoever shall be given you in that hour, that speak; for ye are not the speakers, but the Holy Spirit. 12 But brother shall deliver up brother to death, and father child; and children shall rise up against parents, and cause them to be put to death. 13 And ye will be hated of all on account of my name; but he that has endured to the end, he shall be saved.

14 But when ye shall see the abomination of desolation standing where it should not, (he that reads let him consider it,) then let those in Judaea flee to the mountains; 15 and him that is upon the housetop not come down into the house, nor enter into it to take away anything out of his house; 16 and him that is in the field not return back to take his garment. 17 But woe to those that are with child and to those that give suck in those days! 18 And pray that it may not be in winter time; 19 for those days shall be distress such as there has not been the like since the beginning of creation which God created, until now, and never shall be; 20 and if the Lord had not cut short those days, no flesh should have been saved; but on account of the elect whom he has chosen, he has cut short those days. 21 And then if any one say to you, Lo, here is the Christ, or Lo, there, believe it not. 22 For false Christs and false prophets will arise, and give signs and wonders to deceive, if possible, even the elect. 23 But do ye take heed: behold, I have told you all things beforehand.

24 But in those days, after that distress, the sun shall be darkened and the moon shall not give its light; 25 and the stars of heaven shall be falling down, and the powers which are in the heavens shall be shaken; 26 and then shall they see the Son of man coming in clouds with great power and glory; 27 and then shall he send his angels and shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from end of earth to end of heaven.

28 But learn the parable from the fig-tree: when its branch already becomes tender and puts forth the leaves, ye know that the summer is near. 29 Thus also ye, when ye see these things happening, know that it is near, at the doors. 30 Verily I say unto you, This generation shall in no wise pass away, till all these things take place. 31 The heaven and the earth shall pass away, but my words shall in no wise pass away. 32 But of that day or of that hour no one knows, neither the angels who are in heaven, nor the Son, but the Father. 33 Take heed, watch and pray, for ye do not know when the time is: 34 it is as a man gone out of the country, having left his house and given to his bondmen the authority, and to each one his work, and commanded the doorkeeper that he should watch. 35 Watch therefore, for ye do not know when the master of the house comes: evening, or midnight, or cock-crow, or morning; 36 lest coming suddenly he find you sleeping. 37 But what I say to you, I say to all, Watch.

Mark 14

1 Now the passover and the feast of unleavened bread was after two days. And the chief priests and the scribes were seeking how they might seize him by subtlety and kill him. 2 For they said, Not in the feast, lest perhaps there be a tumult of the people. 3 And when he was in Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper, as he lay at table, there came a woman having an alabaster flask of ointment of pure nard, very costly; and having broken the alabaster flask, she poured it out upon his head. 4 And there were some indignant in themselves, and saying, Why has this waste been made of the ointment? 5 for this ointment could have been sold for more than three hundred denarii and given to the poor. And they spoke very angrily at her. 6 But Jesus said, Let her alone; why do ye trouble her? she has wrought a good work as to me; 7 for ye have the poor always with you, and whenever ye would ye can do them good; but me ye have not always. 8 What she could she has done. She has beforehand anointed my body for the burial. 9 And verily I say unto you, Wheresoever these glad tidings may be preached in the whole world, what this woman has done shall be also spoken of for a memorial of her. 10 And Judas Iscariote, one of the twelve, went away to the chief priests that he might deliver him up to them; 11 and they, when they heard it, rejoiced, and promised him to give money. And he sought how he could opportunely deliver him up.

12 And the first day of unleavened bread, when they slew the passover, his disciples say to him, Where wilt thou that we go and prepare, that thou mayest eat the passover? 13 And he sends two of his disciples, and says to them, Go into the city, and a man shall meet you carrying a pitcher of water; follow him. 14 And wheresoever he enters, say to the master of the house, The Teacher says, Where is my guest-chamber where I may eat the passover with my disciples? 15 and he will shew you a large upper room furnished ready. There make ready for us. 16 And his disciples went away and came into the city, and found as he had said to them; and they made ready the passover. 17 And when evening was come, he comes with the twelve. 18 And as they lay at table and were eating, Jesus said, Verily I say to you, One of you shall deliver me up; he who is eating with me. 19 And they began to be grieved, and to say to him, one by one, Is it I? and another, Is it I? 20 But he answered and said to them, One of the twelve, he who dips with me in the dish. 21 The Son of man goes indeed as it is written concerning him, but woe to that man by whom the Son of man is delivered up; it were good for that man if he had not been born. 22 And as they were eating, Jesus, having taken bread, when he had blessed, broke it, and gave it to them, and said, Take this: this is my body. 23 And having taken the cup, when he had given thanks, he gave it to them, and they all drank out of it. 24 And he said to them, This is my blood, that of the new covenant, that shed for many. 25 Verily I say to you, I will no more drink at all of the fruit of the vine, until that day when I drink it new in the kingdom of God. 26 And having sung a hymn, they went out to the mount of Olives. 27 And Jesus says to them, All ye shall be offended, for it is written, I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep shall be scattered abroad. 28 But after I am risen, I will go before you into Galilee. 29 But Peter said to him, Even if all should be offended, yet not I. 30 And Jesus says to him, Verily I say to thee, that thou to-day, in this night, before the cock shall crow twice, thou shalt thrice deny me. 31 But he said so much exceedingly the more, If I should have to die with thee, I will in no wise deny thee. And likewise said they all too.

32 And they come to a place of which the name is Gethsemane, and he says to his disciples, Sit here while I shall pray. 33 And he takes with him Peter and James and John, and he began to be amazed and oppressed in spirit. 34 And he says to them, My soul is full of grief even unto death; abide here and watch. 35 And, going forward a little, he fell upon the earth; and he prayed that, if it were possible, the hour might pass away from him. 36 And he said, Abba, Father, all things are possible to thee: take away this cup from me; but not what I will, but what thou wilt. 37 And he comes and finds them sleeping. And he says to Peter, Simon, dost thou sleep? Hast thou not been able to watch one hour? 38 Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation. The spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh weak. 39 And going away, he prayed again, saying the same thing. 40 And returning, he found them again sleeping, for their eyes were heavy; and they knew not what they should answer him. 41 And he comes the third time and says to them, Sleep on now, and take your rest. It is enough; the hour is come; behold, the Son of man is delivered up into the hands of sinners. 42 Arise, let us go; behold, he that delivers me up has drawn nigh.

43 And immediately, while he was yet speaking, Judas comes up, being one of the twelve, and with him a great crowd, with swords and sticks, from the chief priests and the scribes and the elders. 44 Now he that delivered him up had given them a sign between them, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, that is he; seize him, and lead him away safely. 45 And being come, straightway coming up to him, he says, Rabbi, Rabbi; and he covered him with kisses. 46 And they laid their hands upon him and seized him. 47 But a certain one of those who stood by, having drawn his sword, struck the bondman of the high priest, and took off his ear. 48 And Jesus answering said to them, Are ye come out as against a robber, with swords and sticks to take me? 49 I was daily with you teaching in the temple, and ye did not seize me; but it is that the scriptures may be fulfilled. 50 And all left him and fled. 51 And a certain young man followed him with a linen cloth cast about his naked body; and the young men seize him; 52 but he, leaving the linen cloth behind him, fled from them naked.

53 And they led away Jesus to the high priest. And there come together to him all the chief priests and the elders and the scribes. 54 And Peter followed him at a distance, till he was within the court of the high priest's palace; and he was sitting with the officers and warming himself in the light of the fire. 55 And the chief priests and the whole sanhedrim sought testimony against Jesus to cause him to be put to death, and did not find any. 56 For many bore false witness against him, and their testimony did not agree. 57 And certain persons rose up and bore false witness against him, saying, 58 We heard him saying, I will destroy this temple which is made with hands, and in the course of three days I will build another not made with hands. 59 And neither thus did their testimony agree. 60 And the high priest, rising up before them all, asked Jesus, saying, Answerest thou nothing? What do these testify against thee? 61 But he was silent, and answered nothing. Again the high priest asked him, and says to him, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the Blessed? 62 And Jesus said, I am, and ye shall see the Son of man sitting at the right hand of power, and coming with the clouds of heaven. 63 And the high priest, having rent his clothes, says, What need have we any more of witnesses? 64 Ye have heard the blasphemy; what think ye? And they all condemned him to be guilty of death. 65 And some began to spit upon him, and cover up his face, and buffet him, and say to him, Prophesy; and the officers struck him with the palms of their hands.

66 And Peter being below in the palace-court, there comes one of the maids of the high priest, 67 and seeing Peter warming himself, having looked at him, says, And thou wast with the Nazarene, Jesus. 68 But he denied, saying, I know not nor understand what thou sayest. And he went out into the vestibule; and a cock crew. 69 And the maid, seeing him, again began to say to those that stood by, This is one of them. 70 And he again denied. And again, after a little, those that stood by said to Peter, Truly thou art one of them, for also thou art a Galilean. 71 But he began to curse and to swear, I know not this man of whom ye speak. 72 And the second time a cock crew. And Peter remembered the word that Jesus said to him, Before the cock crow twice, thou shalt deny me thrice; and when he thought thereon he wept.

Mark 15

1 And immediately in the morning the chief priests, having taken counsel with the elders and scribes and the whole sanhedrim, bound Jesus and carried him away, and delivered him up to Pilate. 2 And Pilate asked him, Art thou the King of the Jews? And he answered and said to him, Thou sayest. 3 And the chief priests accused him urgently. 4 And Pilate asked him again, saying, Answerest thou nothing? See of how many things they bear witness against thee. 5 But Jesus still answered nothing, so that Pilate marvelled. 6 But at the feast he released to them one prisoner, whomsoever they begged of him. 7 Now there was the person named Barabbas bound with those who had made insurrection with him, and that had committed murder in the insurrection. 8 And the crowd crying out began to beg that he would do to them as he had always done. 9 But Pilate answered them saying, Will ye that I release to you the King of the Jews? 10 for he knew that the chief priests had delivered him up through envy. 11 But the chief priests stirred up the crowd that he might rather release Barabbas to them. 12 And Pilate answering said to them again, What will ye then that I do to him whom ye call King of the Jews? 13 And they cried out again, Crucify him. 14 And Pilate said to them, What evil then has he done? But they cried out the more urgently, Crucify him.

15 And Pilate, desirous of contenting the crowd, released to them Barabbas, and delivered up Jesus, when he had scourged him, that he might be crucified. 16 And the soldiers led him away into the court which is called the praetorium, and they call together the whole band. 17 And they clothe him with purple, and bind round on him a crown of thorns which they had plaited. 18 And they began to salute him, Hail, King of the Jews! 19 And they struck his head with a reed, and spat on him, and, bending the knee, did him homage. 20 And when they had mocked him, they took the purple off him, and put his own clothes on him; and they lead him out that they may crucify him. 21 And they compel to go with them a certain passer-by, Simon, a Cyrenian, coming from the field, the father of Alexander and Rufus, that he might carry his cross.

22 And they bring him to the place called Golgotha, which, being interpreted, is Place of a skull. 23 And they offered him wine to drink medicated with myrrh; but he did not take it. 24 And having crucified him, they part his clothes amongst themselves, casting lots on them, what each one should take. 25 And it was the third hour, and they crucified him. 26 And the superscription of what he was accused of was written up: The King of the Jews. 27 And with him they crucify two robbers, one on his right hand, and one on his left. 28 And the scripture was fulfilled which says, And he was reckoned with the lawless. 29 And they that passed by reviled him, shaking their heads, and saying, Aha, thou that destroyest the temple and buildest it in three days, 30 save thyself, and descend from the cross. 31 In like manner the chief priests also, with the scribes, mocking with one another, said, He saved others; himself he cannot save. 32 Let the Christ the King of Israel descend now from the cross, that we may see and may believe. And they that were crucified with him reproached him.

33 And when the sixth hour was come, there came darkness over the whole land until the ninth hour; 34 and at the ninth hour, Jesus cried with a loud voice, saying, Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani? which is, being interpreted, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? 35 And some of those who stood by, when they heard it, said, Behold, he calls for Elias. 36 And one, running and filling a sponge with vinegar, fixed it on a reed, and gave him to drink, saying, Let alone, let us see if Elias comes to take him down. 37 And Jesus, having uttered a loud cry, expired. 38 And the veil of the temple was rent in two from the top to the bottom. 39 And the centurion who stood by over against him, when he saw that he had expired having thus cried out, said, Truly this man was Son of God. 40 And there were women also looking on from afar off, among whom were both Mary of Magdala, and Mary the mother of James the less and of Joses, and Salome; 41 who also, when he was in Galilee, followed him and ministered to him; and many others who came up with him to Jerusalem.

42 And when it was already evening, since it was the preparation, that is, the day before a sabbath, 43 Joseph of Arimathaea, an honourable councillor, who also himself was awaiting the kingdom of God, coming, emboldened himself and went in to Pilate and begged the body of Jesus. 44 And Pilate wondered if he were already dead; and having called to him the centurion, he inquired of him if he had long died. 45 And when he knew from the centurion, he granted the body to Joseph. 46 And having bought fine linen, and having taken him down, he swathed him in the fine linen, and laid him in a sepulchre which was cut out of rock, and rolled a stone to the door of the sepulchre. 47 And Mary of Magdala and Mary the mother of Joses saw where he was put.

Mark 16

1 And the sabbath being now past, Mary of Magdala, and Mary the mother of James, and Salome, bought aromatic spices that they might come and embalm him. 2 And very early on the first day of the week they come to the sepulchre, the sun having risen. 3 And they said to one another, Who shall roll us away the stone out of the door of the sepulchre? 4 And when they looked, they see that the stone has been rolled away, for it was very great. 5 And entering into the sepulchre, they saw a young man sitting on the right, clothed in a white robe, and they were amazed and alarmed; 6 but he says to them, Be not alarmed. Ye seek Jesus, the Nazarene, the crucified one. He is risen, he is not here; behold the place where they had put him. 7 But go, tell his disciples and Peter, he goes before you into Galilee; there shall ye see him, as he said to you. 8 And they went out, and fled from the sepulchre. And trembling and excessive amazement possessed them, and they said nothing to any one, for they were afraid.

9 Now when he had risen very early, the first day of the week, he appeared first to Mary of Magdala, out of whom he had cast seven demons. 10 She went and brought word to those that had been with him, who were grieving and weeping. 11 And when these heard that he was alive and had been seen of her, they disbelieved it. 12 And after these things he was manifested in another form to two of them as they walked, going into the country; 13 and they went and brought word to the rest; neither did they believe them.

14 Afterwards as they lay at table he was manifested to the eleven, and reproached them with their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they had not believed those who had seen him risen. 15 And he said to them, Go into all the world, and preach the glad tidings to all the creation. 16 He that believes and is baptised shall be saved, and he that disbelieves shall be condemned. 17 And these signs shall follow those that have believed: in my name they shall cast out demons; they shall speak with new tongues; 18 they shall take up serpents; and if they should drink any deadly thing it shall not injure them; they shall lay hands upon the infirm, and they shall be well.

19 The Lord therefore, after he had spoken to them, was taken up into heaven, and sat at the right hand of God. 20 And they, going forth, preached everywhere, the Lord working with them, and confirming the word by the signs following upon it.

Luke 1

1 Forasmuch as many have undertaken to draw up a relation concerning the matters fully believed among us, 2 as those who from the beginning were eye-witnesses of and attendants on the Word have delivered them to us, 3 it has seemed good to me also, accurately acquainted from the origin with all things, to write to thee with method, most excellent Theophilus, 4 that thou mightest know the certainty of those things in which thou hast been instructed.

5 There was in the days of Herod, the king of Judaea, a certain priest, by name Zacharias, of the course of Abia, and his wife of the daughters of Aaron, and her name Elizabeth. 6 And they were both just before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blameless. 7 And they had no child, because Elizabeth was barren, and they were both advanced in years. 8 And it came to pass, as he fulfilled his priestly service before God in the order of his course, 9 it fell to him by lot, according to the custom of the priesthood, to enter into the temple of the Lord to burn incense. 10 And all the multitude of the people were praying without at the hour of incense. 11 And an angel of the Lord appeared to him, standing on the right of the altar of incense. 12 And Zacharias was troubled, seeing him, and fear fell upon him. 13 But the angel said to him, Fear not, Zacharias, because thy supplication has been heard, and thy wife Elizabeth shall bear thee a son, and thou shalt call his name John. 14 And he shall be to thee joy and rejoicing, and many shall rejoice at his birth. 15 For he shall be great before the Lord, and he shall drink no wine nor strong drink; and he shall be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from his mother's womb. 16 And many of the sons of Israel shall he turn to the Lord their God. 17 And he shall go before him in the spirit and power of Elias, to turn hearts of fathers to children, and disobedient ones to the thoughts of just men, to make ready for the Lord a prepared people. 18 And Zacharias said to the angel, How shall I know this, for I am an old man, and my wife advanced in years? 19 And the angel answering, said to him, I am Gabriel, who stand before God, and I have been sent to speak to thee, and to bring these glad tidings to thee; 20 and behold, thou shalt be silent and not able to speak, till the day in which these things shall take place, because thou hast not believed my words, the which shall be fulfilled in their time. 21 And the people were awaiting Zacharias, and they wondered at his delaying in the temple. 22 But when he came out he could not speak to them, and they recognised that he had seen a vision in the temple. And he was making signs to them, and continued dumb. 23 And it came to pass, when the days of his service were completed, he departed to his house. 24 Now after these days, Elizabeth his wife conceived, and hid herself five months, saying, 25 Thus has the Lord done to me in these days in which he looked upon me to take away my reproach among men.

26 But in the sixth month, the angel Gabriel was sent of God to a city of Galilee, of which the name was Nazareth, 27 to a virgin betrothed to a man whose name was Joseph, of the house of David; and the virgin's name was Mary. 28 And the angel came in to her, and said, Hail, thou favoured one! the Lord is with thee: blessed art thou amongst women. 29 But she, seeing the angel, was troubled at his word, and reasoned in her mind what this salutation might be. 30 And the angel said to her, Fear not, Mary, for thou hast found favour with God; 31 and behold, thou shalt conceive in the womb and bear a son, and thou shalt call his name Jesus. 32 He shall be great, and shall be called Son of the Highest; and the Lord God shall give him the throne of David his father; 33 and he shall reign over the house of Jacob for the ages, and of his kingdom there shall not be an end. 34 But Mary said to the angel, How shall this be, since I know not a man? 35 And the angel answering said to her, The Holy Spirit shall come upon thee, and power of the Highest overshadow thee, wherefore the holy thing also which shall be born shall be called Son of God. 36 And behold, Elizabeth, thy kinswoman, she also has conceived a son in her old age, and this is the sixth month to her that was called barren: 37 for nothing shall be impossible with God. 38 And Mary said, Behold the bondmaid of the Lord; be it to me according to thy word. And the angel departed from her.

39 And Mary, rising up in those days, went into the hill country with haste, to a city of Judah, 40 and entered into the house of Zacharias, and saluted Elizabeth. 41 And it came to pass, as Elizabeth heard the salutation of Mary, the babe leaped in her womb; and Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit, 42 and cried out with a loud voice and said, Blessed artthou amongst women, and blessed the fruit of thy womb. 43 And whence is this to me, that the mother of my Lord should come to me? 44 For behold, as the voice of thy salutation sounded in my ears, the babe leaped with joy in my womb. 45 And blessed is she that has believed, for there shall be a fulfilment of the things spoken to her from the Lord. 46 And Mary said, My soul magnifies the Lord, 47 and my spirit has rejoiced in God my Saviour. 48 For he has looked upon the low estate of his bondmaid; for behold, from henceforth all generations shall call me blessed. 49 For the Mighty One has done to me great things, and holy is his name; 50 and his mercy is to generations and generations to them that fear him. 51 He has wrought strength with his arm; he has scattered haughty ones in the thought of their heart. 52 He has put down rulers from thrones, and exalted the lowly. 53 He has filled the hungry with good things, and sent away the rich empty. 54 He has helped Israel his servant, in order to remember mercy, 55 (as he spoke to our fathers,) to Abraham and to his seed for ever. 56 And Mary abode with her about three months, and returned to her house.

57 But the time was fulfilled for Elizabeth that she should bring forth, and she gave birth to a son. 58 And her neighbours and kinsfolk heard that the Lord had magnified his mercy with her, and they rejoiced with her. 59 And it came to pass on the eighth day they came to circumcise the child, and they called it after the name of his father, Zacharias. 60 And his mother answering said, No; but he shall be called John. 61 And they said to her, There is no one among thy kinsfolk who is called by this name. 62 And they made signs to his father as to what he might wish it to be called. 63 And having asked for a writing-table, he wrote saying, John is his name. And they all wondered. 64 And his mouth was opened immediately, and his tongue, and he spake, blessing God. 65 And fear came upon all who dwelt round about them; and in the whole hill-country of Judaea all these things were the subject of conversation. 66 And all who heard them laid them up in their heart, saying, What then will this child be? And the Lord's hand was with him.

67 And Zacharias his father was filled with the Holy Spirit, and prophesied, saying, 68 Blessed be the Lord the God of Israel, because he has visited and wrought redemption for his people, 69 and raised up a horn of deliverance for us in the house of David his servant; 70 as he spoke by the mouth of his holy prophets, who have been since the world began; 71 deliverance from our enemies and out of the hand of all who hate us; 72 to fulfil mercy with our fathers and remember his holy covenant, 73 the oath which he swore to Abraham our father, 74 to give us, that, saved out of the hand of our enemies, we should serve him without fear 75 in piety and righteousness before him all our days. 76 And thou, child, shalt be called the prophet of the Highest; for thou shalt go before the face of the Lord to make ready his ways; 77 to give knowledge of deliverance to his people by the remission of their sins 78 on account of the bowels of mercy of our God; wherein the dayspring from on high has visited us, 79 to shine upon them who were sitting in darkness and in the shadow of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace. 80 --And the child grew and was strengthened in spirit; and he was in the deserts until the day of his shewing to Israel.

Luke 2

1 But it came to pass in those days that a decree went out from Caesar Augustus, that a census should be made of all the habitable world. 2 The census itself first took place when Cyrenius had the government of Syria. 3 And all went to be inscribed in the census roll, each to his own city: 4 and Joseph also went up from Galilee out of the city Nazareth to Judaea, to David's city, the which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and family of David, 5 to be inscribed in the census roll with Mary who was betrothed to him as his wife, she being great with child. 6 And it came to pass, while they were there, the days of her giving birth to her child were fulfilled, 7 and she brought forth her first-born son, and wrapped him up in swaddling-clothes and laid him in the manger, because there was no room for them in the inn.

8 And there were shepherds in that country abiding without, and keeping watch by night over their flock. 9 And lo, an angel of the Lord was there by them, and the glory of the Lord shone around them, and they feared with great fear. 10 And the angel said to them, Fear not, for behold, I announce to you glad tidings of great joy, which shall be to all the people; 11 for to-day a Saviour has been born to you in David's city, who is Christ the Lord. 12 And this is the sign to you: ye shall find a babe wrapped in swaddling-clothes, and lying in a manger. 13 And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host, praising God and saying, 14 Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, good pleasure in men. 15 And it came to pass, as the angels departed from them into heaven, that the shepherds said to one another, Let us make our way then now as far as Bethlehem, and let us see this thing that is come to pass, which the Lord has made known to us. 16 And they came with haste, and found both Mary and Joseph, and the babe lying in the manger; 17 and having seen it they made known about the country the thing which had been said to them concerning this child. 18 And all who heard it wondered at the things said to them by the shepherds. 19 But Mary kept all these things in her mind, pondering them in her heart. 20 And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all things which they had heard and seen, as it had been said to them.

21 And when eight days were fulfilled for circumcising him, his name was called Jesus, which was the name given by the angel before he had been conceived in the womb. 22 And when the days were fulfilled for their purifying according to the law of Moses, they brought him to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord 23 (as it is written in the law of the Lord: Every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord), 24 and to offer a sacrifice according to what is said in the law of the Lord: A pair of turtle doves, or two young pigeons.

25 And behold, there was a man in Jerusalem whose name was Simeon; and this man was just and pious, awaiting the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was upon him. 26 And it was divinely communicated to him by the Holy Spirit, that he should not see death before he should see the Lord's Christ. 27 And he came in the Spirit into the temple; and as the parents brought in the child Jesus that they might do for him according to the custom of the law, 28 he received him into his arms, and blessed God, and said, 29 Lord, now thou lettest thy bondman go, according to thy word, in peace; 30 for mine eyes have seen thy salvation, 31 which thou hast prepared before the face of all peoples; 32 a light for revelation of the Gentiles and the glory of thy people Israel. 33 And his father and mother wondered at the things which were said concerning him. 34 And Simeon blessed them, and said to Mary his mother, Lo, this child is set for the fall and rising up of many in Israel, and for a sign spoken against; 35 (and even a sword shall go through thine own soul;) so that the thoughts may be revealed from many hearts. 36 And there was a prophetess, Anna, daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Asher, who was far advanced in years, having lived with her husband seven years from her virginity, 37 and herself a widow up to eighty-four years; who did not depart from the temple, serving night and day with fastings and prayers; 38 and she coming up the same hour gave praise to the Lord, and spoke of him to all those who waited for redemption in Jerusalem. 39 And when they had completed all things according to the law of the Lord, they returned to Galilee to their own city Nazareth. 40 And the child grew and waxed strong in spirit, filled with wisdom, and God's grace was upon him.

41 And his parents went yearly to Jerusalem at the feast of the passover. 42 And when he was twelve years old, and they went up to Jerusalem according to the custom of the feast 43 and had completed the days, as they returned, the boy Jesus remained behind in Jerusalem, and his parents knew not of it; 44 but, supposing him to be in the company that journeyed together, they went a day's journey, and sought him among their relations and acquaintances: 45 and not having found him they returned to Jerusalem seeking him. 46 And it came to pass, after three days they found him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the teachers and hearing them and asking them questions. 47 And all who heard him were astonished at his understanding and answers. 48 And when they saw him they were amazed: and his mother said to him, Child, why hast thou dealt thus with us? behold, thy father and I have sought thee distressed. 49 And he said to them, Why is it that ye have sought me? did ye not know that I ought to be occupied in my Father's business? 50 And they understood not the thing that he said to them. 51 And he went down with them and came to Nazareth, and he was in subjection to them. And his mother kept all these things in her heart. 52 And Jesus advanced in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and men.

Luke 3

1 Now in the fifteenth year of the government of Tiberius Caesar, Pontius Pilate being governor of Judaea, and Herod tetrarch of Galilee, and Philip his brother tetrarch of Ituraea and the region of Trachonitis, and Lysanias tetrarch of Abilene, 2 in the high priesthood of Annas and Caiaphas, the word of God came upon John, the son of Zacharias, in the wilderness. 3 And he came into all the district round the Jordan, preaching the baptism of repentance for the remission of sins, 4 as it is written in the book of the words of Esaias the prophet: Voice of one crying in the wilderness: Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make straight his paths. 5 Every gorge shall be filled up, and every mountain and hill shall be brought low, and the crooked places shall become a straight path, and the rough places smooth ways, 6 and all flesh shall see the salvation of God. 7 He said therefore to the crowds which went out to be baptised by him, Offspring of vipers, who has forewarned you to flee from the coming wrath? 8 Produce therefore fruits worthy of repentance; and begin not to say in yourselves, We have Abraham for our father, for I say unto you that God is able of these stones to raise up children to Abraham. 9 And already also the axe is applied to the root of the trees; every tree therefore not producing good fruit is cut down and cast into the fire. 10 And the crowds asked him saying, What should we do then? 11 And he answering says to them, He that has two body-coats, let him give to him that has none; and he that has food, let him do likewise. 12 And tax-gatherers came also to be baptised, and they said to him, Teacher, what should we do? 13 And he said to them, Take no more money than what is appointed to you. 14 And persons engaged in military service also asked him saying, And we, what should we do? And he said to them, Oppress no one, nor accuse falsely, and be satisfied with your pay.

15 But as the people were in expectation, and all were reasoning in their hearts concerning John whether he might be the Christ, 16 John answered all, saying, I indeed baptise you with water, but the mightier than I is coming, the thong of whose sandals I am not fit to unloose; he shall baptise you with the Holy Spirit and fire; 17 whose winnowing-fan is in his hand, and he will thoroughly purge his threshing-floor, and will gather the wheat into his garner, but the chaff he will burn with fire unquenchable. 18 Exhorting then many other things also he announced his glad tidings to the people. 19 But Herod the tetrarch, being reproved by him as to Herodias, the wife of his brother, and as to all the wicked things which Herod had done, 20 added this also to all the rest, that he shut up John in prison.

21 And it came to pass, all the people having been baptised, and Jesus having been baptised and praying, that the heaven was opened, 22 and the Holy Spirit descended in a bodily form as a dove upon him; and a voice came out of heaven, Thou art my beloved Son, in thee I have found my delight. 23 And Jesus himself was beginning to be about thirty years old; being as was supposed son of Joseph; of Eli, 24 of Matthat, of Levi, of Melchi, of Janna, of Joseph, 25 of Mattathias, of Amos, of Naoum, of Esli, of Naggai, 26 of Maath, of Mattathias, of Semei, of Joseph, of Juda, 27 of Joannes, of Resa, of Zorobabel, of Salathiel, of Neri, 28 of Melchi, of Addi, of Cosam, of Elmodam, of Er, 29 of Joses, of Eliezer, of Joreim, of Matthat, of Levi, 30 of Simeon, of Juda, of Joseph, of Jonan, of Eliakim, 31 of Meleas, of Menan, of Mattatha, of Nathan, of David, 32 of Jesse, of Obed, of Booz, of Salmon, of Naasson, 33 of Aminadab, of Aram, of Esrom, of Phares, of Juda, 34 of Jacob, of Isaac, of Abraham, of Terah, of Nachor, 35 of Seruch, of Ragau, of Phalek, of Eber, of Sala, 36 of Cainan, of Arphaxad, of Sem, of Noe, of Lamech, 37 of Methusala, of Enoch, of Jared, of Maleleel, of Cainan, 38 of Enos, of Seth, of Adam, of God.

Luke 4

1 But Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, returned from the Jordan, and was led by the Spirit in the wilderness 2 forty days, tempted of the devil; and in those days he did not eat anything, and when they were finished he hungered. 3 And the devil said to him, If thou be Son of God, speak to this stone, that it become bread. 4 And Jesus answered unto him saying, It is written, Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word of God. 5 And the devil, leading him up into a high mountain, shewed him all the kingdoms of the habitable world in a moment of time. 6 And the devil said to him, I will give thee all this power, and their glory; for it is given up to me, and to whomsoever I will I give it. 7 If therefore thou wilt do homage before me, all of it shall be thine. 8 And Jesus answering him said, It is written, Thou shalt do homage to the Lord thy God, and him alone shalt thou serve. 9 And he led him to Jerusalem, and set him on the edge of the temple, and said to him, If thou be Son of God, cast thyself down hence; 10 for it is written, He shall give charge to his angels concerning thee to keep thee; 11 and on their hands shall they bear thee, lest in any wise thou strike thy foot against a stone. 12 And Jesus answering said to him, It is said, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God. 13 And the devil, having completed every temptation, departed from him for a time.

14 And Jesus returned in the power of the Spirit to Galilee; and a rumour went out into the whole surrounding country about him; 15 and he taught in their synagogues, being glorified of all. 16 And he came to Nazareth, where he was brought up; and he entered, according to his custom, into the synagogue on the sabbath day, and stood up to read. 17 And the book of the prophet Esaias was given to him; and having unrolled the book he found the place where it was written, 18 The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, because he has anointed me to preach glad tidings to the poor; he has sent me to preach to captives deliverance, and to theblind sight, to send forth the crushed delivered, 19 to preach the acceptable year of the Lord. 20 And having rolled up the book, when he had delivered it up to the attendant, he sat down; and the eyes of all in the synagogue were fixed upon him. 21 And he began to say to them, To-day this scripture is fulfilled in your ears. 22 And all bore witness to him, and wondered at the words of grace which were coming out of his mouth. And they said, Is not this the son of Joseph? 23 And he said to them, Ye will surely say to me this parable, Physician, heal thyself; whatsoever we have heard has taken place in Capernaum do here also in thine own country. 24 And he said, Verily I say to you, that no prophet is acceptable in his own country. 25 But of a truth I say to you, There were many widows in Israel in the days of Elias, when the heaven was shut up for three years and six months, so that a great famine came upon all the land, 26 and to none of them was Elias sent but to Sarepta of Sidonia, to a woman that was a widow. 27 And there were many lepers in Israel in the time of Elisha the prophet, and none of them was cleansed but Naaman the Syrian. 28 And they were all filled with rage in the synagogue, hearing these things; 29 and rising up they cast him forth out of the city, and led him up to the brow of the mountain upon which their city was built, so that they might throw him down the precipice; 30 but he, passing through the midst of them, went his way,

31 and descended to Capernaum, a city of Galilee, and taught them on the sabbaths. 32 And they were astonished at his doctrine, for his word was with authority. 33 And there was in the synagogue a man having a spirit of an unclean demon, and he cried with a loud voice, 34 saying, Eh! what have we to do with thee, Jesus, Nazarene? hast thou come to destroy us? I know thee who thou art, the Holy One of God. 35 And Jesus rebuked him, saying, Hold thy peace, and come out from him. And the demon, having thrown him down into the midst, came out from him without doing him any injury. 36 And astonishment came upon all, and they spoke to one another, saying, What word is this? for with authority and power he commands the unclean spirits, and they come out. 37 And a rumour went out into every place of the country round concerning him. 38 And rising up out of the synagogue, he entered into the house of Simon. But Simon's mother-in-law was suffering under a bad fever; and they asked him for her. 39 And standing over her, he rebuked the fever, and it left her; and forthwith standing up she served them. 40 And when the sun went down, all, as many as had persons sick with divers diseases, brought them to him, and having laid his hands on every one of them, he healed them; 41 and demons also went out from many, crying out and saying, Thou art the Son of God. And rebuking them, he suffered them not to speak, because they knew him to be the Christ. 42 And when it was day he went out, and went into a desert place, and the crowds sought after him, and came up to him, and would have kept him back that he should not go from them. 43 But he said to them, I must needs announce the glad tidings of the kingdom of God to the other cities also, for for this I have been sent forth. 44 And he was preaching in the synagogues of Galilee.

Luke 5

1 And it came to pass, as the crowd pressed on him to hear the word of God, that he was standing by the lake of Gennesaret: 2 and he saw two ships standing by the lake, but the fishermen, having come down from them, were washing their nets. 3 And getting into one of the ships, which was Simon's, he asked him to draw out a little from the land; and he sat down and taught the crowds out of the ship. 4 But when he ceased speaking, he said to Simon, Draw out into the deep water and let down your nets for a haul. 5 And Simon answering said to him, Master, having laboured through the whole night we have taken nothing, but at thy word I will let down the net. 6 And having done this, they enclosed a great multitude of fishes. And their net broke. 7 And they beckoned to their partners who were in the other ship to come and help them, and they came, and filled both the ships, so that they were sinking. 8 But Simon Peter, seeing it, fell at Jesus' knees, saying, Depart from me, for I am a sinful man, Lord. 9 For astonishment had laid hold on him, and on all those who were with him, at the haul of fishes which they had taken; 10 and in like manner also on James and John, sons of Zebedee, who were partners with Simon. And Jesus said to Simon, Fear not; henceforth thou shalt be catching men. 11 And having run the ships on shore, leaving all they followed him.

12 And it came to pass as he was in one of the cities, that behold, there was a man full of leprosy, and seeing Jesus, falling upon his face, he besought him saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou art able to cleanse me. 13 And stretching forth his hand he touched him, saying, I will; be thou cleansed: and immediately the leprosy departed from him. 14 And he enjoined him to tell no one; but go, shew thyself to the priest, and offer for thy cleansing as Moses ordained, for a testimony to them. 15 But the report concerning him was spread abroad still more, and great crowds came together to hear, and to be healed from their infirmities. 16 And he withdrew himself, and was about in the desert places and praying.

17 And it came to pass on one of the days, that he was teaching, and there were Pharisees and doctors of the law sitting by, who were come out of every village of Galilee and Judaea and out of Jerusalem; and the Lord's power was there to heal them. 18 And lo, men bringing upon a couch a man who was paralysed; and they sought to bring him in, and put him before him. 19 And not finding what way to bring him in, on account of the crowd, going up on the housetop they let him down through the tiles, with his little couch, into the midst before Jesus. 20 And seeing their faith, he said, Man, thy sins are forgiven thee. 21 And the scribes and the Pharisees began to reason in their minds, saying, Who is this who speaks blasphemies? Who is able to forgive sins but God alone? 22 But Jesus, knowing their reasonings, answering said to them, Why reason ye in your hearts? 23 which is easier, to say, Thy sins are forgiven thee; or to say, Rise up and walk? 24 But that ye may know that the Son of man has power on earth to forgive sins, he said to the paralysed man, I say to thee, Arise, and take up thy little couch and go to thine house. 25 And immediately standing up before them, having taken up that whereon he was laid, he departed to his house, glorifying God. 26 And astonishment seized all, and they glorified God, and were filled with fear, saying, We have seen strange things to-day.

27 And after these things he went forth and saw a tax-gatherer, Levi by name, sitting at the receipt of taxes, and said to him, Follow me. 28 And having left all, rising up, he followed him. 29 And Levi made a great entertainment for him in his house, and there was a great crowd of tax-gatherers and others who were at table with them. 30 And their scribes and the Pharisees murmured at his disciples, saying, Why do ye eat and drink with tax-gatherers and sinners? 31 And Jesus answering said to them, They that are in sound health have not need of a physician, but those that are ill. 32 I am not come to call righteous persons, but sinful ones to repentance. 33 And they said to him, Why do the disciples of John fast often and make supplications, in like manner those also of the Pharisees, but thine eat and drink? 34 And he said to them, Can ye make the sons of the bridechamber fast when the bridegroom is with them? 35 But days will come when also the bridegroom will have been taken away from them; then shall they fast in those days. 36 And he spoke also a parable to them: No one puts a piece of a new garment upon an old garment, otherwise he will both rend the new, and the piece which is from the new will not suit with the old. 37 And no one puts new wine into old skins, otherwise the new wine will burst the skins, and it will be poured out, and the skins will be destroyed; 38 but new wine is to be put into new skins, and both are preserved. 39 And no one having drunk old wine straightway wishes for new, for he says, The old is better.

Luke 6

1 And it came to pass on the second-first sabbath, that he went through cornfields, and his disciples were plucking the ears and eating them, rubbing them in their hands. 2 But some of the Pharisees said to them, Why do ye what is not lawful to do on the sabbath? 3 And Jesus answering said to them, Have ye not read so much as this, what David did when he hungered, he and those who were with him, 4 how he entered into the house of God and took the shewbread and ate, and gave to those also who were with him, which it is not lawful that any eat, unless the priests alone? 5 And he said to them, The Son of man is Lord of the sabbath also. 6 And it came to pass on another sabbath also that he entered into the synagogue and taught; and there was a man there, and his right hand was withered. 7 And the scribes and the Pharisees were watching if he would heal on the sabbath, that they might find something of which to accuse him. 8 But he knew their thoughts, and said to the man who had the withered hand, Get up, and stand in the midst. And having risen up he stood there. 9 Jesus therefore said to them, I will ask you if it is lawful on the sabbath to do good, or to do evil? to save life, or to destroy it? 10 And having looked around on them all, he said to him, Stretch out thy hand. And he did so and his hand was restored as the other. 11 But they were filled with madness, and they spoke together among themselves what they should do to Jesus.

12 And it came to pass in those days that he went out into the mountain to pray, and he spent the night in prayer to God. 13 And when it was day he called his disciples, and having chosen out twelve from them, whom also he named apostles: 14 Simon, to whom also he gave the name of Peter, and Andrew his brother, and James and John, and Philip and Bartholomew, 15 and Matthew and Thomas, James the son of Alphaeus and Simon who was called Zealot, 16 and Judas brother of James, and Judas Iscariote, who was also his betrayer; 17 and having descended with them, he stood on a level place, and a crowd of his disciples, and a great multitude of the people from all Judaea and Jerusalem, and the sea coast of Tyre and Sidon, who came to hear him, and to be healed of their diseases; 18 and those that were beset by unclean spirits were healed. 19 And all the crowd sought to touch him, for power went out from him and healed all.

20 And he, lifting up his eyes upon his disciples, said, Blessed are ye poor, for yours is the kingdom of God. 21 Blessed ye that hunger now, for ye shall be filled. Blessed ye that weep now, for ye shall laugh. 22 Blessed are ye when men shall hate you, and when they shall separate you from them, and shall reproach you, and cast out your name as wicked, for the Son of man's sake: 23 rejoice in that day and leap for joy, for behold, your reward is great in the heaven, for after this manner did their fathers act toward the prophets. 24 But woe to you rich, for ye have received your consolation. 25 Woe to you that are filled, for ye shall hunger. Woe to you who laugh now, for ye shall mourn and weep. 26 Woe, when all men speak well of you, for after this manner did their fathers to the false prophets.

27 But to you that hear I say, Love your enemies; do good to those that hate you; 28 bless those that curse you; pray for those who use you despitefully. 29 To him that smites thee on the cheek, offer also the other; and from him that would take away thy garment, forbid not thy body-coat also. 30 To every one that asks of thee, give; and from him that takes away what is thine, ask it not back. 31 And as ye wish that men should do to you, do ye also to them in like manner. 32 And if ye love those that love you, what thank is it to you? for even sinners love those that love them. 33 And if ye do good to those that do good to you, what thank is it to you? for even sinners do the same. 34 And if ye lend to those from whom ye hope to receive, what thank is it to you? for even sinners lend to sinners that they may receive the like. 35 But love your enemies, and do good, and lend, hoping for nothing in return, and your reward shall be great, and ye shall be sons of the Highest; for he is good to the unthankful and wicked. 36 Be ye therefore merciful, even as your Father also is merciful.

37 And judge not, and ye shall not be judged; condemn not, and ye shall not be condemned. Remit, and it shall be remitted to you. 38 Give, and it shall be given to you; good measure, pressed down, and shaken together, and running over, shall be given into your bosom: for with the same measure with which ye mete it shall be measured to you again. 39 And he spoke also a parable to them: Can a blind man lead a blind man? shall not both fall into the ditch? 40 The disciple is not above his teacher, but every one that is perfected shall be as his teacher. 41 But why lookest thou on the mote which is in the eye of thy brother, but perceivest not the beam which is in thine own eye? 42 or how canst thou say to thy brother, Brother, allow me, I will cast out the mote that is in thine eye, thyself not seeing the beam that is in thine eye? Hypocrite, cast out first the beam out of thine eye, and then thou shalt see clear to cast out the mote which is in the eye of thy brother. 43 For there is no good tree which produces corrupt fruit, nor a corrupt tree which produces good fruit; 44 for every tree is known by its own fruit, for figs are not gathered from thorns, nor grapes vintaged from a bramble. 45 The good man, out of the good treasure of his heart, brings forth good; and the wicked man out of the wicked, brings forth what is wicked: for out of the abundance of the heart his mouth speaks. 46 And why call ye me, Lord, Lord, and do not the things that I say? 47 Every one that comes to me, and hears my words and does them, I will shew you to whom he is like. 48 He is like a man building a house, who dug and went deep, and laid a foundation on the rock; but a great rain coming, the stream broke upon that house, and could not shake it, for it had been founded on the rock. 49 And he that has heard and not done, is like a man who has built a house on the ground without a foundation, on which the stream broke, and immediately it fell, and the breach of that house was great.

Luke 7

1 And when he had completed all his words in the hearing of the people, he entered into Capernaum. 2 And a certain centurion's bondman who was dear to him was ill and about to die; 3 and having heard of Jesus, he sent to him elders of the Jews, begging him that he might come and save his bondman. 4 But they, being come to Jesus, besought him diligently, saying, He is worthy to whom thou shouldest grant this, 5 for he loves our nation, and himself has built the synagogue for us. 6 And Jesus went with them. But already, when he was not far from the house, the centurion sent to him friends, saying to him, Lord, do not trouble thyself, for I am not worthy that thou shouldest enter under my roof. 7 Wherefore neither did I count myself worthy to come to thee. But say by a word and my servant shall be healed. 8 For I also am a man placed under authority, having under myself soldiers, and I say to this one, Go, and he goes; and to another, Come, and he comes; and to my bondman, Do this, and he does it. 9 And Jesus hearing this wondered at him, and turning to the crowd following him said, I say to you, Not even in Israel have I found so great faith. 10 And they who had been sent returning to the house found the bondman, who was ill, in good health.

11 And it came to pass afterwards he went into a city called Nain, and many of his disciples and a great crowd went with him. 12 And as he drew near to the gate of the city, behold, a dead man was carried out, the only son of his mother, and she a widow, and a very considerable crowd of the city was with her. 13 And the Lord, seeing her, was moved with compassion for her, and said to her, Weep not; 14 and coming up he touched the bier, and the bearers stopped. And he said, Youth, I say to thee, Wake up. 15 And the dead sat up and began to speak; and he gave him to his mother. 16 And fear seized on all, and they glorified God, saying, A great prophet has been raised up amongst us; and God has visited his people. 17 And this report went out in all Judaea concerning him, and in all the surrounding country. 18 And the disciples of John brought him word concerning all these things:

19 and John, having called two of his disciples, sent to Jesus, saying, Art thou he that is coming, or are we to wait for another? 20 But the men having come to him said, John the baptist has sent us to thee, saying, Art thou he that is coming, or are we to wait for another? 21 In that hour he healed many of diseases and plagues and evil spirits, and to many blind he granted sight. 22 And Jesus answering said to them, Go, bring back word to John of what ye have seen and heard: that blind see, lame walk, lepers are cleansed, deaf hear, dead are raised, poor are evangelized; 23 and blessed is whosoever shall not be offended in me. 24 And the messengers of John having departed, he began to speak to the crowds concerning John: What went ye out into the wilderness to behold? a reed shaken by the wind? 25 But what went ye out to see? a man clothed in delicate garments? Behold, those who are in splendid clothing and live luxuriously are in the courts of kings. 26 But what went ye out to see? a prophet? Yea, I say to you, and what is more excellent than a prophet. 27 This is he concerning whom it is written, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face, who shall prepare thy way before thee; 28 for I say unto you, Among them that are born of women a greater prophet is no one than John the baptist; but he who is a little one in the kingdom of God is greater than he. 29 (And all the people who heard it, and the tax-gatherers, justified God, having been baptised with the baptism of John; 30 but the Pharisees and the lawyers rendered null as to themselves the counsel of God, not having been baptised by him.) 31 To whom therefore shall I liken the men of this generation, and to whom are they like? 32 They are like children sitting in the market-place, and calling one to another and saying, We have piped to you, and ye have not danced; we have mourned to you, and ye have not wept. 33 For John the baptist has come neither eating bread nor drinking wine, and ye say, He has a demon. 34 The Son of man has come eating and drinking, and ye say, Behold an eater and wine-drinker, a friend of tax-gatherers and sinners; 35 and wisdom has been justified of all her children.

36 But one of the Pharisees begged him that he would eat with him. And entering into the house of the Pharisee he took his place at table; 37 and behold, a woman in the city, who was a sinner, and knew that he was sitting at meat in the house of the Pharisee, having taken an alabaster box of myrrh, 38 and standing at his feet behind him weeping, began to wash his feet with tears; and she wiped them with the hairs of her head, and kissed his feet, and anointed them with the myrrh. 39 And the Pharisee who had invited him, seeing it, spoke with himself saying, This person if he were a prophet would have known who and what the woman is who touches him, for she is a sinner. 40 And Jesus answering said to him, Simon, I have somewhat to say to thee. And he says, Teacher, say it. 41 There were two debtors of a certain creditor: one owed five hundred denarii and the other fifty; 42 but as they had nothing to pay, he forgave both of them their debt: say, which of them therefore will love him most? 43 And Simon answering said, I suppose he to whom he forgave the most. And he said to him, Thou hast rightly judged. 44 And turning to the woman he said to Simon, Seest thou this woman? I entered into thy house; thou gavest me not water on my feet, but she has washed my feet with tears, and wiped them with her hair. 45 Thou gavest me not a kiss, but she from the time I came in has not ceased kissing my feet. 46 My head with oil thou didst not anoint, but she has anointed my feet with myrrh. 47 For which cause I say to thee, Her many sins are forgiven; for she loved much; but he to whom little is forgiven loves little. 48 And he said to her, Thy sins are forgiven. 49 And they that were with them at table began to say within themselves, Who is this who forgives also sins? 50 And he said to the woman, Thy faith has saved thee; go in peace.

Luke 8

1 And it came to pass afterwards that he went through the country city by city, and village by village, preaching and announcing the glad tidings of the kingdom of God; and the twelve were with him, 2 and certain women who had been healed of wicked spirits and infirmities, Mary who was called Magdalene, from whom seven demons had gone out, 3 and Joanna, wife of Chuza, Herod's steward, and Susanna, and many others, who ministered to him of their substance.

4 And a great crowd coming together, and those who were coming to him out of each city, he spoke by parable: 5 The sower went out to sow his seed; and as he sowed, some fell along the way, and it was trodden under foot, and the birds of the heaven devoured it up; 6 and other fell upon the rock, and having sprung up, it was dried up because it had not moisture; 7 and other fell in the midst of the thorns, and the thorns having sprung up with it choked it; 8 and other fell into the good ground, and having sprung up bore fruit a hundredfold. As he said these things he cried, He that has ears to hear, let him hear. 9 And his disciples asked him saying, What may this parable be? 10 And he said, To you it is given to know the mysteries of the kingdom of God, but to the rest in parables, in order that seeing they may not see, and hearing they may not understand. 11 But the parable is this: The seed is the word of God. 12 But those by the wayside are those who hear; then comes the devil and takes away the word from their heart that they may not believe and be saved. 13 But those upon the rock, those who when they hear receive the word with joy; and these have no root, who believe for a time, and in time of trial fall away. 14 But that that fell where the thorns were, these are they who having heard go away and are choked under cares and riches and pleasures of life, and bring no fruit to perfection. 15 But that in the good ground, these are they who in an honest and good heart, having heard the word keep it, and bring forth fruit with patience. 16 And no one having lighted a lamp covers it with a vessel or puts it under a couch, but sets it on a lamp-stand, that they who enter in may see the light. 17 For there is nothing hid which shall not become manifest, nor secret which shall not be known and come to light. 18 Take heed therefore how ye hear; for whosoever has, to him shall be given, and whosoever has not, even what he seems to have shall be taken from him. 19 And his mother and his brethren came to him, and could not get to him because of the crowd. 20 And it was told him saying, Thy mother and thy brethren stand without, wishing to see thee. 21 But he answering said to them, My mother and my brethren are those who hear the word of God and do it.

22 And it came to pass on one of the days, that he entered into a ship, himself and his disciples; and he said to them, Let us pass over to the other side of the lake; and they set off from shore. 23 And as they sailed, he fell asleep; and a sudden squall of wind came down on the lake, and they were filled with water, and were in danger; 24 and coming to him they woke him up, saying, Master, master, we perish. But he, rising up, rebuked the wind and the raging of the water; and they ceased, and there was a calm. 25 And he said to them, Where is your faith? And, being afraid, they were astonished, saying to one another, Who then is this, that he commands even the winds and the water, and they obey him? 26 And they arrived in the country of the Gadarenes, which is over against Galilee. 27 And as he got out of the ship on the land, a certain man out of the city met him, who had demons a long time, and put on no clothes, and did not abide in a house, but in the tombs. 28 But seeing Jesus, he cried out, and fell down before him, and with a loud voice said, What have I to do with thee, Jesus Son of the Most High God? I beseech thee torment me not. 29 For he had commanded the unclean spirit to go out from the man. For very often it had seized him; and he had been bound, kept with chains and fetters; and breaking the bonds he was driven by the demon into the deserts. 30 And Jesus asked him saying, What is thy name? And he said, Legion: for many demons had entered into him. 31 And they besought him that he would not command them to go away into the bottomless pit. 32 And there was there a herd of many swine feeding on the mountain, and they besought him that he would suffer them to enter into those; and he suffered them. 33 And the demons, going out from the man, entered into the swine, and the herd rushed down the precipice into the lake, and were choked. 34 But they that fed them, seeing what had happened, fled, and told it to the city and to the country. 35 And they went out to see what had happened, and came to Jesus, and found the man from whom the demons had gone out, sitting, clothed and sensible, at the feet of Jesus. And they were afraid. 36 And they also who had seen it told them how the possessed man had been healed. 37 And all the multitude of the surrounding country of the Gadarenes asked him to depart from them, for they were possessed with great fear; and he, entering into the ship, returned. 38 But the man out of whom the demons had gone besought him that he might be with him. But he sent him away, saying, 39 Return to thine house and relate how great things God has done for thee. And he went away through the whole city, publishing how great things Jesus had done for him.

40 And it came to pass when Jesus returned, the crowd received him gladly, for they were all expecting him. 41 And behold, a man came, whose name was Jairus, and he was a ruler of the synagogue, and falling at the feet of Jesus besought him to come to his house, 42 because he had an only daughter, about twelve years old, and she was dying. And as he went the crowds thronged him. 43 And a woman who had a flux of blood since twelve years, who, having spent all her living on physicians, could not be cured by any one, 44 coming up behind, touched the hem of his garment, and immediately her flux of blood stopped. 45 And Jesus said, Who has touched me? But all denying, Peter and those with him said, Master, the crowds close thee in and press upon thee, and sayest thou, Who has touched me? 46 And Jesus said, Some one has touched me, for I have known that power has gone out from me. 47 And the woman, seeing that she was not hid, came trembling, and falling down before him declared before all the people for what cause she had touched him, and how she was immediately healed. 48 And he said to her, Be of good courage, daughter; thy faith has healed thee; go in peace. 49 While he was yet speaking, comes some one from the ruler of the synagogue, saying to him, Thy daughter is dead; do not trouble the teacher. 50 But Jesus, hearing it, answered him saying, Fear not: only believe, and she shall be made well. 51 And when he came to the house he suffered no one to go in but Peter and John and James and the father of the child and the mother. 52 And all were weeping and lamenting her. But he said, Do not weep, for she has not died, but sleeps. 53 And they derided him, knowing that she had died. 54 But he, having turned them all out and taking hold of her hand, cried saying, Child, arise. 55 And her spirit returned, and immediately she rose up; and he commanded something to eat to be given to her. 56 And her parents were amazed; but he enjoined them to tell no one what had happened.

Luke 9

1 And having called together the twelve, he gave them power and authority over all demons, and to heal diseases, 2 and sent them to proclaim the kingdom of God and to heal the sick. 3 And he said to them, Take nothing for the way, neither staff, nor scrip, nor bread, nor money; nor to have two body-coats apiece. 4 And into whatsoever house ye enter, there abide and thence go forth. 5 And as many as may not receive you, going forth from that city, shake off even the dust from your feet for a witness against them. 6 And going forth they passed through the villages, announcing the glad tidings and healing everywhere. 7 And Herod the tetrarch heard of all the things which were done by him, and was in perplexity, because it was said by some that John was risen from among the dead, 8 and by some that Elias had appeared, and by others that one of the old prophets had risen again. 9 And Herod said, John I have beheaded, but who is this of whom I hear such things? and he sought to see him.

10 And the apostles having returned related to him whatever they had done. And he took them and withdrew apart into a desert place of a city called Bethsaida. 11 But the crowds knowing it followed him; and he received them and spake to them of the kingdom of God, and cured those that had need of healing. 12 But the day began to decline, and the twelve came and said to him, Send away the crowd that they may go into the villages around, and into the fields, and lodge and find victuals, for here we are in a desert place. 13 And he said to them, Give ye them to eat. And they said, We have not more than five loaves and two fishes, unless we should go and buy food for all this people; 14 for they were about five thousand men. And he said to his disciples, Make them sit down in companies by fifties. 15 And they did so, and made them all sit down. 16 And taking the five loaves and the two fishes, looking up to heaven he blessed them, and broke and gave to the disciples to set before the crowd. 17 And they all ate and were filled; and there was taken up of what had remained over and above to them in fragments twelve hand-baskets.

18 And it came to pass as he was praying alone, his disciples were with him, and he asked them saying, Who do the crowds say that I am? 19 But they answering said, John the baptist; but others, Elias; and others, that one of the old prophets has risen again. 20 And he said to them, But ye, who do ye say that I am? And Peter answering said, The Christ of God. 21 But, earnestly charging them, he enjoined them to say this to no man, 22 saying, The Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected of the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and the third day be raised up. 23 And he said to them all, If any one will come after me, let him deny himself and take up his cross daily and follow me; 24 for whosoever shall desire to save his life shall lose it, but whosoever shall lose his life for my sake, he shall save it. 25 For what shall a man profit if he shall have gained the whole world, and have destroyed, or come under the penalty of the loss of himself? 26 For whosoever shall have been ashamed of me and of my words, of him will the Son of man be ashamed when he shall come in his glory, and in that of the Father, and of the holy angels. 27 But I say unto you of a truth, There are some of those standing here who shall not taste death until they shall have seen the kingdom of God.

28 And it came to pass after these words, about eight days, that taking Peter and John and James he went up into a mountain to pray. 29 And as he prayed the fashion of his countenance became different and his raiment white and effulgent. 30 And lo, two men talked with him, who were Moses and Elias, 31 who, appearing in glory, spoke of his departure which he was about to accomplish in Jerusalem. 32 But Peter and those with him were oppressed with sleep: but having fully awoke up they saw his glory, and the two men who stood with him. 33 And it came to pass as they departed from him, Peter said to Jesus, Master, it is good for us to be here; and let us make three tabernacles, one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias: not knowing what he said. 34 But as he was saying these things, there came a cloud and overshadowed them, and they feared as they entered into the cloud: 35 and there was a voice out of the cloud saying, This is my beloved Son: hear him. 36 And as the voice was heard Jesus was found alone: and they kept silence, and told no one in those days any of the things they had seen.

37 And it came to pass on the following day, when they came down from the mountain, a great crowd met him. 38 And lo, a man from the crowd cried out saying, Teacher, I beseech thee look upon my son, for he is mine only child: 39 and behold, a spirit takes him, and suddenly he cries out, and it tears him with foaming, and with difficulty departs from him after crushing him. 40 And I besought thy disciples that they might cast him out, and they could not. 41 And Jesus answering said, O unbelieving and perverted generation, how long shall I be with you and suffer you? Bring hither thy son. 42 But as he was yet coming, the demon tore him and dragged him all together. And Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit, and healed the child and gave him back to his father.

43 And all were astonished at the glorious greatness of God. And as all wondered at all the things which Jesus did, he said to his disciples, 44 Do ye let these words sink into your ears. For the Son of man is about to be delivered into men's hands. 45 But they understood not this saying, and it was hid from them that they should not perceive it. And they feared to ask him concerning this saying. 46 And a reasoning came in amongst them, who should be the greatest of them. 47 And Jesus, seeing the reasoning of their heart, having taken a little child set it by him, 48 and said to them, Whosoever shall receive this little child in my name receives me, and whosoever shall receive me receives him that sent me. For he who is the least among you all, he is great. 49 And John answering said, Master, we saw some one casting out demons in thy name, and we forbad him, because he follows not with us. 50 And Jesus said to him, Forbid him not, for he that is not against you is for you.

51 And it came to pass when the days of his receiving up were fulfilled, that he stedfastly set his face to go to Jerusalem. 52 And he sent messengers before his face. And having gone they entered into a village of the Samaritans that they might make ready for him. 53 And they did not receive him, because his face was turned as going to Jerusalem. 54 And his disciples James and John seeing it said, Lord, wilt thou that we speak that fire come down from heaven and consume them, as also Elias did? 55 But turning he rebuked them and said, Ye know not of what spirit ye are. 56 And they went to another village.

57 And it came to pass as they went in the way, one said to him, I will follow thee wheresoever thou goest, Lord. 58 And Jesus said to him, The foxes have holes and the birds of the heaven roosting-places, but the Son of man has not where he may lay his head. 59 And he said to another, Follow me. But he said, Lord, allow me to go first and bury my father. 60 But Jesus said to him, Suffer the dead to bury their own dead, but do thou go and announce the kingdom of God. 61 And another also said, I will follow thee, Lord, but first allow me to bid adieu to those at my house. 62 But Jesus said to him, No one having laid his hand on the plough and looking back is fit for the kingdom of God.

Luke 10

1 Now after these things the Lord appointed seventy others also, and sent them two and two before his face into every city and place where he himself was about to come. 2 And he said to them, The harvest indeed is great, but the workmen few; supplicate therefore the Lord of the harvest that he may send out workmen into his harvest. 3 Go: behold I send you forth as lambs in the midst of wolves. 4 Carry neither purse nor scrip nor sandals, and salute no one on the way. 5 And into whatsoever house ye enter, first say, Peace to this house. 6 And if a son of peace be there, your peace shall rest upon it; but if not it shall turn to you again. 7 And in the same house abide, eating and drinking such things as they have; for the workman is worthy of his hire. Remove not from house to house. 8 And into whatsoever city ye may enter and they receive you, eat what is set before you, 9 and heal the sick in it, and say to them, The kingdom of God is come nigh to you. 10 But into whatsoever city ye may have entered and they do not receive you, go out into its streets and say, 11 Even the dust of your city, which cleaves to us on the feet, do we shake off against you; but know this, that the kingdom of God is come nigh. 12 I say to you that it shall be more tolerable for Sodom in that day than for that city. 13 Woe to thee, Chorazin! woe to thee, Bethsaida! for if the works of power which have taken place in you had taken place in Tyre and Sidon, they had long ago repented, sitting in sackcloth and ashes. 14 But it shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon in the judgment than for you. 15 And thou, Capernaum, who hast been raised up to heaven, shalt be brought down even to hades. 16 He that hears you hears me; and he that rejects you rejects me; and he that rejects me rejects him that sent me.

17 And the seventy returned with joy, saying, Lord, even the demons are subject to us through thy name. 18 And he said to them, I beheld Satan as lightning falling out of heaven. 19 Behold, I give you the power of treading upon serpents and scorpions and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing shall in anywise injure you. 20 Yet in this rejoice not, that the spirits are subjected to you, but rejoice that your names are written in the heavens. 21 In the same hour Jesus rejoiced in spirit and said, I praise thee, Father, Lord of the heaven and of the earth, that thou hast hid these things from wise and prudent, and hast revealed them to babes: yea, Father, for thus has it been well-pleasing in thy sight. 22 All things have been delivered to me by my Father, and no one knows who the Son is but the Father, and who the Father is but the Son, and he to whomsoever the Son is pleased to reveal him. 23 And having turned to the disciples privately he said, Blessed are the eyes which see the things that ye see. 24 For I say to you that many prophets and kings have desired to see the things which ye behold, and did not see them; and to hear the things which ye hear, and did not hear them.

25 And behold, a certain lawyer stood up tempting him, and saying, Teacher, having done what, shall I inherit life eternal? 26 And he said to him, What is written in the law? how readest thou? 27 But he answering said, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy strength, and with all thine understanding; and thy neighbour as thyself. 28 And he said to him, Thou hast answered right: this do and thou shalt live. 29 But he, desirous of justifying himself, said to Jesus, And who is my neighbour? 30 And Jesus replying said, A certain man descended from Jerusalem to Jericho and fell into the hands of robbers, who also, having stripped him and inflicted wounds, went away leaving him in a half-dead state. 31 And a certain priest happened to go down that way, and seeing him, passed on on the opposite side; 32 and in like manner also a Levite, being at the spot, came and looked at him and passed on on the opposite side. 33 But a certain Samaritan journeying came to him, and seeing him, was moved with compassion, 34 and came up to him and bound up his wounds, pouring in oil and wine; and having put him on his own beast, took him to the inn and took care of him. 35 And on the morrow as he left, taking out two denarii he gave them to the innkeeper, and said to him, Take care of him, and whatsoever thou shalt expend more, I will render to thee on my coming back. 36 Which now of these three seems to thee to have been neighbour of him who fell into the hands of the robbers? 37 And he said, He that shewed him mercy. And Jesus said to him, Go, and do thou likewise.

38 And it came to pass as they went that he entered into a certain village; and a certain woman, Martha by name, received him into her house. 39 And she had a sister called Mary, who also, having sat down at the feet of Jesus was listening to his word. 40 Now Martha was distracted with much serving, and coming up she said, Lord, dost thou not care that my sister has left me to serve alone? Speak to her therefore that she may help me. 41 But Jesus answering said to her, Martha, Martha, thou art careful and troubled about many things; 42 but there is need of one, and Mary has chosen the good part, the which shall not be taken from her.

Luke 11

1 And it came to pass as he was in a certain place praying, when he ceased, one of his disciples said to him, Lord, teach us to pray, even as John also taught his disciples. 2 And he said to them, When ye pray, say, Father, thy name be hallowed; thy kingdom come; 3 give us our needed bread for each day; 4 and remit us our sins, for we also remit to every one indebted to us; and lead us not into temptation. 5 And he said to them, Who among you shall have a friend, and shall go to him at midnight and say to him, Friend, let me have three loaves, 6 since a friend of mine on a journey is come to me, and I have nothing to set before him; 7 and he within answering should say, Do not disturb me; the door is already shut, and my children are with me in bed; I cannot rise up to give it thee? 8 --I say to you, Although he will not get up and give them to him because he is his friend, because of his shamelessness, at any rate, he will rise and give him as many as he wants. 9 And I say to you, Ask, and it shall be given to you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened to you. 10 For every one that asks receives; and he that seeks finds; and to him that knocks it will be opened. 11 But of whom of you that is a father shall a son ask bread, and the father shall give him a stone? or also a fish, and instead of a fish shall give him a serpent? 12 or if also he shall ask an egg, shall give him a scorpion? 13 If therefore ye, being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much rather shall the Father who is of heaven give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him?

14 And he was casting out a demon, and it was dumb; and it came to pass, the demon being gone out, the dumb man spoke. And the crowds wondered. 15 But some from among them said, By Beelzebub the prince of the demons casts he out demons. 16 And others tempting him sought from him a sign out of heaven. 17 But he, knowing their thoughts, said to them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation: and a house set against a house falls; 18 and if also Satan is divided against himself, how shall his kingdom subsist? because ye say that I cast out demons by Beelzebub. 19 But if I by Beelzebub cast out demons, your sons--by whom do they cast them out? For this reason they shall be your judges. 20 But if by the finger of God I cast out demons, then the kingdom of God is come upon you. 21 When the strong man armed keeps his own house, his goods are in peace; 22 but when the stronger than he coming upon him overcomes him, he takes away his panoply in which he trusted, and he will divide the spoil he has taken from him. 23 He that is not with me is against me, and he that gathers not with me scatters. 24 When the unclean spirit has gone out of the man, he goes through dry places seeking rest; and not finding any he says, I will return to my house whence I came out. 25 And having come, he finds it swept and adorned. 26 Then he goes and takes seven other spirits worse than himself, and entering in, they dwell there; and the last condition of that man becomes worse than the first.

27 And it came to pass as he spake these things, a certain woman, lifting up her voice out of the crowd, said to him, Blessed is the womb that has borne thee, and the paps which thou hast sucked. 28 But he said, Yea rather, blessed are they who hear the word of God and keep it.

29 But as the crowds thronged together, he began to say, This generation is a wicked generation: it seeks a sign, and a sign shall not be given to it but the sign of Jonas. 30 For as Jonas was a sign to the Ninevites, thus shall also the Son of man be to this generation. 31 A queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with the men of this generation, and shall condemn them: for she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and behold, more than Solomon is here. 32 Men of Nineveh shall stand up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for they repented at the preaching of Jonas; and behold, more than Jonas is here. 33 But no one having lit a lamp sets it in secret, nor under the corn-measure, but on the lamp-stand, that they who enter in may see the light. 34 The lamp of the body is thine eye: when thine eye is simple, thy whole body also is light; but when it is wicked, thy body also is dark. 35 See therefore that the light which is in thee be not darkness. 36 If therefore thy whole body is light, not having any part dark, it shall be all light as when the lamp lights thee with its brightness.

37 But as he spoke, a certain Pharisee asked him that he would dine with him; and entering in he placed himself at table. 38 But the Pharisee seeing it wondered that he had not first washed before dinner. 39 But the Lord said to him, Now do ye Pharisees cleanse the outside of the cup and of the dish, but your inward parts are full of plunder and wickedness. 40 Fools, has not he who has made the outside made the inside also? 41 But rather give alms of what ye have, and behold, all things are clean to you. 42 But woe unto you, Pharisees, for ye pay tithes of mint and rue and every herb, and pass by the judgment and the love of God: these ye ought to have done, and not have left those aside. 43 Woe unto you, Pharisees, for ye love the first seat in the synagogues and salutations in the market-places. 44 Woe unto you, for ye are as the sepulchres which appear not, and the men walking over them do not know it. 45 And one of the doctors of the law answering says to him, Teacher, in saying these things thou insultest us also. 46 And he said, To you also woe, doctors of the law, for ye lay upon men burdens heavy to bear, and yourselves do not touch the burdens with one of your fingers. 47 Woe unto you, for ye build the sepulchres of the prophets, but your fathers killed them. 48 Ye bear witness then, and consent to the works of your fathers; for they killed them, and ye build their sepulchres. 49 For this reason also the wisdom of God has said, I will send to them prophets and apostles, and of these shall they kill and drive out by persecution, 50 that the blood of all the prophets which has been poured out from the foundation of the world may be required of this generation, 51 from the blood of Abel to the blood of Zacharias, who perished between the altar and the house; yea, I say to you, it shall be required of this generation. 52 Woe unto you, the doctors of the law, for ye have taken away the key of knowledge; yourselves have not entered in, and those who were entering in ye have hindered. 53 And as he said these things to them, the scribes and the Pharisees began to press him urgently, and to make him speak of many things; 54 watching him, and seeking to catch something out of his mouth, that they might accuse him.

Luke 12

1 In those times, the myriads of the crowd being gathered together, so that they trod one on another, he began to say to his disciples first, Beware of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy; 2 but there is nothing covered up which shall not be revealed, nor secret that shall not be known; 3 therefore whatever ye have said in the darkness shall be heard in the light, and what ye have spoken in the ear in chambers shall be proclaimed upon the housetops. 4 But I say to you, my friends, Fear not those who kill the body and after this have no more that they can do. 5 But I will shew you whom ye shall fear: Fear him who after he has killed has authority to cast into hell; yea, I say to you, Fear him. 6 Are not five sparrows sold for two assaria? and one of them is not forgotten before God. 7 But even the hairs of your head are all numbered. Fear not therefore, ye are better than many sparrows. 8 But I say to you, Whosoever shall confess me before men, the Son of man will confess him also before the angels of God; 9 but he that shall have denied me before men shall be denied before the angels of God; 10 and whoever shall say a word against the Son of man it shall be forgiven him; but to him that speaks injuriously against the Holy Spirit it shall not be forgiven. 11 But when they bring you before the synagogues and rulers and the authorities, be not careful how or what ye shall answer, or what ye shall say; 12 for the Holy Spirit shall teach you in the hour itself what should be said.

13 And a person said to him out of the crowd, Teacher, speak to my brother to divide the inheritance with me. 14 But he said to him, Man, who established me as a judge or a divider over you? 15 And he said to them, Take heed and keep yourselves from all covetousness, for it is not because a man is in abundance that his life is in his possessions. 16 And he spoke a parable to them, saying, The land of a certain rich man brought forth abundantly. 17 And he reasoned within himself saying, What shall I do? for I have not a place where I shall lay up my fruits. 18 And he said, This will I do: I will take away my granaries and build greater, and there I will lay up all my produce and my good things; 19 and I will say to my soul, Soul, thou hast much good things laid by for many years; repose thyself, eat, drink, be merry. 20 But God said to him, Fool, this night thy soul shall be required of thee; and whose shall be what thou hast prepared? 21 Thus is he who lays up treasure for himself, and is not rich toward God.

22 And he said to his disciples, For this cause I say unto you, Be not careful for life, what ye shall eat, nor for the body, what ye shall put on. 23 The life is more than food, and the body than raiment. 24 Consider the ravens, that they sow not nor reap; which have neither storehouse nor granary; and God feeds them. How much better are ye than the birds? 25 But which of you by being careful can add to his stature one cubit? 26 If therefore ye cannot do even what is least, why are ye careful about the rest? 27 Consider the lilies how they grow: they neither toil nor spin; but I say unto you, Not even Solomon in all his glory was clothed as one of these. 28 But if God thus clothe the grass, which to-day is in the field and to-morrow is cast into the oven, how much rather you, O ye of little faith? 29 And ye, seek not what ye shall eat or what ye shall drink, and be not in anxiety; 30 for all these things do the nations of the world seek after, and your Father knows that ye have need of these things; 31 but seek his kingdom, and all these things shall be added to you. 32 Fear not, little flock, for it has been the good pleasure of your Father to give you the kingdom. 33 Sell what ye possess and give alms; make to yourselves purses which do not grow old, a treasure which does not fail in the heavens, where thief does not draw near nor moth destroy. 34 For where your treasure is, there also will your heart be. 35 Let your loins be girded about, and lamps burning; 36 and ye like men who wait their own lord whenever he may leave the wedding, that when he comes and knocks, they may open to him immediately. 37 Blessed are those bondmen whom the lord on coming shall find watching; verily I say unto you, that he will gird himself and make them recline at table, and coming up will serve them. 38 And if he come in the second watch, and come in the third watch, and find them thus, blessed are those bondmen. 39 But this know, that if the master of the house had known in what hour the thief was coming, he would have watched, and not have suffered his house to be dug through. 40 And ye therefore, be ye ready, for in the hour in which ye do not think it, the Son of man comes.

41 And Peter said to him, Lord, sayest thou this parable to us, or also to all? 42 And the Lord said, Who then is the faithful and prudent steward, whom his lord will set over his household, to give the measure of corn in season? 43 Blessed is that bondman whom his lord on coming shall find doing thus; 44 verily I say unto you, that he will set him over all that he has. 45 But if that bondman should say in his heart, My lord delays to come, and begin to beat the menservants and the maidservants, and to eat and to drink and to be drunken, 46 the lord of that bondman shall come in a day when he does not expect it, and in an hour he knows not of, and shall cut him in two and appoint his portion with the unbelievers. 47 But that bondman who knew his own lord's will, and had not prepared himself nor done his will, shall be beaten with many stripes; 48 but he who knew it not, and did things worthy of stripes, shall be beaten with few. And to every one to whom much has been given, much shall be required from him; and to whom menhave committed much, they will ask from him the more. 49 I have come to cast a fire on the earth; and what will I if already it has been kindled? 50 But I have a baptism to be baptised with, and how am I straitened until it shall have been accomplished! 51 Think ye that I have come to give peace in the earth? Nay, I say to you, but rather division: 52 for from henceforth there shall be five in one house divided; three shall be divided against two, and two against three: 53 father against son, and son against father; mother against daughter, and daughter against mother; a mother-in-law against her daughter-in-law, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law.

54 And he said also to the crowds, When ye see a cloud rising out of the west, straightway ye say, A shower is coming; and so it happens. 55 And when ye see the south wind blow, ye say, There will be heat; and it happens. 56 Hypocrites, ye know how to judge of the appearance of the earth and of the heaven; how is it then that ye do not discern this time? 57 And why even of yourselves judge ye not what is right? 58 For as thou goest with thine adverse party before a magistrate, strive in the way to be reconciled with him, lest he drag thee away to the judge, and the judge shall deliver thee to the officer, and the officer cast thee into prison. 59 I say unto thee, Thou shalt in no wise come out thence until thou hast paid the very last mite.

Luke 13

1 Now at the same time there were present some who told him of the Galileans whose blood Pilate mingled with that of their sacrifices. 2 And he answering said to them, Think ye that these Galileans were sinners beyond all the Galileans because they suffered such things? 3 No, I say to you, but if ye repent not, ye shall all perish in the same manner. 4 Or those eighteen on whom the tower in Siloam fell and killed them, think ye that they were debtors beyond all the men who dwell in Jerusalem? 5 No, I say to you, but if ye repent not, ye shall all perish in like manner.

6 And he spoke this parable: A certain man had a fig-tree planted in his vineyard, and he came seeking fruit upon it and did not find any. 7 And he said to the vinedresser, Behold, these three years I come seeking fruit on this fig-tree and find none: cut it down; why does it also render the ground useless? 8 But he answering says to him, Sir, let it alone for this year also, until I shall dig about it and put dung, 9 and if it shall bear fruit--but if not, after that thou shalt cut it down.

10 And he was teaching in one of the synagogues on the sabbath. 11 And lo, there was a woman having a spirit of infirmity eighteen years, and she was bent together and wholly unable to lift her head up. 12 And Jesus, seeing her, called to her, and said to her, Woman, thou art loosed from thine infirmity. 13 And he laid his hands upon her; and immediately she was made straight, and glorified God. 14 But the ruler of the synagogue, indignant because Jesus healed on the sabbath, answering said to the crowd, There are six days in which people ought to work; in these therefore come and be healed, and not on the sabbath day. 15 The Lord therefore answered him and said, Hypocrites! does not each one of you on the sabbath loose his ox or his ass from the manger and leading it away, water it? 16 And this woman, who is a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan has bound, lo, these eighteen years, ought she not to be loosed from this bond on the sabbath day? 17 And as he said these things, all who were opposed to him were ashamed; and all the crowd rejoiced at all the glorious things which were being done by him.

18 And he said, To what is the kingdom of God like? and to what shall I liken it? 19 It is like a grain of mustard seed which a man took and cast into his garden; and it grew and became a great tree, and the birds of heaven lodged in its branches. 20 And again he said, To what shall I liken the kingdom of God? 21 It is like leaven, which a woman took and hid in three measures of meal until the whole was leavened. 22 And he went through one city and village after another, teaching, and journeying to Jerusalem.

23 And one said to him, Sir, are such as are to be saved few in number? But he said unto them, 24 Strive with earnestness to enter in through the narrow door, for many, I say to you, will seek to enter in and will not be able. 25 From the time that the master of the house shall have risen up and shall have shut the door, and ye shall begin to stand without and to knock at the door, saying, Lord, open to us; and he answering shall say to you, I know you not whence ye are: 26 then shall ye begin to say, We have eaten in thy presence and drunk, and thou hast taught in our streets; 27 and he shall say, I tell you, I do not know you whence ye are; depart from me, all ye workers of iniquity. 28 There shall be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth, when ye shall see Abraham and Isaac and Jacob and all the prophets in the kingdom of God, but yourselves cast out. 29 And they shall come from east and west, and from north and south, and shall lie down at table in the kingdom of God. 30 And behold, there are last who shall be first, and there are first who shall be last.

31 The same hour certain Pharisees came up, saying to him, Get out, and go hence, for Herod is desirous to kill thee. 32 And he said to them, Go, tell that fox, Behold, I cast out demons and accomplish cures to-day and to-morrow, and the third day I am perfected; 33 but I must needs walk to-day and to-morrow and the day following, for it must not be that a prophet perish out of Jerusalem. 34 Jerusalem, Jerusalem, the city that kills the prophets and stones those that are sent unto her, how often would I have gathered thy children together, as a hen her brood under her wings, and ye would not. 35 Behold, your house is left unto you; and I say unto you, that ye shall not see me until it come that ye say, Blessed is he that comes in the name of the Lord.

Luke 14

1 And it came to pass, as he went into the house of one of the rulers, who was of the Pharisees, to eat bread on the sabbath, that they were watching him. 2 And behold, there was a certain dropsical man before him. 3 And Jesus answering spoke unto the doctors of the law and Pharisees, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath? 4 But they were silent. And taking him he healed him and let him go. 5 And answering he said to them, Of which of you shall an ass or ox fall into a well, that he does not straightway pull him up on the sabbath day? 6 And they were not able to answer him to these things.

7 And he spoke a parable to those that were invited, remarking how they chose out the first places, saying to them, 8 When thou art invited by any one to a wedding, do not lay thyself down in the first place at table, lest perhaps a more honourable than thou be invited by him, 9 and he who invited thee and him come and say to thee, Give place to this man, and then thou begin with shame to take the last place. 10 But when thou hast been invited, go and put thyself down in the last place, that when he who has invited thee comes, he may say to thee, Friend, go up higher: then shalt thou have honour before all that are lying at table with thee; 11 for every one that exalts himself shall be abased, and he that abases himself shall be exalted. 12 And he said also to him that had invited him, When thou makest a dinner or a supper, call not thy friends, nor thy brethren, nor thy kinsfolk, nor rich neighbours, lest it may be they also should invite thee in return, and a recompense be made thee. 13 But when thou makest a feast, call poor, crippled, lame, blind: 14 and thou shalt be blessed; for they have not the means to recompense thee; for it shall be recompensed thee in the resurrection of the just.

15 And one of those that were lying at table with them, hearing these things, said to him, Blessed is he who shall eat bread in the kingdom of God. 16 And he said to him, A certain man made a great supper and invited many. 17 And he sent his bondman at the hour of supper to say to those who were invited, Come, for already all things are ready. 18 And all began, without exception, to excuse themselves. The first said to him, I have bought land, and I must go out and see it; I pray thee hold me for excused. 19 And another said, I have bought five yoke of oxen, and I go to prove them; I pray thee hold me for excused. 20 And another said, I have married a wife, and on this account I cannot come. 21 And the bondman came up and brought back word of these things to his lord. Then the master of the house, in anger, said to his bondman, Go out quickly into the streets and lanes of the city, and bring here the poor and crippled and lame and blind. 22 And the bondman said, Sir, it is done as thou hast commanded, and there is still room. 23 And the lord said to the bondman, Go out into the ways and fences and compel to come in, that my house may be filled; 24 for I say to you, that not one of those men who were invited shall taste of my supper.

25 And great crowds went with him; and, turning round, he said to them, 26 If any man come to me, and shall not hate his own father and mother, and wife, and children, and brothers, and sisters, yea, and his own life too, he cannot be my disciple; 27 and whoever does not carry his cross and come after me cannot be my disciple. 28 For which of you, desirous of building a tower, does not first sit down and count the cost, if he have what is needed to complete it; 29 in order that, having laid the foundation of it, and not being able to finish it, all who see it do not begin to mock at him, 30 saying, This man began to build and was not able to finish? 31 Or what king, going on his way to engage in war with another king, does not, sitting down first, take counsel whether he is able with ten thousand to meet him coming against him with twenty thousand? 32 and if not, while he is yet far off, having sent an embassy, he asks for terms of peace. 33 Thus then every one of you who forsakes not all that is his own cannot be my disciple. 34 Salt then is good, but if the salt also has become savourless, wherewith shall it be seasoned? 35 It is proper neither for land nor for dung; it is cast out. He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.

Luke 15

1 And all the tax-gatherers and the sinners were coming near to him to hear him; 2 and the Pharisees and the scribes murmured, saying, This man receives sinners and eats with them. 3 And he spoke to them this parable, saying, 4 What man of you having a hundred sheep, and having lost one of them, does not leave the ninety and nine in the wilderness and go after that which is lost, until he find it? 5 and having found it, he lays it upon his own shoulders, rejoicing; 6 and being come to the house, calls together the friends and the neighbours, saying to them, Rejoice with me, for I have found my lost sheep. 7 I say unto you, that thus there shall be joy in heaven for one repenting sinner, more than for ninety and nine righteous who have no need of repentance. 8 Or, what woman having ten drachmas, if she lose one drachma, does not light a lamp and sweep the house and seek carefully till she find it? 9 and having found it she calls together the friends and neighbours, saying, Rejoice with me, for I have found the drachma which I had lost. 10 Thus, I say unto you, there is joy before the angels of God for one repenting sinner.

11 And he said, A certain man had two sons; 12 and the younger of them said to his father, Father, give to me the share of the property that falls to me. And he divided to them what he was possessed of. 13 And after not many days the younger son gathering all together went away into a country a long way off, and there dissipated his property, living in debauchery. 14 But when he had spent all there arose a violent famine throughout that country, and he began to be in want. 15 And he went and joined himself to one of the citizens of that country, and he sent him into his fields to feed swine. 16 And he longed to fill his belly with the husks which the swine were eating; and no one gave to him. 17 And coming to himself, he said, How many hired servants of my father's have abundance of bread, and I perish here by famine. 18 I will rise up and go to my father, and I will say to him, Father, I have sinned against heaven and before thee; 19 I am no longer worthy to be called thy son: make me as one of thy hired servants. 20 And he rose up and went to his own father. But while he was yet a long way off, his father saw him, and was moved with compassion, and ran, and fell upon his neck, and covered him with kisses. 21 And the son said to him, Father, I have sinned against heaven and before thee; I am no longer worthy to be called thy son. 22 But the father said to his bondmen, Bring out the best robe and clothe him in it, and put a ring on his hand and sandals on his feet; 23 and bring the fatted calf and kill it, and let us eat and make merry: 24 for this my son was dead and has come to life, was lost and has been found. And they began to make merry. 25 And his elder son was in the field; and as, coming up, he drew nigh to the house, he heard music and dancing. 26 And having called one of the servants, he inquired what these things might be. 27 And he said to him, Thy brother is come, and thy father has killed the fatted calf because he has received him safe and well. 28 But he became angry and would not go in. And his father went out and besought him. 29 But he answering said to his father, Behold, so many years I serve thee, and never have I transgressed a commandment of thine; and to me hast thou never given a kid that I might make merry with my friends: 30 but when this thy son, who has devoured thy substance with harlots, is come, thou hast killed for him the fatted calf. 31 But he said to him, Child, thou art ever with me, and all that is mine is thine. 32 But it was right to make merry and rejoice, because this thy brother was dead and has come to life again, and was lost and has been found.

Luke 16

1 And he said also to his disciples, There was a certain rich man who had a steward, and he was accused to him as wasting his goods. 2 And having called him, he said to him, What is this that I hear of thee? give the reckoning of thy stewardship, for thou canst be no longer steward. 3 And the steward said within himself, What shall I do; for my lord is taking the stewardship from me? I am not able to dig; I am ashamed to beg. 4 I know what I will do, that when I shall have been removed from the stewardship I may be received into their houses. 5 And having called to him each one of the debtors of his own lord, he said to the first, How much owest thou to my lord? 6 And he said, A hundred baths of oil. And he said to him, Take thy writing and sit down quickly and write fifty. 7 Then he said to another, And thou, how much dost thou owe? And he said, A hundred cors of wheat. And he says to him, Take thy writing and write eighty. 8 And the lord praised the unrighteous steward because he had done prudently. For the sons of this world are, for their own generation, more prudent than the sons of light. 9 And I say to you, Make to yourselves friends with the mammon of unrighteousness, that when it fails ye may be received into the eternal tabernacles. 10 He that is faithful in the least is faithful also in much; and he that is unrighteous in the least is unrighteous also in much. 11 If therefore ye have not been faithful in the unrighteous mammon, who shall entrust to you the true? 12 and if ye have not been faithful in that which is another's, who shall give to you your own? 13 No servant can serve two masters, for either he will hate the one and will love the other, or he will cleave to the one and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon. 14 And the Pharisees also, who were covetous, heard all these things, and mocked him. 15 And he said to them, Ye are they who justify themselves before men, but God knows your hearts; for what amongst men is highly thought of is an abomination before God. 16 The law and the prophets were until John: from that time the glad tidings of the kingdom of God are announced, and every one forces his way into it. 17 But it is easier that the heaven and the earth should pass away than that one tittle of the law should fail. 18 Every one who puts away his wife and marries another commits adultery; and every one that marries one put away from a husband commits adultery.

19 Now there was a rich man and he was clothed in purple and fine linen, making good cheer in splendour every day. 20 And there was a poor man, by name Lazarus, who was laid at his gateway full of sores, 21 and desiring to be filled with the crumbs which fell from the table of the rich man; but the dogs also coming licked his sores. 22 And it came to pass that the poor man died, and that he was carried away by the angels into the bosom of Abraham. And the rich man also died and was buried. 23 And in hades lifting up his eyes, being in torments, he sees Abraham afar off, and Lazarus in his bosom. 24 And he crying out said, Father Abraham, have compassion on me, and send Lazarus that he may dip the tip of his finger in water and cool my tongue, for I am suffering in this flame. 25 But Abraham said, Child, recollect that thou hast fully received thy good things in thy lifetime, and likewise Lazarus evil things. But now he is comforted here, and thou art in suffering. 26 And besides all this, between us and you a great chasm is fixed, so that those who desire to pass hence to you cannot, nor do they who desire to cross from there pass over unto us. 27 And he said, I beseech thee then, father, that thou wouldest send him to the house of my father, 28 for I have five brothers, so that he may earnestly testify to them, that they also may not come to this place of torment. 29 But Abraham says to him, They have Moses and the prophets: let them hear them. 30 But he said, Nay, father Abraham, but if one from the dead should go to them, they will repent. 31 And he said to him, If they hear not Moses and the prophets, not even if one rise from among the dead will they be persuaded.

Luke 17

1 And he said to his disciples, It cannot be but that offences come, but woe to him by whom they come! 2 It would be more profitable for him if a millstone were hanged about his neck and he cast into the sea, than that he should be a snare to one of these little ones. 3 Take heed to yourselves: if thy brother should sin, rebuke him; and if he should repent, forgive him. 4 And if he should sin against thee seven times in the day, and seven times should return to thee, saying, I repent, thou shalt forgive him. 5 And the apostles said to the Lord, Give more faith to us. 6 But the Lord said, If ye have faith as a grain of mustard seed, ye had said to this sycamine tree, Be thou rooted up, and be thou planted in the sea, and it would have obeyed you. 7 But which of you is there who, having a bondman ploughing or shepherding, when he comes in out of the field, will say, Come and lie down immediately to table? 8 But will he not say to him, Prepare what I shall sup on, and gird thyself and serve me that I may eat and drink; and after that thou shalt eat and drink? 9 Is he thankful to the bondman because he has done what was ordered? I judge not. 10 Thus ye also, when ye shall have done all things that have been ordered you, say, We are unprofitable bondmen; we have done what it was our duty to do.

11 And it came to pass as he was going up to Jerusalem, that he passed through the midst of Samaria and Galilee. 12 And as he entered into a certain village ten leprous men met him, who stood afar off. 13 And they lifted up their voice saying, Jesus, Master, have compassion on us. 14 And seeing them he said to them, Go, shew yourselves to the priests. And it came to pass as they were going they were cleansed. 15 And one of them, seeing that he was cured, turned back, glorifying God with a loud voice, 16 and fell on his face at his feet giving him thanks: and he was a Samaritan. 17 And Jesus answering said, Were not the ten cleansed? but the nine, where are they? 18 There have not been found to return and give glory to God save this stranger. 19 And he said to him, Rise up and go thy way: thy faith has made thee well.

20 And having been asked by the Pharisees, When is the kingdom of God coming? he answered them and said, The kingdom of God does not come with observation; 21 nor shall they say, Lo here, or, Lo there; for behold, the kingdom of God is in the midst of you. 22 And he said to the disciples, Days are coming, when ye shall desire to see one of the days of the Son of man, and shall not see it. 23 And they will say to you, Lo here, or Lo there; go not, nor follow them. 24 For as the lightning shines which lightens from one end under heaven to the other end under heaven, thus shall the Son of man be in his day. 25 But first he must suffer many things and be rejected of this generation. 26 And as it took place in the days of Noe, thus also shall it be in the days of the Son of man: 27 they ate, they drank, they married, they were given in marriage, until the day that Noe entered into the ark, and the flood came and destroyed all of them; 28 and in like manner as took place in the days of Lot: they ate, they drank, they bought, they sold, they planted, they builded; 29 but on the day that Lot went out from Sodom, it rained fire and sulphur from heaven, and destroyed all of them: 30 after this manner shall it be in the day that the Son of man is revealed. 31 In that day, he who shall be on the housetop, and his stuff in the house, let him not go down to take it away; and he that is in the field, let him likewise not return back. 32 Remember the wife of Lot. 33 Whosoever shall seek to save his life shall lose it, and whosoever shall lose it shall preserve it. 34 I say to you, In that night there shall be two men upon one bed; one shall be seized and the other shall be let go. 35 Two women shall be grinding together; the one shall be seized and the other shall be let go. 36 Two men shall be in the field; the one shall be seized and the other let go. 37 And answering they say to him, Where, Lord? And he said to them, Where the body is, there the eagles will be gathered together.

Luke 18

1 And he spoke also a parable to them to the purport that they should always pray and not faint, 2 saying, There was a judge in a city, not fearing God and not respecting man: 3 and there was a widow in that city, and she came to him, saying, Avenge me of mine adverse party. 4 And he would not for a time; but afterwards he said within himself, If even I fear not God and respect not man, 5 at any rate because this widow annoys me I will avenge her, that she may not by perpetually coming completely harass me. 6 And the Lord said, Hear what the unjust judge says. 7 And shall not God at all avenge his elect, who cry to him day and night, and he bears long as to them? 8 I say unto you that he will avenge them speedily. But when the Son of man comes, shall he indeed find faith on the earth?

9 And he spoke also to some, who trusted in themselves that they were righteous and made nothing of all the rest of men, this parable: 10 Two men went up into the temple to pray; the one a Pharisee, and the other a tax-gatherer. 11 The Pharisee, standing, prayed thus to himself: God, I thank thee that I am not as the rest of men, rapacious, unjust, adulterers, or even as this tax-gatherer. 12 I fast twice in the week, I tithe everything I gain. 13 And the tax-gatherer, standing afar off, would not lift up even his eyes to heaven, but smote upon his breast, saying, O God, have compassion on me, the sinner. 14 I say unto you, This man went down to his house justified rather than that other. For every one who exalts himself shall be humbled, and he that humbles himself shall be exalted.

15 And they brought to him also infants that he might touch them, but the disciples when they saw it rebuked them. 16 But Jesus calling them to him said, Suffer little children to come to me, and do not forbid them, for of such is the kingdom of God. 17 Verily I say to you, Whosoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child shall in no wise enter therein.

18 And a certain ruler asked him saying, Good teacher, having done what, shall I inherit eternal life? 19 But Jesus said to him, Why callest thou me good? There is none good but one, God. 20 Thou knowest the commandments: Do not commit adultery, Do not kill, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Honour thy father and thy mother. 21 And he said, All these things have I kept from my youth. 22 And when Jesus had heard this, he said to him, One thing is lacking to thee yet: Sell all that thou hast and distribute to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in the heavens, and come, follow me. 23 But when he heard this he became very sorrowful, for he was very rich. 24 But when Jesus saw that he became very sorrowful, he said, How difficultly shall those who have riches enter into the kingdom of God; 25 for it is easier for a camel to enter through a needle's eye than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God. 26 And those who heard it said, And who can be saved? 27 But he said, The things that are impossible with men are possible with God. 28 And Peter said, Behold, we have left all things and have followed thee. 29 And he said to them, Verily I say to you, There is no one who has left home, or parents, or brethren, or wife, or children, for the kingdom of God's sake, 30 who shall not receive manifold more at this time, and in the coming age life eternal.

31 And he took the twelve to him and said to them, Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and all things that are written of the Son of man by the prophets shall be accomplished; 32 for he shall be delivered up to the nations, and shall be mocked, and insulted, and spit upon. 33 And when they have scourged him they will kill him; and on the third day he will rise again. 34 And they understood nothing of these things. And this word was hidden from them, and they did not know what was said.

35 And it came to pass when he came into the neighbourhood of Jericho, a certain blind man sat by the wayside begging. 36 And when he heard the crowd passing, he inquired what this might be. 37 And they told him that Jesus the Nazaraean was passing by. 38 And he called out saying, Jesus, Son of David, have mercy on me. 39 And those who were going before rebuked him that he might be silent; but he cried out so much the more, Son of David, have mercy on me. 40 And Jesus stood still, and commanded him to be led to him. And when he drew nigh he asked him saying, 41 What wilt thou that I shall do to thee? And he said, Lord, that I may see. 42 And Jesus said to him, See: thy faith has healed thee. 43 And immediately he saw, and followed him, glorifying God. And all the people when they saw it gave praise to God.

Luke 19

1 And he entered and passed through Jericho. 2 And behold, there was a man by name called Zacchaeus, and he was chief tax-gatherer, and he was rich. 3 And he sought to see Jesus who he was: and he could not for the crowd, because he was little in stature. 4 And running on before, he got up into a sycamore that he might see him, for he was going to pass that way. 5 And when he came up to the place, Jesus looked up and saw him, and said to him, Zacchaeus, make haste and come down, for to-day I must remain in thy house. 6 And he made haste and came down, and received him with joy. 7 And all murmured when they saw it, saying, He has turned in to lodge with a sinful man. 8 But Zacchaeus stood and said to the Lord, Behold, Lord, the half of my goods I give to the poor, and if I have taken anything from any man by false accusation, I return him fourfold. 9 And Jesus said to him, To-day salvation is come to this house, inasmuch as he also is a son of Abraham; 10 for the Son of man has come to seek and to save that which is lost.

11 But as they were listening to these things, he added and spake a parable, because he was near to Jerusalem and they thought that the kingdom of God was about to be immediately manifested. 12 He said therefore, A certain high-born man went to a distant country to receive for himself a kingdom and return. 13 And having called his own ten bondmen, he gave to them ten minas, and said to them, Trade while I am coming. 14 But his citizens hated him, and sent an embassy after him, saying, We will not that this man should reign over us. 15 And it came to pass on his arrival back again, having received the kingdom, that he desired these bondmen to whom he gave the money to be called to him, in order that he might know what every one had gained by trading. 16 And the first came up, saying, My Lord, thy mina has produced ten minas. 17 And he said to him, Well done, thou good bondman; because thou hast been faithful in that which is least, be thou in authority over ten cities. 18 And the second came, saying, My Lord, thy mina has made five minas. 19 And he said also to this one, And thou, be over five cities. 20 And another came, saying, My Lord, lo, there is thy mina, which I have kept laid up in a towel. 21 For I feared thee because thou art a harsh man: thou takest up what thou hast not laid down, and thou reapest what thou hast not sowed. 22 He says to him, Out of thy mouth will I judge thee, wicked bondman: thou knewest that I am a harsh man, taking up what I have not laid down and reaping what I have not sowed. 23 And why didst thou not give my money to the bank; and I should have received it, at my coming, with interest? 24 And he said to those that stood by, Take from him the mina and give it to him who has the ten minas. 25 And they said to him, Lord, he has ten minas. 26 For I say unto you, that to every one that has shall be given; but from him that has not, that even which he has shall be taken from him. 27 Moreover those mine enemies, who would not have me to reign over them, bring them here and slay them before me.

28 And having said these things, he went on before, going up to Jerusalem. 29 And it came to pass as he drew near to Bethphage and Bethany at the mountain called the mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples, 30 saying, Go into the village over against you, in which ye will find, on entering it, a colt tied up, on which no child of man ever sat at any time: loose it and lead it here. 31 And if any one ask you, Why do ye loose it? thus shall ye say to him, Because the Lord has need of it. 32 And they that were sent, having gone their way, found as he had said to them. 33 And as they were loosing the colt, its masters said to them, Why loose ye the colt? 34 And they said, Because the Lord has need of it. 35 And they led it to Jesus; and having cast their own garments on the colt, they put Jesus on it. 36 And as he went, they strewed their clothes in the way. 37 And as he drew near, already at the descent of the mount of Olives, all the multitude of the disciples began, rejoicing, to praise God with a loud voice for all the works of power which they had seen, 38 saying, Blessed the King that comes in the name of the Lord: peace in heaven, and glory in the highest. 39 And some of the Pharisees from the crowd said to him, Teacher, rebuke thy disciples. 40 And he answering said to them, I say unto you, If these shall be silent, the stones will cry out.

41 And as he drew near, seeing the city, he wept over it, 42 saying, If thou hadst known, even thou, even at least in this thy day, the things that are for thy peace: but now they are hid from thine eyes; 43 for days shall come upon thee, that thine enemies shall make a palisaded mound about thee, and shall close thee around, and keep thee in on every side, 44 and shall lay thee even with the ground, and thy children in thee; and shall not leave in thee a stone upon a stone: because thou knewest not the season of thy visitation. 45 And entering into the temple, he began to cast out those that sold and bought in it, 46 saying to them, It is written, My house is a house of prayer, but ye have made it a den of robbers. 47 And he was teaching day by day in the temple: and the chief priests and the scribes and the chief of the people sought to destroy him, 48 and did not find what they could do, for all the people hung on him to hear.

Luke 20

1 And it came to pass on one of the days, as he was teaching the people in the temple, and announcing the glad tidings, the chief priests and the scribes with the elders came up, 2 and spoke to him saying, Tell us by what authority thou doest these things, or who is it who has given thee this authority? 3 And he answering said to them, I also will ask you one thing, and tell me: 4 The baptism of John, was it of heaven or of men? 5 And they reasoned among themselves, saying, If we should say, Of heaven, he will say, Why have ye not believed him? 6 but if we should say, Of men, the whole people will stone us, for they are persuaded that John was a prophet. 7 And they answered, they did not know whence. 8 And Jesus said to them, Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.

9 And he began to speak to the people this parable: A man planted a vineyard and let it out to husbandmen, and left the country for a long time. 10 And in the season he sent to the husbandmen a bondman, that they might give to him of the fruit of the vineyard; but the husbandmen, having beaten him, sent him away empty. 11 And again he sent another bondman; but they, having beaten him also, and cast insult upon him, sent him away empty. 12 And again he sent a third; and they, having wounded him also, cast him out. 13 And the lord of the vineyard said, What shall I do? I will send my beloved son: perhaps when they see him they will respect him. 14 But when the husbandmen saw him, they reasoned among themselves, saying, This is the heir; come, let us kill him, that the inheritance may become ours. 15 And having cast him forth out of the vineyard, they killed him. What therefore shall the lord of the vineyard do to them? 16 He will come and destroy those husbandmen, and will give the vineyard to others. And when they heard it they said, May it never be! 17 But he looking at them said, What then is this that is written, The stone which they that builded rejected, this has become the corner-stone? 18 Every one falling on this stone shall be broken, but on whomsoever it shall fall, it shall grind him to powder. 19 And the chief priests and the scribes sought the same hour to lay hands on him, and they feared the people; for they knew that he had spoken this parable of them.

20 And having watched him, they sent out suborned persons, pretending to be just men, that they might take hold of him in his language, so that they might deliver him up to the power and authority of the governor. 21 And they asked him saying, Teacher, we know that thou sayest and teachest rightly, and acceptest no man's person, but teachest with truth the way of God: 22 Is it lawful for us to give tribute to Caesar, or not? 23 But perceiving their deceit he said to them, Why do ye tempt me? 24 Shew me a denarius. Whose image and superscription has it? And answering they said, Caesar's. 25 And he said to them, Pay therefore what is Caesar's to Caesar, and what is God's to God. 26 And they were not able to take hold of him in his expressions before the people, and, wondering at his answer, they were silent.

27 And some of the Sadducees, who deny that there is any resurrection, coming up to him, 28 demanded of him saying, Teacher, Moses wrote to us, If any one's brother, who has a wife, die, and he die childless, his brother shall take the wife and raise up seed to his brother. 29 There were then seven brethren: and the first, having taken a wife, died childless; 30 and the second took the woman, and he died childless; 31 and the third took her: and in like manner also the seven left no children and died; 32 and last of all the woman also died. 33 In the resurrection therefore of which of them does she become wife, for the seven had her as wife? 34 And Jesus said to them, The sons of this world marry and are given in marriage, 35 but they who are counted worthy to have part in that world, and the resurrection from among the dead, neither marry nor are given in marriage; 36 for neither can they die any more, for they are equal to angels, and are sons of God, being sons of the resurrection. 37 But that the dead rise, even Moses shewed in the section of the bush, when he called the Lord the God of Abraham and the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob; 38 but he is not God of the dead but of the living; for all live for him.

39 And some of the scribes answering said, Teacher, thou hast well spoken. 40 For they did not dare any more to ask him anything. 41 And he said to them, How do they say that the Christ is David's son, 42 and David himself says in the book of Psalms, The Lord said to my Lord, Sit at my right hand 43 until I put thine enemies as footstool of thy feet? 44 David therefore calls him Lord, and how is he his son? 45 And, as all the people were listening, he said to his disciples, 46 Beware of the scribes, who like to walk about in long robes, and who love salutations in the market-places, and first seats in the synagogues, and first places at suppers; 47 who devour the houses of widows, and as a pretext make long prayers. These shall receive a severer judgment.

Luke 21

1 And he looked up and saw the rich casting their gifts into the treasury; 2 but he saw also a certain poor widow casting therein two mites. 3 And he said, Verily I say unto you, that this poor widow has cast in more than all; 4 for all these out of their abundance have cast into the gifts of God; but she out of her need has cast in all the living which she had.

5 And as some spoke of the temple, that it was adorned with goodly stones and consecrated offerings, he said, 6 As to these things which ye are beholding, days are coming in which there shall not be left stone upon stone which shall not be thrown down. 7 And they asked him saying, Teacher, when then shall these things be; and what is the sign when these things are going to take place? 8 And he said, See that ye be not led astray, for many shall come in my name, saying, I am he, and the time is drawn nigh: go ye not therefore after them. 9 And when ye shall hear of wars and tumults, be not terrified, for these things must first take place, but the end is not immediately. 10 Then he said to them, Nation shall rise up against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; 11 there shall be both great earthquakes in different places, and famines and pestilences; and there shall be fearful sights and great signs from heaven. 12 But before all these things they shall lay their hands upon you and persecute you, delivering you up to synagogues and prisons, bringing you before kings and governors on account of my name; 13 but it shall turn out to you for a testimony. 14 Settle therefore in your hearts not to meditate beforehand your defence, 15 for I will give you a mouth and wisdom which all your opposers shall not be able to reply to or resist. 16 But ye will be delivered up even by parents and brethren and relations and friends, and they shall put to death some from among you, 17 and ye will be hated of all for my name's sake. 18 And a hair of your head shall in no wise perish. 19 By your patient endurance gain your souls.

20 But when ye see Jerusalem encompassed with armies, then know that its desolation is drawn nigh. 21 Then let those who are in Judaea flee to the mountains, and those who are in the midst of it depart out, and those who are in the country not enter into it; 22 for these are days of avenging, that all the things that are written may be accomplished. 23 But woe to them that are with child and to them who give suck in those days, for there shall be great distress upon the land and wrath upon this people. 24 And they shall fall by the edge of the sword, and be led captive into all the nations; and Jerusalem shall be trodden down of the nations until the times of the nations be fulfilled. 25 And there shall be signs in sun and moon and stars, and upon the earth distress of nations in perplexity at the roar of the sea and rolling waves, 26 men ready to die through fear and expectation of what is coming on the habitable earth, for the powers of the heavens shall be shaken. 27 And then shall they see the Son of man coming in a cloud with power and great glory. 28 But when these things begin to come to pass, look up and lift up your heads, because your redemption draws nigh.

29 And he spoke a parable to them: Behold the fig-tree and all the trees; 30 when they already sprout, ye know of your own selves, on looking at them, that already the summer is near. 31 So also ye, when ye see these things take place, know that the kingdom of God is near. 32 Verily I say unto you, that this generation shall in no wise pass away until all come to pass. 33 The heaven and the earth shall pass away, but my words shall in no wise pass away. 34 But take heed to yourselves lest possibly your hearts be laden with surfeiting and drinking and cares of life, and that day come upon you suddenly unawares; 35 for as a snare shall it come upon all them that dwell upon the face of the whole earth. 36 Watch therefore, praying at every season, that ye may be accounted worthy to escape all these things which are about to come to pass, and to stand before the Son of man. 37 And by day he was teaching in the temple, and by night, going out, he remained abroad on the mountain called the mount of Olives; 38 and all the people came early in the morning to him in the temple to hear him.

Luke 22

1 Now the feast of unleavened bread, which is called the passover, drew nigh, 2 and the chief priests and the scribes sought how they might kill him; for they feared the people. 3 And Satan entered into Judas, who was surnamed Iscariote, being of the number of the twelve. 4 And he went away and spoke with the chief priests and captains as to how he should deliver him up to them. 5 And they were rejoiced, and agreed to give him money. 6 And he came to an agreement to do it, and sought an opportunity to deliver him up to them away from the crowd.

7 And the day of unleavened bread came, in which the passover was to be killed. 8 And he sent Peter and John, saying, Go and prepare the passover for us, that we may eat it. 9 But they said to him, Where wilt thou that we prepare it? 10 And he said to them, Behold, as ye enter into the city a man will meet you, carrying an earthen pitcher of water; follow him into the house where he goes in; 11 and ye shall say to the master of the house, The Teacher says to thee, Where is the guest-chamber where I may eat the passover with my disciples? 12 And he will shew you a large upper room furnished: there make ready. 13 And having gone they found it as he had said to them; and they prepared the passover. 14 And when the hour was come, he placed himself at table, and the twelve apostles with him. 15 And he said to them, With desire I have desired to eat this passover with you before I suffer. 16 For I say unto you, that I will not eat any more at all of it until it be fulfilled in the kingdom of God. 17 And having received a cup, when he had given thanks he said, Take this and divide it among yourselves. 18 For I say unto you, that I will not drink at all of the fruit of the vine until the kingdom of God come. 19 And having taken a loaf, when he had given thanks, he broke it, and gave it to them, saying, This is my body which is given for you: this do in remembrance of me. 20 In like manner also the cup, after having supped, saying, This cup is the new covenant in my blood, which is poured out for you.

21 Moreover, behold, the hand of him that delivers me up is with me on the table; 22 and the Son of man indeed goes as it is determined, but woe unto that man by whom he is delivered up. 23 And they began to question together among themselves who then it could be of them who was about to do this. 24 And there was also a strife among them which of them should be held to be the greatest. 25 And he said to them, The kings of the nations rule over them, and they that exercise authority over them are called benefactors. 26 But ye shall not be thus; but let the greater among you be as the younger, and the leader as he that serves. 27 For which is greater, he that is at table or he that serves? Is not he that is at table? But I am in the midst of you as the one that serves. 28 But ye are they who have persevered with me in my temptations. 29 And I appoint unto you, as my Father has appointed unto me, a kingdom, 30 that ye may eat and drink at my table in my kingdom, and sit on thrones judging the twelve tribes of Israel. 31 And the Lord said, Simon, Simon, behold, Satan has demanded to have you, to sift you as wheat; 32 but I have besought for thee that thy faith fail not; and thou, when once thou hast been restored, confirm thy brethren. 33 And he said to him, Lord, with thee I am ready to go both to prison and to death. 34 And he said, I tell thee, Peter, the cock shall not crow to-day before that thou shalt thrice deny that thou knowest me. 35 And he said to them, When I sent you without purse and scrip and sandals, did ye lack anything? And they said, Nothing. 36 He said therefore to them, But now he that has a purse let him take it, in like manner also a scrip, and he that has none let him sell his garment and buy a sword; 37 for I say unto you, that this that is written must yet be accomplished in me, And he was reckoned with the lawless: for also the things concerning me have an end. 38 And they said, Lord, behold here are two swords. And he said to them, It is enough.

39 And going forth he went according to his custom to the mount of Olives, and the disciples also followed him. 40 And when he was at the place he said to them, Pray that ye enter not into temptation. 41 And he was withdrawn from them about a stone's throw, and having knelt down he prayed, 42 saying, Father, if thou wilt remove this cup from me: --but then, not my will, but thine be done. 43 And an angel appeared to him from heaven strengthening him. 44 And being in conflict he prayed more intently. And his sweat became as great drops of blood, falling down upon the earth. 45 And rising up from his prayer, coming to the disciples, he found them sleeping from grief. 46 And he said to them, Why sleep ye? rise up and pray that ye enter not into temptation.

47 As he was yet speaking, behold, a crowd, and he that was called Judas, one of the twelve, went on before them, and drew near to Jesus to kiss him. 48 And Jesus said to him, Judas, deliverest thou up the Son of man with a kiss? 49 And they who were around him, seeing what was going to follow, said to him, Lord, shall we smite with the sword? 50 And a certain one from among them smote the bondman of the high priest and took off his right ear. 51 And Jesus answering said, Suffer thus far; and having touched his ear, he healed him. 52 And Jesus said to the chief priests and captains of the temple and elders, who were come against him, Have ye come out as against a robber with swords and sticks? 53 When I was day by day with you in the temple ye did not stretch out your hands against me; but this is your hour and the power of darkness.

54 And having laid hold on him, they led him away, and they led him into the house of the high priest. And Peter followed afar off. 55 And they having lit a fire in the midst of the court and sat down together, Peter sat among them. 56 And a certain maid, having seen him sitting by the light, and having fixed her eyes upon him, said, And this man was with him. 57 But he denied him, saying, Woman, I do not know him. 58 And after a short time another seeing him said, And thou art of them. But Peter said, Man, I am not. 59 And after the lapse of about one hour another stoutly maintained it, saying, In truth this man also was with him, for also he is a Galilaean. 60 And Peter said, Man, I know not what thou sayest. And immediately, while he was yet speaking, the cock crew. 61 And the Lord, turning round, looked at Peter; and Peter remembered the word of the Lord, how he said to him, Before the cock crow thou shalt deny me thrice. 62 And Peter, going forth without, wept bitterly.

63 And the men who held him mocked him, beating him; 64 and covering him up, asked him saying, Prophesy, who is it that struck thee? 65 And they said many other injurious things to him. 66 And when it was day, the elderhood of the people, both the chief priests and scribes, were gathered together, and led him into their council, saying, 67 If thou art the Christ, tell us. And he said to them, If I tell you, ye will not at all believe; 68 and if I should ask you, ye would not answer me at all, nor let me go; 69 but henceforth shall the Son of man be sitting on the right hand of the power of God. 70 And they all said, Thou then art the Son of God? And he said to them, Ye say that I am. 71 And they said, What need have we any more of witness, for we have heard ourselves out of his mouth?

Luke 23

1 And the whole multitude of them, rising up, led him to Pilate. 2 And they began to accuse him, saying, We have found this man perverting our nation, and forbidding to give tribute to Caesar, saying that he himself is Christ, a king. 3 And Pilate demanded of him saying, Art thou the king of the Jews? And he answering him said, Thou sayest. 4 And Pilate said to the chief priests and the crowds, I find no guilt in this man. 5 But they insisted, saying, He stirs up the people, teaching throughout all Judaea, beginning from Galilee even on to here. 6 But Pilate, having heard Galilee named, demanded if the man were a Galilaean; 7 and having learned that he was of Herod's jurisdiction, remitted him to Herod, who himself also was at Jerusalem in those days. 8 And when Herod saw Jesus he greatly rejoiced, for he had been a long while desirous of seeing him, because of hearing many things concerning him, and he hoped to see some sign done by him; 9 and he questioned him in many words, but he answered him nothing. 10 And the chief priests and the scribes stood and accused him violently. 11 And Herod with his troops having set him at nought and mocked him, having put a splendid robe upon him, sent him back to Pilate. 12 And Pilate and Herod became friends with one another the same day, for they had been at enmity before between themselves.

13 And Pilate, having called together the chief priests and the rulers and the people, 14 said to them, Ye have brought to me this man as turning away the people to rebellion, and behold, I, having examined him before you, have found nothing criminal in this man as to the things of which ye accuse him; 15 nor Herod either, for I remitted you to him, and behold, nothing worthy of death is done by him. 16 Having chastised him therefore, I will release him. 17 (Now he was obliged to release one for them at the feast.) 18 But they cried out in a mass saying, Away with this man and release Barabbas to us; 19 who was one who, for a certain tumult which had taken place in the city, and for murder, had been cast into prison. 20 Pilate therefore, desirous to release Jesus, again addressed them. 21 But they cried out in reply saying, Crucify, crucify him. 22 And he said the third time to them, What evil then has this man done? I have found no cause of death in him: I will chastise him therefore and release him. 23 But they were urgent with loud voices, begging that he might be crucified. And their voices and those of the chief priests prevailed. 24 And Pilate adjudged that what they begged should take place. 25 And he released him who, for tumult and murder, had been cast into prison, whom they begged for, and Jesus he delivered up to their will.

26 And as they led him away, they laid hold on a certain Simon, a Cyrenian, coming from the field, and put the cross upon him to bear it behind Jesus. 27 And a great multitude of the people, and of women who wailed and lamented him, followed him. 28 And Jesus turning round to them said, Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep over me, but weep over yourselves and over your children; 29 for behold, days are coming in which they will say, Blessed are the barren, and wombs that have not borne, and breasts that have not given suck. 30 Then shall they begin to say to the mountains, Fall upon us; and to the hills, Cover us: 31 for if these things are done in the green tree, what shall take place in the dry?

32 Now two others also, malefactors, were led with him to be put to death. 33 And when they came to the place which is called Skull, there they crucified him, and the malefactors, one on the right hand, the other on the left. 34 And Jesus said, Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do. And, parting out his garments, they cast lots. 35 And the people stood beholding, and the rulers also with them sneered, saying, He has saved others; let him save himself if this is the Christ, the chosen one of God. 36 And the soldiers also made game of him, coming up offering him vinegar, 37 and saying, If thou be the king of the Jews, save thyself. 38 And there was also an inscription written over him in Greek, and Roman, and Hebrew letters: This is the King of the Jews. 39 Now one of the malefactors who had been hanged spoke insultingly to him, saying, Art not thou the Christ? save thyself and us. 40 But the other answering rebuked him, saying, Dost thou too not fear God, thou that art under the same judgment? 41 and we indeed justly, for we receive the just recompense of what we have done; but this man has done nothing amiss. 42 And he said to Jesus, Remember me, Lord, when thou comest in thy kingdom. 43 And Jesus said to him, Verily I say to thee, To-day shalt thou be with me in paradise.

44 And it was about the sixth hour, and there came darkness over the whole land until the ninth hour. 45 And the sun was darkened, and the veil of the temple rent in the midst. 46 And Jesus, having cried with a loud voice, said, Father, into thy hands I commit my spirit. And having said this, he expired. 47 Now the centurion, seeing what took place, glorified God, saying, In very deed this man was just. 48 And all the crowds who had come together to that sight, having seen the things that took place, returned, beating their breasts. 49 And all those who knew him stood afar off, the women also who had followed him from Galilee, beholding these things.

50 And behold, a man named Joseph, who was a councillor, a good man and a just 51 (this man had not assented to their counsel and deed), of Arimathaea, a city of the Jews, who also waited, himself also, for the kingdom of God 52 --he having gone to Pilate begged the body of Jesus; 53 and having taken it down, wrapped it in fine linen and placed him in a tomb hewn in the rock, where no one had ever been laid. 54 And it was preparation day, and the sabbath twilight was coming on. 55 And women, who had come along with him out of Galilee, having followed, saw the sepulchre and how his body was placed. 56 And having returned they prepared aromatic spices and ointments, and remained quiet on the sabbath, according to the commandment.

Luke 24

1 But on the morrow of the sabbath, very early indeed in the morning, they came to the tomb, bringing the aromatic spices which they had prepared. 2 And they found the stone rolled away from the sepulchre. 3 And when they had entered they found not the body of the Lord Jesus. 4 And it came to pass as they were in perplexity about it, that behold, two men suddenly stood by them in shining raiment. 5 And as they were filled with fear and bowed their faces to the ground, they said to them, Why seek ye the living one among the dead? 6 He is not here, but is risen: remember how he spoke to you, being yet in Galilee, 7 saying, The Son of man must be delivered up into the hands of sinners, and be crucified, and rise the third day. 8 And they remembered his words; 9 and, returning from the sepulchre, related all these things to the eleven and to all the rest. 10 Now it was Mary of Magdala, and Johanna, and Mary the mother of James, and the others with them, who told these things to the apostles. 11 And their words appeared in their eyes as an idle tale, and they disbelieved them. 12 But Peter, rising up, ran to the sepulchre, and stooping down he sees the linen clothes lying there alone, and went away home, wondering at what had happened.

13 And behold, two of them were going on the same day to a village distant sixty stadia from Jerusalem, called Emmaus; 14 and they conversed with one another about all these things which had taken place. 15 And it came to pass as they conversed and reasoned, that Jesus himself drawing nigh, went with them; 16 but their eyes were holden so as not to know him. 17 And he said to them, What discourses are these which pass between you as ye walk, and are downcast? 18 And one of them, named Cleopas, answering said to him, Thou sojournest alone in Jerusalem, and dost not know what has taken place in it in these days? 19 And he said to them, What things? And they said to him, The things concerning Jesus the Nazaraean, who was a prophet mighty in deed and word before God and all the people; 20 and how the chief priests and our rulers delivered him up to the judgment of death and crucified him. 21 But we had hoped that he was the one who is about to redeem Israel. But then, besides all these things, it is now, to-day, the third day since these things took place. 22 And withal, certain women from amongst us astonished us, having been very early at the sepulchre, 23 and, not having found his body, came, saying that they also had seen a vision of angels, who say that he is living. 24 And some of those with us went to the sepulchre, and found it so, as the women also had said, but him they saw not. 25 And he said to them, O senseless and slow of heart to believe in all that the prophets have spoken! 26 Ought not the Christ to have suffered these things and to enter into his glory? 27 And having begun from Moses and from all the prophets, he interpreted to them in all the scriptures the things concerning himself. 28 And they drew near to the village where they were going, and he made as though he would go farther. 29 And they constrained him, saying, Stay with us, for it is toward evening and the day is declining. And he entered in to stay with them. 30 And it came to pass as he was at table with them, having taken the bread, he blessed, and having broken it, gave it to them. 31 And their eyes were opened, and they recognised him. And he disappeared from them. 32 And they said to one another, Was not our heart burning in us as he spoke to us on the way, and as he opened the scriptures to us? 33 And rising up the same hour, they returned to Jerusalem. And they found the eleven, and those with them, gathered together, 34 saying, The Lord is indeed risen and has appeared to Simon. 35 And they related what had happened on the way, and how he was made known to them in the breaking of bread.

36 And as they were saying these things, he himself stood in their midst, and says to them, Peace be unto you. 37 But they, being confounded and being frightened, supposed they beheld a spirit. 38 And he said to them, Why are ye troubled? and why are thoughts rising in your hearts? 39 behold my hands and my feet, that it is I myself. Handle me and see, for a spirit has not flesh and bones as ye see me having. 40 And having said this he shewed them his hands and his feet. 41 But while they yet did not believe for joy, and were wondering, he said to them, Have ye anything here to eat? 42 And they gave him part of a broiled fish and of a honeycomb; 43 and he took it and ate before them. 44 And he said to them, These are the words which I spoke to you while I was yet with you, that all that is written concerning me in the law of Moses and prophets and psalms must be fulfilled. 45 Then he opened their understanding to understand the scriptures, 46 and said to them, Thus it is written, and thus it behoved the Christ to suffer, and to rise from among the dead the third day; 47 and that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in his name to all the nations beginning at Jerusalem. 48 And ye are witnesses of these things. 49 And behold, I send the promise of my Father upon you; but do ye remain in the city till ye be clothed with power from on high.

50 And he led them out as far as Bethany, and having lifted up his hands, he blessed them. 51 And it came to pass as he was blessing them, he was separated from them and was carried up into heaven. 52 And they, having done him homage, returned to Jerusalem with great joy, 53 and were continually in the temple praising and blessing God.

John 1

1 In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. 2 He was in the beginning with God. 3 All things received being through him, and without him not one thing received being which has received being. 4 In him was life, and the life was the light of men.

5 And the light appears in darkness, and the darkness apprehended it not. 6 There was a man sent from God, his name John. 7 He came for witness, that he might witness concerning the light, that all might believe through him. 8 He was not the light, but that he might witness concerning the light. 9 The true light was that which, coming into the world, lightens every man. 10 He was in the world, and the world had its being through him, and the world knew him not. 11 He came to his own, and his own received him not; 12 but as many as received him, to them gave he the right to be children of God, to those that believe on his name; 13 who have been born, not of blood, nor of flesh's will, nor of man's will, but of God. 14 And the Word became flesh, and dwelt among us (and we have contemplated his glory, a glory as of an only-begotten with a father), full of grace and truth;

15 (John bears witness of him, and he has cried, saying, This was he of whom I said, He that comes after me is preferred before me, for he was before me;) 16 for of his fulness we all have received, and grace upon grace. 17 For the law was given by Moses: grace and truth subsists through Jesus Christ. 18 No one has seen God at any time; the only-begotten Son, who is in the bosom of the Father, he hath declared him.

19 And this is the witness of John, when the Jews sent from Jerusalem priests and Levites that they might ask him, Thou, who art thou? 20 And he acknowledged and denied not, and acknowledged, I am not the Christ. 21 And they asked him, What then? Art thou Elias? And he says, I am not. Art thou the prophet? And he answered, No. 22 They said therefore to him, Who art thou? that we may give an answer to those who sent us. What sayest thou of thyself? 23 He said, I am the voice of one crying in the wilderness, Make straight the path of the Lord, as said Esaias the prophet. 24 And they were sent from among the Pharisees. 25 And they asked him and said to him, Why baptisest thou then, if thou art not the Christ, nor Elias, nor the prophet? 26 John answered them saying, I baptise with water. In the midst of you stands, whom ye do not know, 27 he who comes after me, the thong of whose sandal I am not worthy to unloose. 28 These things took place in Bethany, across the Jordan, where John was baptising.

29 On the morrow he sees Jesus coming to him, and says, Behold the Lamb of God, who takes away the sin of the world. 30 He it is of whom I said, A man comes after me who takes a place before me, because he was before me; 31 and I knew him not; but that he might be manifested to Israel, therefore have I come baptising with water. 32 And John bore witness, saying, I beheld the Spirit descending as a dove from heaven, and it abode upon him. 33 And I knew him not; but he who sent me to baptise with water, he said to me, Upon whom thou shalt see the Spirit descending and abiding on him, he it is who baptises with the Holy Spirit. 34 And I have seen and borne witness that this is the Son of God. 35 Again, on the morrow, there stood John and two of his disciples. 36 And, looking at Jesus as he walked, he says, Behold the Lamb of God.

37 And the two disciples heard him speaking, and followed Jesus. 38 But Jesus having turned, and seeing them following, says to them, What seek ye? And they said to him, Rabbi (which, being interpreted, signifies Teacher), where abidest thou? 39 He says to them, Come and see. They went therefore, and saw where he abode; and they abode with him that day. It was about the tenth hour. 40 Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, was one of the two who heard this from John and followed him. 41 He first finds his own brother Simon, and says to him, We have found the Messias (which being interpreted is Christ). 42 And he led him to Jesus. Jesus looking at him said, Thou art Simon, the son of Jonas; thou shalt be called Cephas (which interpreted is stone).

43 On the morrow he would go forth into Galilee, and Jesus finds Philip, and says to him, Follow me. 44 And Philip was from Bethsaida, of the city of Andrew and Peter. 45 Philip finds Nathanael, and says to him, We have found him of whom Moses wrote in the law, and the prophets, Jesus, the son of Joseph, who is from Nazareth. 46 And Nathanael said to him, Can anything good come out of Nazareth? Philip says to him, Come and see. 47 Jesus saw Nathanael coming to him, and says of him, Behold one truly an Israelite, in whom there is no guile. 48 Nathanael says to him, Whence knowest thou me? Jesus answered and said to him, Before that Philip called thee, when thou wast under the fig-tree, I saw thee. 49 Nathanael answered and said to him, Rabbi, thou art the Son of God, thou art the King of Israel. 50 Jesus answered and said to him, Because I said to thee, I saw thee under the fig-tree, believest thou? Thou shalt see greater things than these. 51 And he says to him, Verily, verily, I say to you, Henceforth ye shall see the heaven opened, and the angels of God ascending and descending on the Son of man.

John 2

1 And on the third day a marriage took place in Cana of Galilee, and the mother of Jesus was there. 2 And Jesus also, and his disciples, were invited to the marriage. 3 And wine being deficient, the mother of Jesus says to him, They have no wine. 4 Jesus says to her, What have I to do with thee, woman? mine hour has not yet come. 5 His mother says to the servants, Whatever he may say to you, do. 6 Now there were standing there six stone water-vessels, according to the purification of the Jews, holding two or three measures each. 7 Jesus says to them, Fill the water-vessels with water. And they filled them up to the brim. 8 And he says to them, Draw out now, and carry it to the feast-master. And they carried it. 9 But when the feast-master had tasted the water which had been made wine (and knew not whence it was, but the servants knew who drew the water), the feast-master calls the bridegroom, 10 and says to him, Every man sets on first the good wine, and when men have well drunk, then the inferior; thou hast kept the good wine till now. 11 This beginning of signs did Jesus in Cana of Galilee, and manifested his glory; and his disciples believed on him.

12 After this he descended to Capernaum, he and his mother and his brethren and his disciples; and there they abode not many days. 13 And the passover of the Jews was near, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. 14 And he found in the temple the sellers of oxen and sheep and doves, and the money-changers sitting; 15 and, having made a scourge of cords, he cast them all out of the temple, both the sheep and the oxen; and he poured out the change of the money-changers, and overturned the tables, 16 and said to the sellers of doves, Take these things hence; make not my Father's house a house of merchandise. 17 And his disciples remembered that it is written, The zeal of thy house devours me. 18 The Jews therefore answered and said to him, What sign shewest thou to us, that thou doest these things? 19 Jesus answered and said to them, Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up. 20 The Jews therefore said, Forty and six years was this temple building, and thou wilt raise it up in three days? 21 But he spoke of the temple of his body. 22 When therefore he was raised from among the dead, his disciples remembered that he had said this, and believed the scripture and the word which Jesus had spoken.

23 And when he was in Jerusalem, at the passover, at the feast, many believed on his name, beholding his signs which he wrought. 24 But Jesus himself did not trust himself to them, because he knew all men, 25 and that he had not need that any should testify of man, for himself knew what was in man.

John 3

1 But there was a man from among the Pharisees, his name Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews; 2 he came to him by night, and said to him, Rabbi, we know that thou art come a teacher from God, for none can do these signs that thou doest unless God be with him. 3 Jesus answered and said to him, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except any one be born anew he cannot see the kingdom of God. 4 Nicodemus says to him, How can a man be born being old? can he enter a second time into the womb of his mother and be born? 5 Jesus answered, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except any one be born of water and of Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God. 6 That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is born of the Spirit is spirit. 7 Do not wonder that I said to thee, It is needful that ye should be born anew. 8 The wind blows where it will, and thou hearest its voice, but knowest not whence it comes and where it goes: thus is every one that is born of the Spirit. 9 Nicodemus answered and said to him, How can these things be? 10 Jesus answered and said to him, Thou art the teacher of Israel and knowest not these things! 11 Verily, verily, I say unto thee, We speak that which we know, and we bear witness of that which we have seen, and ye receive not our witness. 12 If I have said the earthly things to you, and ye believe not, how, if I say the heavenly things to you, will ye believe? 13 And no one has gone up into heaven, save he who came down out of heaven, the Son of man who is in heaven. 14 And as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, thus must the Son of man be lifted up, 15 that every one who believes on him may not perish, but have life eternal. 16 For God so loved the world, that he gave his only-begotten Son, that whosoever believes on him may not perish, but have life eternal. 17 For God has not sent his Son into the world that he may judge the world, but that the world may be saved through him. 18 He that believes on him is not judged: but he that believes not has been already judged, because he has not believed on the name of the only-begotten Son of God. 19 And this is the judgment, that light is come into the world, and men have loved darkness rather than light; for their works were evil. 20 For every one that does evil hates the light, and does not come to the light that his works may not be shewn as they are; 21 but he that practises the truth comes to the light, that his works may be manifested that they have been wrought in God.

22 After these things came Jesus and his disciples into the land of Judaea; and there he abode with them and baptised. 23 And John also was baptising in Aenon, near Salim, because there was a great deal of water there; and they came to him and were baptised: 24 for John was not yet cast into prison. 25 There was therefore a reasoning of the disciples of John with a Jew about purification. 26 And they came to John and said to him, Rabbi, he who was with thee beyond the Jordan, to whom thou barest witness, behold, he baptises, and all come to him. 27 John answered and said, A man can receive nothing unless it be given him out of heaven. 28 Ye yourselves bear me witness that I said, I am not the Christ, but, that I am sent before him. 29 He that has the bride is the bridegroom; but the friend of the bridegroom, who stands and hears him, rejoices in heart because of the voice of the bridegroom: this my joy then is fulfilled. 30 He must increase, but I must decrease. 31 He who comes from above is above all. He who has his origin in the earth is of the earth, and speaks as of the earth. He who comes out of heaven is above all, 32 and what he has seen and has heard, this he testifies; and no one receives his testimony. 33 He that has received his testimony has set to his seal that God is true; 34 for he whom God has sent speaks the words of God, for God gives not the Spirit by measure. 35 The Father loves the Son, and has given all things to be in his hand. 36 He that believes on the Son has life eternal, and he that is not subject to the Son shall not see life, but the wrath of God abides upon him.

John 4

1 When therefore the Lord knew that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus makes and baptises more disciples than John 2 (however, Jesus himself did not baptise, but his disciples), 3 he left Judaea and went away again unto Galilee.

4 And he must needs pass through Samaria. 5 He comes therefore to a city of Samaria called Sychar, near to the land which Jacob gave to his son Joseph. 6 Now a fountain of Jacob's was there; Jesus therefore, being wearied with the way he had come, sat just as he was at the fountain. It was about the sixth hour. 7 A woman comes out of Samaria to draw water. Jesus says to her, Give me to drink 8 (for his disciples had gone away into the city that they might buy provisions). 9 The Samaritan woman therefore says to him, How dost thou, being a Jew, ask to drink of me who am a Samaritan woman? for Jews have no intercourse with Samaritans. 10 Jesus answered and said to her, If thou knewest the gift of God, and who it is that says to thee, Give me to drink, thou wouldest have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water. 11 The woman says to him, Sir, thou hast nothing to draw with, and the well is deep: whence then hast thou the living water? 12 Art thou greater than our father Jacob, who gave us the well, and drank of it himself, and his sons, and his cattle? 13 Jesus answered and said to her, Every one who drinks of this water shall thirst again; 14 but whosoever drinks of the water which I shall give him shall never thirst for ever, but the water which I shall give him shall become in him a fountain of water, springing up into eternal life. 15 The woman says to him, Sir, give me this water, that I may not thirst nor come here to draw. 16 Jesus says to her, Go, call thy husband, and come here. 17 The woman answered and said, I have not a husband. Jesus says to her, Thou hast well said, I have not a husband; 18 for thou hast had five husbands, and he whom now thou hast is not thy husband: this thou hast spoken truly. 19 The woman says to him, Sir, I see that thou art a prophet. 20 Our fathers worshipped in this mountain, and ye say that in Jerusalem is the place where one must worship. 21 Jesus says to her, Woman, believe me, the hour is coming when ye shall neither in this mountain nor in Jerusalem worship the Father. 22 Ye worship ye know not what; we worship what we know, for salvation is of the Jews. 23 But the hour is coming and now is, when the true worshippers shall worship the Father in spirit and truth; for also the Father seeks such as his worshippers. 24 God is a spirit; and they who worship him must worship him in spirit and truth. 25 The woman says to him, I know that Messias is coming, who is called Christ; when he comes he will tell us all things. 26 Jesus says to her, I who speak to thee am he.

27 And upon this came his disciples, and wondered that he spoke with a woman; yet no one said, What seekest thou? or, Why speakest thou with her? 28 The woman then left her waterpot and went away into the city, and says to the men, 29 Come, see a man who told me all things I had ever done: is not he the Christ? 30 They went out of the city and came to him. 31 But meanwhile the disciples asked him saying, Rabbi, eat. 32 But he said to them, I have food to eat which ye do not know. 33 The disciples therefore said to one another, Has any one brought him anything to eat? 34 Jesus says to them, My food is that I should do the will of him that has sent me, and that I should finish his work. 35 Do not ye say, that there are yet four months and the harvest comes? Behold, I say to you, Lift up your eyes and behold the fields, for they are already white to harvest. 36 He that reaps receives wages and gathers fruit unto life eternal, that both he that sows and he that reaps may rejoice together. 37 For in this is verified the true saying, It is one who sows and another who reaps. 38 I have sent you to reap that on which ye have not laboured; others have laboured, and ye have entered into their labours. 39 But many of the Samaritans of that city believed on him because of the word of the woman who bore witness, He told me all things that I had ever done. 40 When therefore the Samaritans came to him they asked him to abide with them, and he abode there two days. 41 And more a great deal believed on account of his word; 42 and they said to the woman, It is no longer on account of thy saying that we believe, for we have heard him ourselves, and we know that this is indeed the Saviour of the world.

43 But after the two days he went forth thence and went away into Galilee, 44 for Jesus himself bore witness that a prophet has no honour in his own country. 45 When therefore he came into Galilee, the Galileans received him, having seen all that he had done in Jerusalem during the feast, for they also went to the feast. 46 He came therefore again to Cana of Galilee, where he made the water wine. And there was a certain courtier in Capernaum whose son was sick. 47 He, having heard that Jesus had come out of Judaea into Galilee, went to him and asked him that he would come down and heal his son, for he was about to die. 48 Jesus therefore said to him, Unless ye see signs and wonders ye will not believe. 49 The courtier says to him, Sir, come down ere my child die. 50 Jesus says to him, Go, thy son lives. And the man believed the word which Jesus said to him, and went his way. 51 But already, as he was going down, his servants met him and brought him word saying, Thy child lives. 52 He inquired therefore from them the hour at which he got better. And they said to him, Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him. 53 The father therefore knew that it was in that hour in which Jesus said to him, Thy son lives; and he believed, himself and his whole house. 54 This second sign again did Jesus, being come out of Judaea into Galilee.

John 5

1 After these things was a feast of the Jews, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. 2 Now there is in Jerusalem, at the sheepgate, a pool, which is called in Hebrew, Bethesda, having five porches. 3 In these lay a multitude of sick, blind, lame, withered, awaiting the moving of the water. 4 For an angel descended at a certain season in the pool and troubled the water. Whoever therefore first went in after the troubling of the water became well, whatever disease he laboured under. 5 But there was a certain man there who had been suffering under his infirmity thirty and eight years. 6 Jesus seeing this man lying there, and knowing that he was in that state now a great length of time, says to him, Wouldest thou become well? 7 The infirm man answered him, Sir, I have not a man, in order, when the water has been troubled, to cast me into the pool; but while I am coming another descends before me. 8 Jesus says to him, Arise, take up thy couch and walk. 9 And immediately the man became well, and took up his couch and walked: and on that day was sabbath. 10 The Jews therefore said to the healed man, It is sabbath, it is not permitted thee to take up thy couch. 11 He answered them, He that made me well, he said to me, Take up thy couch and walk. 12 They asked him therefore, Who is the man who said to thee, Take up thy couch and walk? 13 But he that had been healed knew not who it was, for Jesus had slidden away, there being a crowd in the place. 14 After these things Jesus finds him in the temple, and said to him, Behold, thou art become well: sin no more, that something worse do not happen to thee. 15 The man went away and told the Jews that it was Jesus who had made him well. 16 And for this the Jews persecuted Jesus and sought to kill him, because he had done these things on sabbath.

17 But Jesus answered them, My Father worketh hitherto and I work. 18 For this therefore the Jews sought the more to kill him, because he had not only violated the sabbath, but also said that God was his own Father, making himself equal with God. 19 Jesus therefore answered and said to them, Verily, verily, I say to you, The Son can do nothing of himself save whatever he sees the Father doing: for whatever things he does, these things also the Son does in like manner. 20 For the Father loves the Son and shews him all things which he himself does; and he will shew him greater works than these, that ye may wonder. 21 For even as the Father raises the dead and quickens them, thus the Son also quickens whom he will: 22 for neither does the Father judge any one, but has given all judgment to the Son; 23 that all may honour the Son, even as they honour the Father. He who honours not the Son, honours not the Father who has sent him. 24 Verily, verily, I say unto you, that he that hears my word, and believes him that has sent me, has life eternal, and does not come into judgment, but is passed out of death into life. 25 Verily, verily, I say unto you, that an hour is coming, and now is, when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God, and they that have heard shall live. 26 For even as the Father has life in himself, so he has given to the Son also to have life in himself, 27 and has given him authority to execute judgment also, because he is Son of man. 28 Wonder not at this, for an hour is coming in which all who are in the tombs shall hear his voice, 29 and shall go forth; those that have practised good, to resurrection of life, and those that have done evil, to resurrection of judgment. 30 I cannot do anything of myself; as I hear, I judge, and my judgment is righteous, because I do not seek my will, but the will of him that has sent me.

31 If I bear witness concerning myself, my witness is not true. 32 It is another who bears witness concerning me, and I know that the witness which he bears concerning me is true. 33 Ye have sent unto John, and he has borne witness to the truth. 34 But I do not receive witness from man, but I say this that ye might be saved. 35 He was the burning and shining lamp, and ye were willing for a season to rejoice in his light. 36 But I have the witness that is greater than that of John; for the works which the Father has given me that I should complete them, the works themselves which I do, bear witness concerning me that the Father has sent me. 37 And the Father who has sent me himself has borne witness concerning me. Ye have neither heard his voice at any time, nor have seen his shape, 38 and ye have not his word abiding in you; for whom he hath sent, him ye do not believe. 39 Ye search the scriptures, for ye think that in them ye have life eternal, and they it is which bear witness concerning me; 40 and ye will not come to me that ye might have life. 41 I do not receive glory from men, 42 but I know you, that ye have not the love of God in you. 43 I am come in my Father's name, and ye receive me not; if another come in his own name, him ye will receive. 44 How can ye believe, who receive glory one of another, and seek not the glory which comes from God alone? 45 Think not that I will accuse you to the Father: there is one who accuses you, Moses, on whom ye trust; 46 for if ye had believed Moses, ye would have believed me, for he wrote of me. 47 But if ye do not believe his writings, how shall ye believe my words?

John 6

1 After these things Jesus went away beyond the sea of Galilee, or of Tiberias, 2 and a great crowd followed him, because they saw the signs which he wrought upon the sick. 3 And Jesus went up into the mountain, and there sat with his disciples: 4 but the passover, the feast of the Jews, was near. 5 Jesus then, lifting up his eyes and seeing that a great crowd is coming to him, says to Philip, Whence shall we buy loaves that these may eat? 6 But this he said trying him, for he knew what he was going to do. 7 Philip answered him, Loaves for two hundred denarii are not sufficient for them, that each may have some little portion. 8 One of his disciples, Andrew, Simon Peter's brother, says to him, 9 There is a little boy here who has five barley loaves and two small fishes; but this, what is it for so many? 10 And Jesus said, Make the men sit down. Now there was much grass in the place: the men therefore sat down, in number about five thousand. 11 And Jesus took the loaves, and having given thanks, distributed them to those that were set down; and in like manner of the small fishes as much as they would. 12 And when they had been filled, he says to his disciples, Gather together the fragments which are over and above, that nothing may be lost. 13 They gathered them therefore together, and filled twelve hand-baskets full of fragments of the five barley loaves, which were over and above to those that had eaten. 14 The men therefore, having seen the sign which Jesus had done, said, This is truly the prophet which is coming into the world.

15 Jesus therefore knowing that they were going to come and seize him, that they might make him king, departed again to the mountain himself alone. 16 But when evening was come, his disciples went down to the sea, 17 and having gone on board ship, they went over the sea to Capernaum. And it had already become dark, and Jesus had not come to them, 18 and the sea was agitated by a strong wind blowing. 19 Having rowed then about twenty-five or thirty stadia, they see Jesus walking on the sea and coming near the ship; and they were frightened. 20 But he says to them, It is I: be not afraid. 21 They were willing therefore to receive him into the ship; and immediately the ship was at the land to which they went.

22 On the morrow the crowd which stood on the other side of the sea, having seen that there was no other little ship there except that into which his disciples had got, and that Jesus had not gone with his disciples into the ship, but that his disciples had gone away alone; 23 (but other little ships out of Tiberias came near to the place where they ate bread after the Lord had given thanks;) 24 when therefore the crowd saw that Jesus was not there, nor his disciples, they got into the ships, and came to Capernaum, seeking Jesus. 25 And having found him the other side of the sea, they said to him, Rabbi, when art thou arrived here? 26 Jesus answered them and said, Verily, verily, I say to you, Ye seek me not because ye have seen signs, but because ye have eaten of the loaves and been filled. 27 Work not for the food which perishes, but for the food which abides unto life eternal, which the Son of man shall give to you; for him has the Father sealed, even God.

28 They said therefore to him, What should we do that we may work the works of God? 29 Jesus answered and said to them, This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he has sent. 30 They said therefore to him, What sign then doest thou that we may see and believe thee? what dost thou work? 31 Our fathers ate the manna in the wilderness, as it is written, He gave them bread out of heaven to eat. 32 Jesus therefore said to them, Verily, verily, I say to you, It is not Moses that has given you the bread out of heaven; but my Father gives you the true bread out of heaven. 33 For the bread of God is he who comes down out of heaven and gives life to the world. 34 They said therefore to him, Lord, ever give to us this bread. 35 And Jesus said to them, I am the bread of life: he that comes to me shall never hunger, and he that believes on me shall never thirst at any time. 36 But I have said to you, that ye have also seen me and do not believe. 37 All that the Father gives me shall come to me, and him that comes to me I will not at all cast out. 38 For I am come down from heaven, not that I should do my will, but the will of him that has sent me. 39 And this is the will of him that has sent me, that of all that he has given me I should lose nothing, but should raise it up in the last day. 40 For this is the will of my Father, that every one who sees the Son, and believes on him, should have life eternal; and I will raise him up at the last day. 41 The Jews therefore murmured about him, because he said, I am the bread which has come down out of heaven. 42 And they said, Is not this Jesus the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we have known? how then does he say, I am come down out of heaven? 43 Jesus therefore answered and said to them, Murmur not among yourselves. 44 No one can come to me except the Father who has sent me draw him, and I will raise him up in the last day. 45 It is written in the prophets, And they shall be all taught of God. Every one that has heard from the Father himself, and has learned of him, comes to me; 46 not that any one has seen the Father, except he who is of God, he has seen the Father. 47 Verily, verily, I say to you, He that believes on me has life eternal. 48 I am the bread of life. 49 Your fathers ate the manna in the wilderness and died. 50 This is the bread which comes down out of heaven, that one may eat of it and not die. 51 I am the living bread which has come down out of heaven: if any one shall have eaten of this bread he shall live for ever; but the bread withal which I shall give is my flesh, which I will give for the life of the world. 52 The Jews therefore contended among themselves, saying, How can he give us this flesh to eat? 53 Jesus therefore said to them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Unless ye shall have eaten the flesh of the Son of man, and drunk his blood, ye have no life in yourselves. 54 He that eats my flesh and drinks my blood has life eternal, and I will raise him up at the last day: 55 for my flesh is truly food and my blood is truly drink. 56 He that eats my flesh and drinks my blood dwells in me and I in him. 57 As the living Father has sent me and I live on account of the Father, he also who eats me shall live also on account of me. 58 This is the bread which has come down out of heaven. Not as the fathers ate and died: he that eats this bread shall live for ever. 59 These things he said in the synagogue, teaching in Capernaum.

60 Many therefore of his disciples having heard it said, This word is hard; who can hear it? 61 But Jesus, knowing in himself that his disciples murmur concerning this, said to them, Does this offend you? 62 If then ye see the Son of man ascending up where he was before? 63 It is the Spirit which quickens, the flesh profits nothing: the words which I have spoken unto you are spirit and are life. 64 But there are some of you who do not believe. For Jesus knew from the beginning who they were who did not believe, and who would deliver him up. 65 And he said, Therefore said I unto you, that no one can come to me unless it be given to him from the Father. 66 From that time many of his disciples went away back and walked no more with him. 67 Jesus therefore said to the twelve, Will ye also go away? 68 Simon Peter answered him, Lord, to whom shall we go? thou hast words of life eternal; 69 and we have believed and known that thou art the holy one of God. 70 Jesus answered them, Have not I chosen you the twelve? and of you one is a devil. 71 Now he spoke of Judas the son of Simon, Iscariote, for he it was who should deliver him up, being one of the twelve.

John 7

1 And after these things Jesus walked in Galilee, for he would not walk in Judaea, because the Jews sought to kill him. 2 Now the tabernacles, the feast of the Jews, was near. 3 His brethren therefore said to him, Remove hence and go into Judaea, that thy disciples also may see thy works which thou doest; 4 for no one does anything in secret and himself seeks to be known in public. If thou doest these things, manifest thyself to the world: 5 for neither did his brethren believe on him. 6 Jesus therefore says to them, My time is not yet come, but your time is always ready. 7 The world cannot hate you, but me it hates, because I bear witness concerning it that its works are evil. 8 Ye, go ye up to this feast. I go not up to this feast, for my time is not yet fulfilled. 9 Having said these things to them he abode in Galilee. 10 But when his brethren had gone up, then he himself also went up to the feast, not openly, but as in secret. 11 The Jews therefore sought him at the feast, and said, Where is he? 12 And there was much murmuring concerning him among the crowds. Some said, He is a good man; others said, No; but he deceives the crowd. 13 However, no one spoke openly concerning him on account of their fear of the Jews.

14 But when it was now the middle of the feast, Jesus went up into the temple and taught. 15 The Jews therefore wondered, saying, How knows this man letters, having never learned? 16 Jesus therefore answered them and said, My doctrine is not mine, but that of him that has sent me. 17 If any one desire to practise his will, he shall know concerning the doctrine, whether it is of God, or that I speak from myself. 18 He that speaks from himself seeks his own glory; but he that seeks the glory of him that has sent him, he is true, and unrighteousness is not in him. 19 Has not Moses given you the law, and no one of you practises the law? Why do ye seek to kill me? 20 The crowd answered and said, Thou hast a demon: who seeks to kill thee? 21 Jesus answered and said to them, I have done one work, and ye all wonder. 22 Therefore Moses gave you circumcision (not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers), and ye circumcise a man on sabbath. 23 If a man receives circumcision on sabbath, that the law of Moses may not be violated, are ye angry with me because I have made a man entirely sound on sabbath? 24 Judge not according to sight, but judge righteous judgment. 25 Some therefore of those of Jerusalem said, Is not this he whom they seek to kill? 26 and behold, he speaks openly, and they say nothing to him. Have the rulers then indeed recognised that this is the Christ? 27 But as to this man we know whence he is. Now as to the Christ, when he comes, no one knows whence he is. 28 Jesus therefore cried out in the temple, teaching and saying, Ye both know me and ye know whence I am; and I am not come of myself, but he that sent me is true, whom ye do not know. 29 I know him, because I am from him, and he has sent me. 30 They sought therefore to take him; and no one laid his hand upon him, because his hour had not yet come. 31 But many of the crowd believed on him, and said, Will the Christ, when he comes, do more signs than those which this man has done? 32 The Pharisees heard the crowd murmuring these things concerning him, and the Pharisees and the chief priests sent officers that they might take him. 33 Jesus therefore said, Yet a little while I am with you, and I go to him that has sent me. 34 Ye shall seek me and shall not find me, and where I am ye cannot come. 35 The Jews therefore said to one another, Where is he about to go that we shall not find him? Is he about to go to the dispersion among the Greeks, and teach the Greeks? 36 What word is this which he said, Ye shall seek me and shall not find me; and where I am ye cannot come?

37 In the last, the great day of the feast, Jesus stood and cried saying, If any one thirst, let him come to me and drink. 38 He that believes on me, as the scripture has said, out of his belly shall flow rivers of living water. 39 But this he said concerning the Spirit, which they that believed on him were about to receive; for the Spirit was not yet, because Jesus had not yet been glorified. 40 Some out of the crowd therefore, having heard this word, said, This is truly the prophet. 41 Others said, This is the Christ. Others said, Does then the Christ come out of Galilee? 42 Has not the scripture said that the Christ comes of the seed of David, and from the village of Bethlehem, where David was? 43 There was a division therefore in the crowd on account of him. 44 But some of them desired to take him, but no one laid hands upon him.

45 The officers therefore came to the chief priests and Pharisees, and they said to them, Why have ye not brought him? 46 The officers answered, Never man spoke thus, as this man speaks. 47 The Pharisees therefore answered them, Are ye also deceived? 48 Has any one of the rulers believed on him, or of the Pharisees? 49 But this crowd, which does not know the law, are accursed. 50 Nicodemus says to them (being one of themselves), 51 Does our law judge a man before it have first heard from himself, and know what he does? 52 They answered and said to him, Art thou also of Galilee? Search and look, that no prophet arises out of Galilee. 53 And every one went to his home.

John 8

1 But Jesus went to the mount of Olives. 2 And early in the morning he came again into the temple, and all the people came to him; and he sat down and taught them. 3 And the scribes and the Pharisees bring to him a woman taken in adultery, and having set her in the midst, 4 they say to him, Teacher, this woman has been taken in the very act, committing adultery. 5 Now in the law Moses has commanded us to stone such; thou therefore, what sayest thou? 6 But this they said proving him, that they might have something to accuse him of. But Jesus, having stooped down, wrote with his finger on the ground. 7 But when they continued asking him, he lifted himself up and said to them, Let him that is without sin among you first cast the stone at her. 8 And again stooping down he wrote on the ground. 9 But they, having heard that, went out one by one beginning from the elder ones until the last; and Jesus was left alone and the woman standing there. 10 And Jesus, lifting himself up and seeing no one but the woman, said to her, Woman, where are those thine accusers? Has no one condemned thee? 11 And she said, No one, sir. And Jesus said to her, Neither do I condemn thee: go, and sin no more.

12 Again therefore Jesus spoke to them, saying, I am the light of the world; he that follows me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life. 13 The Pharisees therefore said to him, Thou bearest witness concerning thyself; thy witness is not true. 14 Jesus answered and said to them, Even if I bear witness concerning myself, my witness is true, because I know whence I came and whither I go: but ye know not whence I come and whither I go. 15 Ye judge according to the flesh, I judge no one. 16 And if also I judge, my judgment is true, because I am not alone, but I and the Father who has sent me. 17 And in your law too it is written that the testimony of two men is true: 18 I am one who bear witness concerning myself, and the Father who has sent me bears witness concerning me. 19 They said to him therefore, Where is thy Father? Jesus answered, Ye know neither me nor my Father. If ye had known me, ye would have known also my Father. 20 These words spoke he in the treasury, teaching in the temple; and no one took him, for his hour was not yet come.

21 He said therefore again to them, I go away, and ye shall seek me, and shall die in your sin; where I go ye cannot come. 22 The Jews therefore said, Will he kill himself, that he says, Where I go ye cannot come? 23 And he said to them, Ye are from beneath; I am from above. Ye are of this world; I am not of this world. 24 I said therefore to you, that ye shall die in your sins; for unless ye shall believe that I am he, ye shall die in your sins. 25 They said therefore to him, Who art thou? And Jesus said to them, Altogether that which I also say to you. 26 I have many things to say and to judge concerning you, but he that has sent me is true, and I, what I have heard from him, these things I say to the world. 27 They knew not that he spoke to them of the Father. 28 Jesus therefore said to them, When ye shall have lifted up the Son of man, then ye shall know that I am he, and that I do nothing of myself, but as the Father has taught me I speak these things. 29 And he that has sent me is with me; he has not left me alone, because I do always the things that are pleasing to him. 30 As he spoke these things many believed on him.

31 Jesus therefore said to the Jews who believed him, If ye abide in my word, ye are truly my disciples; 32 and ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall set you free. 33 They answered him, We are Abraham's seed, and have never been under bondage to any one; how sayest thou, Ye shall become free? 34 Jesus answered them, Verily, verily, I say to you, Every one that practises sin is the bondman of sin. 35 Now the bondman abides not in the house for ever: the son abides for ever. 36 If therefore the Son shall set you free, ye shall be really free. 37 I know that ye are Abraham's seed; but ye seek to kill me, because my word has no entrance in you.

38 I speak what I have seen with my Father, and ye then do what ye have seen with your father. 39 They answered and said to him, Abraham is our father. Jesus says to them, If ye were Abraham's children, ye would do the works of Abraham; 40 but now ye seek to kill me, a man who has spoken the truth to you, which I have heard from God: this did not Abraham. 41 Ye do the works of your father. They said therefore to him, We are not born of fornication; we have one father, God. 42 Jesus said to them, If God were your father ye would have loved me, for I came forth from God and am come from him; for neither am I come of myself, but he has sent me. 43 Why do ye not know my speech? Because ye cannot hear my word. 44 Ye are of the devil, as your father, and ye desire to do the lusts of your father. He was a murderer from the beginning, and has not stood in the truth, because there is no truth in him. When he speaks falsehood, he speaks of what is his own; for he is a liar and its father: 45 and because I speak the truth, ye do not believe me.

46 Which of you convinces me of sin? If I speak truth, why do ye not believe me? 47 He that is of God hears the words of God: therefore ye hear them not, because ye are not of God. 48 The Jews answered and said to him, Say we not well that thou art a Samaritan and hast a demon? 49 Jesus answered, I have not a demon; but I honour my Father, and ye dishonour me. 50 But I do not seek my own glory: there is he that seeks and judges.

51 Verily, verily, I say unto you, If any one shall keep my word, he shall never see death. 52 The Jews therefore said to him, Now we know that thou hast a demon. Abraham has died, and the prophets, and thou sayest, If any one keep my word, he shall never taste death. 53 Art thou greater than our father Abraham, who has died? and the prophets have died: whom makest thou thyself? 54 Jesus answered, If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing: it is my Father who glorifies me, of whom ye say, He is our God. 55 And ye know him not; but I know him; and if I said, I know him not, I should be like you, a liar. But I know him, and I keep his word. 56 Your father Abraham exulted in that he should see my day, and he saw and rejoiced. 57 The Jews therefore said to him, Thou hast not yet fifty years, and hast thou seen Abraham? 58 Jesus said to them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Before Abraham was, I am. 59 They took up therefore stones that they might cast them at him; but Jesus hid himself and went out of the temple, going through the midst of them, and thus passed on.

John 9

1 And as he passed on, he saw a man blind from birth. 2 And his disciples asked him, saying, Rabbi, who sinned, this man or his parents, that he should be born blind? 3 Jesus answered, Neither has this man sinned nor his parents, but that the works of God should be manifested in him. 4 I must work the works of him that has sent me while it is day. The night is coming, when no one can work. 5 As long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world. 6 Having said these things, he spat on the ground and made mud of the spittle, and put the mud, as ointment, on his eyes. 7 And he said to him, Go, wash in the pool of Siloam, which is interpreted, Sent. He went therefore and washed, and came seeing.

8 The neighbours therefore, and those who used to see him before, that he was a beggar, said, Is not this he that was sitting and begging? 9 Some said, It is he; others said, No, but he is like him: he said, It is I. 10 They said therefore to him, How have thine eyes been opened? 11 He answered and said, A man called Jesus made mud and anointed mine eyes, and said to me, Go to Siloam and wash: and having gone and washed, I saw. 12 They said therefore to him, Where is he? He says, I do not know.

13 They bring him who was before blind to the Pharisees. 14 Now it was sabbath when Jesus made the mud and opened his eyes. 15 The Pharisees therefore also again asked him how he received his sight. And he said to them, He put mud upon mine eyes, and I washed, and I see. 16 Some of the Pharisees therefore said, This man is not of God, for he does not keep the sabbath. Others said, How can a sinful man perform such signs? And there was a division among them. 17 They say therefore again to the blind man, What dost thou say of him, that he has opened thine eyes? And he said, He is a prophet. 18 The Jews therefore did not believe concerning him that he was blind and had received sight, until they had called the parents of him that had received sight. 19 And they asked them saying, This is your son, of whom ye say that he was born blind: how then does he now see? 20 His parents answered them and said, We know that this is our son, and that he was born blind; 21 but how he now sees we do not know, or who has opened his eyes we do not know. He is of age: ask him; he will speak concerning himself. 22 His parents said these things because they feared the Jews, for the Jews had already agreed that if any one confessed him to be the Christ, he should be excommunicated from the synagogue. 23 On this account his parents said, He is of age: ask him. 24 They called therefore a second time the man who had been blind, and said to him, Give glory to God: we know that this man is sinful. 25 He answered therefore, If he is sinful I know not. One thing I know, that, being blind before, now I see. 26 And they said to him again, What did he do to thee? how opened he thine eyes? 27 He answered them, I told you already and ye did not hear: why do ye desire to hear again? do ye also wish to become his disciples? 28 They railed at him, and said, Thou art his disciple, but we are disciples of Moses. 29 We know that God spoke to Moses; but as to this man, we know not whence he is. 30 The man answered and said to them, Now in this is a wonderful thing, that ye do not know whence he is, and he has opened mine eyes. 31 But we know that God does not hear sinners; but if any one be God-fearing and do his will, him he hears. 32 Since time was, it has not been heard that any one opened the eyes of one born blind. 33 If this man were not of God he would be able to do nothing. 34 They answered and said to him, Thou hast been wholly born in sins, and thou teachest us? And they cast him out.

35 Jesus heard that they had cast him out, and having found him, he said to him, Thou, dost thou believe on the Son of God? 36 He answered and said, And who is he, Lord, that I may believe on him? 37 And Jesus said to him, Thou hast both seen him, and he that speaks with thee is he. 38 And he said, I believe, Lord: and he did him homage.

39 And Jesus said, For judgment am I come into this world, that they which see not may see, and they which see may become blind. 40 And some of the Pharisees who were with him heard these things, and they said to him, Are we blind also? 41 Jesus said to them, If ye were blind ye would not have sin; but now ye say, We see, your sin remains.

John 10

1 Verily, verily, I say to you, He that enters not in by the door to the fold of the sheep, but mounts up elsewhere, he is a thief and a robber; 2 but he that enters in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep. 3 To him the porter opens; and the sheep hear his voice; and he calls his own sheep by name, and leads them out. 4 When he has put forth all his own, he goes before them, and the sheep follow him, because they know his voice. 5 But they will not follow a stranger, but will flee from him, because they know not the voice of strangers. 6 This allegory spoke Jesus to them, but they did not know what it was of which he spoke to them. 7 Jesus therefore said again to them, Verily, verily, I say to you, I am the door of the sheep. 8 All whoever came before me are thieves and robbers; but the sheep did not hear them. 9 I am the door: if any one enter in by me, he shall be saved, and shall go in and shall go out and shall find pasture. 10 The thief comes not but that he may steal, and kill, and destroy: I am come that they might have life, and might have it abundantly. 11 I am the good shepherd. The good shepherd lays down his life for the sheep: 12 but he who serves for wages, and who is not the shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, sees the wolf coming, and leaves the sheep and flees; and the wolf seizes them and scatters the sheep. 13 Now he who serves for wages flees because he serves for wages, and is not himself concerned about the sheep. 14 I am the good shepherd; and I know those that are mine, and am known of those that are mine, 15 as the Father knows me and I know the Father; and I lay down my life for the sheep. 16 And I have other sheep which are not of this fold: those also I must bring, and they shall hear my voice; and there shall be one flock, one shepherd. 17 On this account the Father loves me, because I lay down my life that I may take it again. 18 No one takes it from me, but I lay it down of myself. I have authority to lay it down and I have authority to take it again. I have received this commandment of my Father.

19 There was a division again among the Jews on account of these words; 20 but many of them said, He has a demon and raves; why do ye hear him? 21 Others said, These sayings are not those of one that is possessed by a demon. Can a demon open blind people's eyes?

22 Now the feast of the dedication was celebrating at Jerusalem, and it was winter. 23 And Jesus walked in the temple in the porch of Solomon. 24 The Jews therefore surrounded him, and said to him, Until when dost thou hold our soul in suspense? If thou art the Christ, say so to us openly. 25 Jesus answered them, I told you, and ye do not believe. The works which I do in my Father's name, these bear witness concerning me: 26 but ye do not believe, for ye are not of my sheep, as I told you. 27 My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me; 28 and I give them life eternal; and they shall never perish, and no one shall seize them out of my hand. 29 My Father who has given them to me is greater than all, and no one can seize out of the hand of my Father. 30 I and the Father are one. 31 The Jews therefore again took stones that they might stone him. 32 Jesus answered them, Many good works have I shewn you of my Father; for which work of them do ye stone me? 33 The Jews answered him, For a good work we stone thee not, but for blasphemy, and because thou, being a man, makest thyself God. 34 Jesus answered them, Is it not written in your law, I said, Ye are gods? 35 If he called them gods to whom the word of God came (and the scripture cannot be broken), 36 do ye say of him whom the Father has sanctified and sent into the world, Thou blasphemest, because I said, I am Son of God? 37 If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not; 38 but if I do, even if ye believe not me, believe the works, that ye may know and believe that the Father is in me and I in him.

39 They sought therefore again to take him; and he went away from out of their hand 40 and departed again beyond the Jordan to the place where John was baptising at the first: and he abode there. 41 And many came to him, and said, John did no sign; but all things which John said of this man were true. 42 And many believed on him there.

John 11

1 Now there was a certain man sick, Lazarus of Bethany, of the village of Mary and Martha her sister. 2 It was the Mary who anointed the Lord with ointment and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick. 3 The sisters therefore sent to him, saying, Lord, behold, he whom thou lovest is sick. 4 But when Jesus heard it, he said, This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, that the Son of God may be glorified by it. 5 Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus. 6 When therefore he heard, He is sick, he remained two days then in the place where he was. 7 Then after this he says to his disciples, Let us go into Judaea again. 8 The disciples say to him, Rabbi, even but now the Jews sought to stone thee, and goest thou thither again? 9 Jesus answered, Are there not twelve hours in the day? If any one walk in the day, he does not stumble, because he sees the light of this world; 10 but if any one walk in the night, he stumbles, because the light is not in him. 11 These things said he; and after this he says to them, Lazarus, our friend, is fallen asleep, but I go that I may awake him out of sleep. 12 The disciples therefore said to him, Lord, if he be fallen asleep, he will get well. 13 But Jesus spoke of his death, but they thought that he spoke of the rest of sleep. 14 Jesus therefore then said to them plainly, Lazarus has died. 15 And I rejoice on your account that I was not there, in order that ye may believe. But let us go to him. 16 Thomas therefore, called Didymus, said to his fellow disciples, Let us also go, that we may die with him.

17 Jesus therefore on arriving found him to have been four days already in the tomb. 18 Now Bethany was near Jerusalem, about fifteen stadia off, 19 and many of the Jews came to Martha and Mary, that they might console them concerning their brother. 20 Martha then, when she heard Jesus is coming, went to meet him; but Mary sat in the house. 21 Martha therefore said to Jesus, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died; 22 but even now I know, that whatsoever thou shalt ask of God, God will give thee. 23 Jesus says to her, Thy brother shall rise again. 24 Martha says to him, I know that he will rise again in the resurrection in the last day. 25 Jesus said to her, I am the resurrection and the life: he that believes on me, though he have died, shall live; 26 and every one who lives and believes on me shall never die. Believest thou this? 27 She says to him, Yea, Lord; I believe that thou art the Christ, the Son of God, who should come into the world. 28 And having said this, she went away and called her sister Mary secretly, saying, The teacher is come and calls thee. 29 She, when she heard that, rises up quickly and comes to him. 30 Now Jesus had not yet come into the village, but was in the place where Martha came to meet him. 31 The Jews therefore who were with her in the house and consoling her, seeing Mary that she rose up quickly and went out, followed her, saying, She goes to the tomb, that she may weep there. 32 Mary therefore, when she came where Jesus was, seeing him, fell at his feet, saying to him, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died.

33 Jesus therefore, when he saw her weeping, and the Jews who came with her weeping, was deeply moved in spirit, and was troubled, 34 and said, Where have ye put him? They say to him, Lord, come and see. 35 Jesus wept. 36 The Jews therefore said, Behold how he loved him! 37 And some of them said, Could not this man, who has opened the eyes of the blind man, have caused that this man also should not have died? 38 Jesus therefore, again deeply moved in himself, comes to the tomb. Now it was a cave, and a stone lay upon it. 39 Jesus says, Take away the stone. Martha, the sister of the dead, says to him, Lord, he stinks already, for he is four days there. 40 Jesus says to her, Did I not say to thee, that if thou shouldest believe, thou shouldest see the glory of God? 41 They took therefore the stone away. And Jesus lifted up his eyes on high and said, Father, I thank thee that thou hast heard me; 42 but I knew that thou always hearest me; but on account of the crowd who stand around I have said it, that they may believe that thou hast sent me. 43 And having said this, he cried with a loud voice, Lazarus, come forth. 44 And the dead came forth, bound feet and hands with graveclothes, and his face was bound round with a handkerchief. Jesus says to them, Loose him and let him go.

45 Many therefore of the Jews who came to Mary and saw what he had done, believed on him; 46 but some of them went to the Pharisees and told them what Jesus had done. 47 The chief priests, therefore, and the Pharisees gathered a council, and said, What do we? for this man does many signs. 48 If we let him thus alone, all will believe on him, and the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation. 49 But a certain one of them, Caiaphas, being high priest that year, said to them, Ye know nothing 50 nor consider that it is profitable for you that one man die for the people, and not that the whole nation perish. 51 But this he did not say of himself; but, being high priest that year, prophesied that Jesus was going to die for the nation; 52 and not for the nation only, but that he should also gather together into one the children of God who were scattered abroad. 53 From that day therefore they took counsel that they might kill him. 54 Jesus therefore walked no longer openly among the Jews, but went away thence into the country near the desert, to a city called Ephraim, and there he sojourned with the disciples. 55 But the passover of the Jews was near, and many went up to Jerusalem out of the country before the passover, that they might purify themselves. 56 They sought therefore Jesus, and said among themselves, standing in the temple, What do ye think? that he will not come to the feast? 57 Now the chief priests and the Pharisees had given commandment that if any one knew where he was, he should make it known, that they might take him.

John 12

1 Jesus therefore, six days before the passover, came to Bethany, where was the dead man Lazarus, whom Jesus raised from among the dead. 2 There therefore they made him a supper, and Martha served, but Lazarus was one of those at table with him. 3 Mary therefore, having taken a pound of ointment of pure nard of great price, anointed the feet of Jesus, and wiped his feet with her hair, and the house was filled with the odour of the ointment. 4 One of his disciples therefore, Judas son of Simon, Iscariote, who was about to deliver him up, says, 5 Why was this ointment not sold for three hundred denarii and given to the poor? 6 But he said this, not that he cared for the poor, but because he was a thief and had the bag, and carried what was put into it. 7 Jesus therefore said, Suffer her to have kept this for the day of my preparation for burial; 8 for ye have the poor always with you, but me ye have not always. 9 A great crowd therefore of the Jews knew that he was there; and they came, not because of Jesus only, but also that they might see Lazarus whom he raised from among the dead. 10 But the chief priests took counsel that they might kill Lazarus also, 11 because many of the Jews went away on his account and believed on Jesus.

12 On the morrow a great crowd who came to the feast, having heard that Jesus is coming into Jerusalem, 13 took branches of palms and went out to meet him, and cried, Hosanna, blessed is he that comes in the name of the Lord, the King of Israel. 14 And Jesus, having found a young ass, sat upon it; as it is written, 15 Fear not, daughter of Zion: behold, thy King cometh, sitting on an ass's colt. 16 Now his disciples knew not these things at the first; but when Jesus was glorified, then they remembered that these things were written of him, and that they had done these things to him. 17 The crowd therefore that was with him bore witness because he had called Lazarus out of the tomb, and raised him from among the dead. 18 Therefore also the crowd met him because they had heard that he had done this sign. 19 The Pharisees therefore said to one another, Ye see that ye profit nothing: behold, the world is gone after him.

20 And there were certain Greeks among those who came up that they might worship in the feast; 21 these therefore came to Philip, who was of Bethsaida of Galilee, and they asked him saying, Sir, we desire to see Jesus. 22 Philip comes and tells Andrew, and again Andrew comes and Philip, and they tell Jesus. 23 But Jesus answered them saying, The hour is come that the Son of man should be glorified. 24 Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except the grain of wheat falling into the ground die, it abides alone; but if it die, it bears much fruit. 25 He that loves his life shall lose it, and he that hates his life in this world shall keep it to life eternal. 26 If any one serve me, let him follow me; and where I am, there also shall be my servant. And if any one serve me, him shall the Father honour.

27 Now is my soul troubled, and what shall I say? Father, save me from this hour. But on account of this have I come to this hour. 28 Father, glorify thy name. There came therefore a voice out of heaven, I both have glorified and will glorify it again. 29 The crowd therefore, which stood there and heard it, said that it had thundered. Others said, An angel has spoken to him. 30 Jesus answered and said, Not on my account has this voice come, but on yours. 31 Now is the judgment of this world; now shall the prince of this world be cast out: 32 and I, if I be lifted up out of the earth, will draw all to me. 33 But this he said signifying by what death he was about to die. 34 The crowd answered him, We have heard out of the law that the Christ abides for ever; and how sayest thou that the Son of man must be lifted up? Who is this, the Son of man? 35 Jesus therefore said to them, Yet a little while is the light amongst you. Walk while ye have the light, that darkness may not overtake you. And he who walks in the darkness does not know where he goes. 36 While ye have the light, believe in the light, that ye may become sons of light. Jesus said these things, and going away hid himself from them.

37 But though he had done so many signs before them, they believed not on him, 38 that the word of the prophet Esaias which he said might be fulfilled, Lord, who has believed our report? and to whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed? 39 On this account they could not believe, because Esaias said again, 40 He has blinded their eyes and hardened their heart, that they may not see with their eyes, and understand with their heart and be converted, and I should heal them. 41 These things said Esaias because he saw his glory and spoke of him.

42 Although indeed from among the rulers also many believed on him, but on account of the Pharisees did not confess him, that they might not be put out of the synagogue: 43 for they loved glory from men rather than glory from God.

44 But Jesus cried and said, He that believes on me, believes not on me, but on him that sent me; 45 and he that beholds me, beholds him that sent me. 46 I am come into the world as light, that every one that believes on me may not abide in darkness; 47 and if any one hear my words and do not keep them, I judge him not, for I am not come that I might judge the world, but that I might save the world. 48 He that rejects me and does not receive my words, has him who judges him: the word which I have spoken, that shall judge him in the last day. 49 For I have not spoken from myself, but the Father who sent me has himself given me commandment what I should say and what I should speak; 50 and I know that his commandment is life eternal. What therefore I speak, as the Father has said to me, so I speak.

John 13

1 Now before the feast of the passover, Jesus, knowing that his hour had come that he should depart out of this world to the Father, having loved his own who were in the world, loved them to the end. 2 And during supper, the devil having already put it into the heart of Judas son of Simon, Iscariote, that he should deliver him up, 3 Jesus, knowing that the Father had given him all things into his hands, and that he came out from God and was going to God, 4 rises from supper and lays aside his garments, and having taken a linen towel he girded himself: 5 then he pours water into the washhand basin, and began to wash the feet of the disciples, and to wipe them with the linen towel with which he was girded. 6 He comes therefore to Simon Peter; and he says to him, Lord, dost thou wash my feet? 7 Jesus answered and said to him, What I do thou dost not know now, but thou shalt know hereafter. 8 Peter says to him, Thou shalt never wash my feet. Jesus answered him, Unless I wash thee, thou hast not part with me. 9 Simon Peter says to him, Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head. 10 Jesus says to him, He that is washed all over needs not to wash save his feet, but is wholly clean; and ye are clean, but not all. 11 For he knew him that delivered him up: on account of this he said, Ye are not all clean. 12 When therefore he had washed their feet, and taken his garments, having sat down again, he said to them, Do ye know what I have done to you? 13 Ye call me the Teacher and the Lord, and ye say well, for I am so. 14 If I therefore, the Lord and the Teacher, have washed your feet, ye also ought to wash one another's feet; 15 for I have given you an example that, as I have done to you, ye should do also. 16 Verily, verily, I say to you, The bondman is not greater than his lord, nor the sent greater than he who has sent him. 17 If ye know these things, blessed are ye if ye do them.

18 I speak not of you all. I know those whom I have chosen; but that the scripture might be fulfilled, He that eats bread with me has lifted up his heel against me. 19 I tell you it now before it happens, that when it happens, ye may believe that I am he. 20 Verily, verily, I say to you, He who receives whomsoever I shall send receives me; and he that receives me receives him who has sent me. 21 Having said these things, Jesus was troubled in spirit, and testified and said, Verily, verily, I say to you, that one of you shall deliver me up. 22 The disciples therefore looked one on another, doubting of whom he spoke. 23 Now there was at table one of his disciples in the bosom of Jesus, whom Jesus loved. 24 Simon Peter makes a sign therefore to him to ask who it might be of whom he spoke. 25 But he, leaning on the breast of Jesus, says to him, Lord, who is it? 26 Jesus answers, He it is to whom I, after I have dipped the morsel, give it. And having dipped the morsel, he gives it to Judas son of Simon, Iscariote. 27 And, after the morsel, then entered Satan into him. Jesus therefore says to him, What thou doest, do quickly. 28 But none of those at table knew why he said this to him; 29 for some supposed, because Judas had the bag, that Jesus was saying to him, Buy the things of which we have need for the feast; or that he should give something to the poor. 30 Having therefore received the morsel, he went out immediately; and it was night.

31 When therefore he was gone out Jesus says, Now is the Son of man glorified, and God is glorified in him. 32 If God be glorified in him, God also shall glorify him in himself, and shall glorify him immediately. 33 Children, yet a little while I am with you. Ye shall seek me; and, as I said to the Jews, Where I go ye cannot come, I say to you also now. 34 A new commandment I give to you, that ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye also love one another. 35 By this shall all know that ye are disciples of mine, if ye have love amongst yourselves.

36 Simon Peter says to him, Lord, where goest thou? Jesus answered him, Where I go thou canst not follow me now, but thou shalt follow me after. 37 Peter says to him, Lord, why cannot I follow thee now? I will lay down my life for thee. 38 Jesus answers, Thou wilt lay down thy life for me! Verily, verily, I say to thee, The cock shall not crow till thou hast denied me thrice.

John 14

1 Let not your heart be troubled; ye believe on God, believe also on me. 2 In my Father's house there are many abodes; were it not so, I had told you: for I go to prepare you a place; 3 and if I go and shall prepare you a place, I am coming again and shall receive you to myself, that where I am ye also may be.

4 And ye know where I go, and ye know the way. 5 Thomas says to him, Lord, we know not where thou goest, and how can we know the way? 6 Jesus says to him, I am the way, and the truth, and the life. No one comes to the Father unless by me. 7 If ye had known me, ye would have known also my Father, and henceforth ye know him and have seen him. 8 Philip says to him, Lord, shew us the Father and it suffices us. 9 Jesus says to him, Am I so long a time with you, and thou hast not known me, Philip? He that has seen me has seen the Father; and how sayest thou, Shew us the Father? 10 Believest thou not that I am in the Father, and that the Father is in me? The words which I speak to you I do not speak from myself; but the Father who abides in me, he does the works. 11 Believe me that I am in the Father and the Father in me; but if not, believe me for the works' sake themselves.

12 Verily, verily, I say to you, He that believes on me, the works which I do shall he do also, and he shall do greater than these, because I go to the Father. 13 And whatsoever ye shall ask in my name, this will I do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son. 14 If ye shall ask anything in my name, I will do it.

15 If ye love me, keep my commandments. 16 And I will beg the Father, and he will give you another Comforter, that he may be with you for ever, 17 the Spirit of truth, whom the world cannot receive, because it does not see him nor know him; but ye know him, for he abides with you, and shall be in you.

18 I will not leave you orphans, I am coming to you. 19 Yet a little and the world sees me no longer; but ye see me; because I live ye also shall live. 20 In that day ye shall know that I am in my Father, and ye in me, and I in you. 21 He that has my commandments and keeps them, he it is that loves me; but he that loves me shall be loved by my Father, and I will love him and will manifest myself to him. 22 Judas, not the Iscariote, says to him, Lord, how is it that thou wilt manifest thyself to us and not to the world? 23 Jesus answered and said to him, If any one love me, he will keep my word, and my Father will love him, and we will come to him and make our abode with him. 24 He that loves me not does not keep my words; and the word which ye hear is not mine, but that of the Father who has sent me.

25 These things I have said to you, abiding with you; 26 but the Comforter, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and will bring to your remembrance all the things which I have said to you. 27 I leave peace with you; I give my peace to you: not as the world gives do I give to you. Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it fear.

28 Ye have heard that I have said unto you, I go away and I am coming to you. If ye loved me ye would rejoice that I go to the Father, for my Father is greater than I. 29 And now I have told you before it comes to pass, that when it shall have come to pass ye may believe. 30 I will no longer speak much with you, for the ruler of the world comes, and in me he has nothing; 31 but that the world may know that I love the Father, and as the Father has commanded me, thus I do. Rise up, let us go hence.

John 15

1 I am the true vine, and my Father is the husbandman. 2 As to every branch in me not bearing fruit, he takes it away; and as to every one bearing fruit, he purges it that it may bring forth more fruit. 3 Ye are already clean by reason of the word which I have spoken to you. 4 Abide in me and I in you. As the branch cannot bear fruit of itself unless it abide in the vine, thus neither can ye unless ye abide in me. 5 I am the vine, ye are the branches. He that abides in me and I in him, he bears much fruit; for without me ye can do nothing. 6 Unless any one abide in me he is cast out as the branch, and is dried up; and they gather them and cast them into the fire, and they are burned. 7 If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ye shall ask what ye will and it shall come to pass to you. 8 In this is my Father glorified, that ye bear much fruit, and ye shall become disciples of mine.

9 As the Father has loved me, I also have loved you: abide in my love. 10 If ye shall keep my commandments, ye shall abide in my love, as I have kept my Father's commandments and abide in his love. 11 I have spoken these things to you that my joy may be in you, and your joy be full. 12 This is my commandment, that ye love one another, as I have loved you. 13 No one has greater love than this, that one should lay down his life for his friends. 14 Ye are my friends if ye practise whatever I command you. 15 I call you no longer bondmen, for the bondman does not know what his master is doing; but I have called you friends, for all things which I have heard of my Father I have made known to you. 16 Ye have not chosen me, but I have chosen you, and have set you that ye should go and that ye should bear fruit, and that your fruit should abide, that whatsoever ye shall ask the Father in my name he may give you. 17 These things I command you, that ye love one another.

18 If the world hate you, know that it has hated me before you. 19 If ye were of the world, the world would love its own; but because ye are not of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, on account of this the world hates you. 20 Remember the word which I said unto you, The bondman is not greater than his master. If they have persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they have kept my word, they will keep also yours. 21 But they will do all these things to you on account of my name, because they have not known him that sent me. 22 If I had not come and spoken to them, they had not had sin; but now they have no excuse for their sin. 23 He that hates me hates also my Father. 24 If I had not done among them the works which no other one has done, they had not had sin; but now they have both seen and hated both me and my Father. 25 But that the word written in their law might be fulfilled, They hated me without a cause.

26 But when the Comforter is come, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth who goes forth from with the Father, he shall bear witness concerning me; 27 and ye too bear witness, because ye are with me from the beginning.

John 16

1 These things I have spoken unto you that ye may not be offended. 2 They shall put you out of the synagogues; but the hour is coming that every one who kills you will think to render service to God; 3 and these things they will do because they have not known the Father nor me. 4 But I have spoken these things to you, that when their hour shall have come, ye may remember them, that I have said them unto you. But I did not say these things unto you from the beginning, because I was with you. 5 But now I go to him that has sent me, and none of you demands of me, Where goest thou? 6 But because I have spoken these things to you, sorrow has filled your heart.

7 But I say the truth to you, It is profitable for you that I go away; for if I do not go away, the Comforter will not come to you; but if I go I will send him to you. 8 And having come, he will bring demonstration to the world, of sin, and of righteousness, and of judgment: 9 of sin, because they do not believe on me; 10 of righteousness, because I go away to my Father, and ye behold me no longer; 11 of judgment, because the ruler of this world is judged. 12 I have yet many things to say to you, but ye cannot bear them now. 13 But when he is come, the Spirit of truth, he shall guide you into all the truth: for he shall not speak from himself; but whatsoever he shall hear he shall speak; and he will announce to you what is coming. 14 He shall glorify me, for he shall receive of mine and shall announce it to you. 15 All things that the Father has are mine; on account of this I have said that he receives of mine and shall announce it to you.

16 A little while and ye do not behold me; and again a little while and ye shall see me, because I go away to the Father. 17 Some of his disciples therefore said to one another, What is this he says to us, A little while and ye do not behold me; and again a little while and ye shall see me, and, Because I go away to the Father? 18 They said therefore, What is this which he says of the little while? We do not know of what he speaks. 19 Jesus knew therefore that they desired to demand of him, and said to them, Do ye inquire of this among yourselves that I said, A little while and ye do not behold me; and again a little while and ye shall see me? 20 Verily, verily, I say to you, that ye shall weep and lament, ye, but the world shall rejoice; and ye will be grieved, but your grief shall be turned to joy. 21 A woman, when she gives birth to a child, has grief because her hour has come; but when the child is born, she no longer remembers the trouble, on account of the joy that a man has been born into the world. 22 And ye now therefore have grief; but I will see you again, and your heart shall rejoice, and your joy no one takes from you.

23 And in that day ye shall demand nothing of me: verily, verily, I say to you, Whatsoever ye shall ask the Father in my name, he will give you. 24 Hitherto ye have asked nothing in my name: ask, and ye shall receive, that your joy may be full. 25 These things I have spoken to you in allegories; the hour is coming that I will no longer speak to you in allegories, but will declare to you openly concerning the Father. 26 In that day ye shall ask in my name; and I say not to you that I will demand of the Father for you, 27 for the Father himself has affection for you, because ye have had affection for me, and have believed that I came out from God.

28 I came out from the Father and have come into the world; again, I leave the world and go to the Father. 29 His disciples say to him, Lo, now thou speakest openly and utterest no allegory. 30 Now we know that thou knowest all things, and hast not need that any one should demand of thee. By this we believe that thou art come from God. 31 Jesus answered them, Do ye now believe? 32 Behold, the hour is coming, and has come, that ye shall be scattered, each to his own, and shall leave me alone; and yet I am not alone, for the Father is with me. 33 These things have I spoken to you that in me ye might have peace. In the world ye have tribulation; but be of good courage: I have overcome the world.

John 17

1 These things Jesus spoke, and lifted up his eyes to heaven and said, Father, the hour is come; glorify thy Son, that thy Son may glorify thee; 2 as thou hast given him authority over all flesh, that as to all that thou hast given to him, he should give them life eternal. 3 And this is the eternal life, that they should know thee, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent. 4 I have glorified thee on the earth, I have completed the work which thou gavest me that I should do it; 5 and now glorify me, thou Father, along with thyself, with the glory which I had along with thee before the world was.

6 I have manifested thy name to the men whom thou gavest me out of the world. They were thine, and thou gavest them me, and they have kept thy word. 7 Now they have known that all things that thou hast given me are of thee; 8 for the words which thou hast given me I have given them, and they have received them, and have known truly that I came out from thee, and have believed that thou sentest me. 9 I demand concerning them; I do not demand concerning the world, but concerning those whom thou hast given me, for they are thine, 10 (and all that is mine is thine, and all that is thine mine,) and I am glorified in them.

11 And I am no longer in the world, and these are in the world, and I come to thee. Holy Father, keep them in thy name which thou hast given me, that they may be one as we. 12 When I was with them I kept them in thy name; those thou hast given me I have guarded, and not one of them has perished, but the son of perdition, that the scripture might be fulfilled. 13 And now I come to thee. And these things I speak in the world, that they may have my joy fulfilled in them. 14 I have given them thy word, and the world has hated them, because they are not of the world, as I am not of the world. 15 I do not demand that thou shouldest take them out of the world, but that thou shouldest keep them out of evil. 16 They are not of the world, as I am not of the world.

17 Sanctify them by the truth: thy word is truth. 18 As thou hast sent me into the world, I also have sent them into the world; 19 and I sanctify myself for them, that they also may be sanctified by truth.

20 And I do not demand for these only, but also for those who believe on me through their word; 21 that they may be all one, as thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be one in us, that the world may believe that thou hast sent me. 22 And the glory which thou hast given me I have given them, that they may be one, as we are one; 23 I in them and thou in me, that they may be perfected into one and that the world may know that thou hast sent me, and that thou hast loved them as thou hast loved me.

24 Father, as to those whom thou hast given me, I desire that where I am they also may be with me, that they may behold my glory which thou hast given me, for thou lovedst me before the foundation of the world. 25 Righteous Father, --and the world has not known thee, but I have known thee, and these have known that thou hast sent me. 26 And I have made known to them thy name, and will make it known; that the love with which thou hast loved me may be in them and I in them.

John 18

1 Jesus, having said these things, went out with his disciples beyond the torrent Cedron, where was a garden, into which he entered, he and his disciples. 2 And Judas also, who delivered him up, knew the place, because Jesus was often there, in company with his disciples. 3 Judas therefore, having got the band, and officers of the chief priests and Pharisees, comes there with lanterns and torches and weapons. 4 Jesus therefore, knowing all things that were coming upon him, went forth and said to them, Whom seek ye? 5 They answered him, Jesus the Nazaraean. Jesus says to them, I am he. And Judas also, who delivered him up, stood with them. 6 When therefore he said to them, I am he, they went away backward and fell to the ground. 7 He demanded of them therefore again, Whom seek ye? And they said, Jesus the Nazaraean. 8 Jesus answered, I told you that I am he: if therefore ye seek me, let these go away; 9 that the word might be fulfilled which he spoke, As to those whom thou hast given me, I have not lost one of them. 10 Simon Peter therefore, having a sword, drew it, and smote the bondman of the high priest and cut off his right ear; and the bondman's name was Malchus. 11 Jesus therefore said to Peter, Put the sword into the sheath; the cup which the Father has given me, shall I not drink it? 12 The band therefore, and the chiliarch, and the officers of the Jews, took Jesus and bound him:

13 and they led him away to Annas first; for he was father-in-law to Caiaphas, who was high priest that year. 14 But it was Caiaphas who counselled the Jews that it was better that one man should perish for the people. 15 Now Simon Peter followed Jesus, and the other disciple. But that disciple was known to the high priest, and went in with Jesus into the palace of the high priest; 16 but Peter stood at the door without. The other disciple therefore, who was known to the high priest, went out and spoke to the porteress and brought in Peter. 17 The maid therefore, who was porteress, says to Peter, Art thou also of the disciples of this man? He says, I am not. 18 But the bondmen and officers, having made a fire of coals (for it was cold), stood and warmed themselves; and Peter was standing with them and warming himself. 19 The high priest therefore demanded of Jesus concerning his disciples and concerning his doctrine. 20 Jesus answered him, I spoke openly to the world; I taught always in the synagogue and in the temple, where all the Jews come together, and in secret I have spoken nothing. 21 Why demandest thou of me? Demand of those who have heard, what I have spoken to them; behold, they know what I have said. 22 But as he said these things, one of the officers who stood by gave a blow on the face to Jesus, saying, Answerest thou the high priest thus? 23 Jesus answered him, If I have spoken evil, bear witness of the evil; but if well, why smitest thou me? 24 Annas then had sent him bound to Caiaphas the high priest. 25 But Simon Peter was standing and warming himself. They said therefore to him, Art thou also of his disciples? He denied, and said, I am not. 26 One of the bondmen of the high priest, who was kinsman of him whose ear Peter cut off, says, Did not I see thee in the garden with him? 27 Peter denied therefore again, and immediately the cock crew.

28 They lead therefore Jesus from Caiaphas to the praetorium; and it was early morn. And they entered not into the praetorium, that they might not be defiled, but eat the passover. 29 Pilate therefore went out to them and said, What accusation do ye bring against this man? 30 They answered and said to him, If this man were not an evildoer, we should not have delivered him up to thee. 31 Pilate therefore said to them, Take him, ye, and judge him according to your law. The Jews therefore said to him, It is not permitted to us to put any one to death; 32 that the word of Jesus might be fulfilled which he spoke, signifying what death he should die. 33 Pilate therefore entered again into the praetorium and called Jesus, and said to him, Thou art the king of the Jews? 34 Jesus answered him, Dost thou say this of thyself, or have others said it to thee concerning me? 35 Pilate answered, Am I a Jew? Thy nation and the chief priests have delivered thee up to me: what hast thou done? 36 Jesus answered, My kingdom is not of this world; if my kingdom were of this world, my servants had fought that I might not be delivered up to the Jews; but now my kingdom is not from hence. 37 Pilate therefore said to him, Thou art then a king? Jesus answered, Thou sayest it, that I am a king. I have been born for this, and for this I have come into the world, that I might bear witness to the truth. Every one that is of the truth hears my voice. 38 Pilate says to him, What is truth? And having said this he went out again to the Jews, and says to them, I find no fault whatever in him. 39 But ye have a custom that I release some one to you at the passover; will ye therefore that I release unto you the king of the Jews? 40 They cried therefore again all, saying, Not this man, but Barabbas. Now Barabbas was a robber.

John 19

1 Then Pilate therefore took Jesus and scourged him. 2 And the soldiers having plaited a crown of thorns put it on his head, and put a purple robe on him, 3 and came to him and said, Hail, king of the Jews! and gave him blows on the face. 4 And Pilate went out again and says to them, Lo, I bring him out to you, that ye may know that I find in him no fault whatever. 5 (Jesus therefore went forth without, wearing the crown of thorn, and the purple robe.) And he says to them, Behold the man! 6 When therefore the chief priests and the officers saw him they cried out saying, Crucify, crucify him. Pilate says to them, Take him ye and crucify him, for I find no fault in him. 7 The Jews answered him, We have a law, and according to our law he ought to die, because he made himself Son of God. 8 When Pilate therefore heard this word, he was the rather afraid, 9 and went into the praetorium again and says to Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus gave him no answer. 10 Pilate therefore says to him, Speakest thou not to me? Dost thou not know that I have authority to release thee and have authority to crucify thee? 11 Jesus answered, Thou hadst no authority whatever against me if it were not given to thee from above. On this account he that has delivered me up to thee has the greater sin. 12 From this time Pilate sought to release him; but the Jews cried out saying, If thou releasest this man, thou art not a friend to Caesar. Every one making himself a king speaks against Caesar. 13 Pilate therefore, having heard these words, led Jesus out and sat down upon the judgment-seat, at a place called Pavement, but in Hebrew Gabbatha; 14 (now it was the preparation of the passover; it was about the sixth hour;) and he says to the Jews, Behold your king! 15 But they cried out, Take him away, take him away, crucify him. Pilate says to them, Shall I crucify your king? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Caesar.

16 Then therefore he delivered him up to them, that he might be crucified; and they took Jesus and led him away. 17 And he went out, bearing his cross, to the place called place of a skull, which is called in Hebrew, Golgotha; 18 where they crucified him, and with him two others, one on this side, and one on that, and Jesus in the middle.

19 And Pilate wrote a title also and put it on the cross. But there was written: Jesus the Nazaraean, the King of the Jews. 20 This title therefore many of the Jews read, for the place of the city where Jesus was crucified was near; and it was written in Hebrew, Greek, Latin. 21 The chief priests of the Jews therefore said to Pilate, Do not write, The king of the Jews, but that he said, I am king of the Jews. 22 Pilate answered, What I have written, I have written. 23 The soldiers therefore, when they had crucified Jesus, took his clothes, and made four parts, to each soldier a part, and the body-coat; but the body-coat was seamless, woven through the whole from the top. 24 They said therefore to one another, Let us not rend it, but let us cast lots for it, whose it shall be; that the scripture might be fulfilled which says, They parted my garments among themselves, and on my vesture they cast lots. The soldiers therefore did these things. 25 And by the cross of Jesus stood his mother, and the sister of his mother, Mary the wife of Clopas, and Mary of Magdala. 26 Jesus therefore, seeing his mother, and the disciple standing by, whom he loved, says to his mother, Woman, behold thy son. 27 Then he says unto the disciple, Behold thy mother. And from that hour the disciple took her to his own home. 28 After this, Jesus, knowing that all things were now finished, that the scripture might be fulfilled, says, I thirst. 29 There was a vessel therefore there full of vinegar, and having filled a sponge with vinegar, and putting hyssop round it, they put it up to his mouth. 30 When therefore Jesus had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished; and having bowed his head, he delivered up his spirit.

31 The Jews therefore, that the bodies might not remain on the cross on the sabbath, for it was the preparation, (for the day of that sabbath was a great day,) demanded of Pilate that their legs might be broken and they taken away. 32 The soldiers therefore came and broke the legs of the first and of the other that had been crucified with him; 33 but coming to Jesus, when they saw that he was already dead they did not break his legs, 34 but one of the soldiers pierced his side with a spear, and immediately there came out blood and water. 35 And he who saw it bears witness, and his witness is true, and he knows that he says true that ye also may believe. 36 For these things took place that the scripture might be fulfilled, Not a bone of him shall be broken. 37 And again another scripture says, They shall look on him whom they pierced.

38 And after these things Joseph of Arimathaea, who was a disciple of Jesus, but secretly through fear of the Jews, demanded of Pilate that he might take the body of Jesus: and Pilate allowed it. He came therefore and took away the body of Jesus. 39 And Nicodemus also, who at first came to Jesus by night, came, bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about a hundred pounds weight. 40 They took therefore the body of Jesus and bound it up in linen with the spices, as it is the custom with the Jews to prepare for burial. 41 But there was in the place where he had been crucified a garden, and in the garden a new tomb in which no one had ever been laid. 42 There therefore, on account of the preparation of the Jews, because the tomb was near, they laid Jesus.

John 20

1 And on the first day of the week Mary of Magdala comes in early morn to the tomb, while it was still dark, and sees the stone taken away from the tomb. 2 She runs therefore and comes to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple, to whom Jesus was attached, and says to them, They have taken away the Lord out of the tomb, and we know not where they have laid him. 3 Peter therefore went forth, and the other disciple, and came to the tomb. 4 And the two ran together, and the other disciple ran forward faster than Peter, and came first to the tomb, 5 and stooping down he sees the linen cloths lying; he did not however go in. 6 Simon Peter therefore comes, following him, and entered into the tomb, and sees the linen cloths lying, 7 and the handkerchief which was upon his head, not lying with the linen cloths, but folded up in a distinct place by itself. 8 Then entered in therefore the other disciple also who came first to the tomb, and he saw and believed; 9 for they had not yet known the scripture, that he must rise from among the dead. 10 The disciples therefore went away again to their own home.

11 But Mary stood at the tomb weeping without. As therefore she wept, she stooped down into the tomb, 12 and beholds two angels sitting in white garments, one at the head and one at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain. 13 And they say to her, Woman, why dost thou weep? She says to them, Because they have taken away my Lord, and I know not where they have laid him. 14 Having said these things she turned backward and beholds Jesus standing there, and knew not that it was Jesus. 15 Jesus says to her, Woman, why dost thou weep? Whom seekest thou? She, supposing that it was the gardener, says to him, Sir, if thou hast borne him hence, tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will take him away. 16 Jesus says to her, Mary. She, turning round, says to him in Hebrew, Rabboni, which means Teacher. 17 Jesus says to her, Touch me not, for I have not yet ascended to my Father; but go to my brethren and say to them, I ascend to my Father and your Father, and to my God and your God. 18 Mary of Magdala comes bringing word to the disciples that she had seen the Lord, and that he had said these things to her.

19 When therefore it was evening on that day, which was the first day of the week, and the doors shut where the disciples were, through fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in the midst, and says to them, Peace be to you. 20 And having said this, he shewed to them his hands and his side. The disciples rejoiced therefore, having seen the Lord. 21 Jesus said therefore again to them, Peace be to you: as the Father sent me forth, I also send you. 22 And having said this, he breathed into them, and says to them, Receive the Holy Spirit: 23 whose soever sins ye remit, they are remitted to them; whose soever sins ye retain, they are retained. 24 But Thomas, one of the twelve, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came. 25 The other disciples therefore said to him, We have seen the Lord. But he said to them, Unless I see in his hands the mark of the nails, and put my finger into the mark of the nails, and put my hand into his side, I will not believe.

26 And eight days after, his disciples were again within, and Thomas with them. Jesus comes, the doors being shut, and stood in the midst and said, Peace be to you. 27 Then he says to Thomas, Bring thy finger here and see my hands; and bring thy hand and put it into my side; and be not unbelieving, but believing. 28 Thomas answered and said to him, My Lord and my God. 29 Jesus says to him, Because thou hast seen me thou hast believed: blessed they who have not seen and have believed. 30 Many other signs therefore also Jesus did before his disciples, which are not written in this book; 31 but these are written that ye may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and that believing ye might have life in his name.

John 21

1 After these things Jesus manifested himself again to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias. And he manifested himself thus. 2 There were together Simon Peter, and Thomas called Didymus, and Nathanael who was of Cana of Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two others of his disciples. 3 Simon Peter says to them, I go to fish. They say to him, We also come with thee. They went forth, and went on board, and that night took nothing. 4 And early morn already breaking, Jesus stood on the shore; the disciples however did not know that it was Jesus. 5 Jesus therefore says to them, Children, have ye anything to eat? They answered him, No. 6 And he said to them, Cast the net at the right side of the ship and ye will find. They cast therefore, and they could no longer draw it, from the multitude of fishes. 7 That disciple therefore whom Jesus loved says to Peter, It is the Lord. Simon Peter therefore, having heard that it was the Lord, girded his overcoat on him (for he was naked), and cast himself into the sea; 8 and the other disciples came in the small boat, for they were not far from the land, but somewhere about two hundred cubits, dragging the net of fishes. 9 When therefore they went out on the land, they see a fire of coals there, and fish laid on it, and bread. 10 Jesus says to them, Bring of the fishes which ye have now taken. 11 Simon Peter went up and drew the net to the land full of great fishes, a hundred and fifty-three; and though there were so many, the net was not rent. 12 Jesus says to them, Come and dine. But none of the disciples dared inquire of him, Who art thou? knowing that it was the Lord. 13 Jesus comes and takes the bread and gives it to them, and the fish in like manner. 14 This is already the third time that Jesus had been manifested to the disciples, being risen from among the dead.

15 When therefore they had dined, Jesus says to Simon Peter, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me more than these? He says to him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I am attached to thee. He says to him, Feed my lambs. 16 He says to him again a second time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? He says to him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I am attached to thee. He says to him, Shepherd my sheep. 17 He says to him the third time, Simon, son of Jonas, art thou attached to me? Peter was grieved because he said to him the third time, Art thou attached to me? and said to him, Lord, thou knowest all things; thou knowest that I am attached to thee. Jesus says to him, Feed my sheep. 18 Verily, verily, I say to thee, When thou wast young, thou girdedst thyself, and walkedst where thou desiredst; but when thou shalt be old, thou shalt stretch forth thy hands, and another shall gird thee, and bring thee where thou dost not desire. 19 But he said this signifying by what death he should glorify God. And having said this, he says to him, Follow me.

20 Peter, turning round, sees the disciple whom Jesus loved following, who also leaned at supper on his breast, and said, Lord, who is it that delivers thee up? 21 Peter, seeing him, says to Jesus, Lord, and what of this man? 22 Jesus says to him, If I will that he abide until I come, what is that to thee? Follow thou me. 23 This word therefore went out among the brethren, That disciple does not die. And Jesus did not say to him, He does not die; but, If I will that he abide until I come, what is that to thee? 24 This is the disciple who bears witness concerning these things, and who has written these things; and we know that his witness is true. 25 And there are also many other things which Jesus did, the which if they were written one by one, I suppose that not even the world itself would contain the books written.

Acts 1

1 I composed the first discourse, O Theophilus, concerning all things which Jesus began both to do and to teach, 2 until that day in which, having by the Holy Spirit charged the apostles whom he had chosen, he was taken up; 3 to whom also he presented himself living, after he had suffered, with many proofs; being seen by them during forty days, and speaking of the things which concern the kingdom of God; 4 and, being assembled with them, commanded them not to depart from Jerusalem, but to await the promise of the Father, which said he ye have heard of me. 5 For John indeed baptised with water, but ye shall be baptised with the Holy Spirit after now not many days.

6 They therefore, being come together, asked him saying, Lord, is it at this time that thou restorest the kingdom to Israel? 7 And he said to them, It is not yours to know times or seasons, which the Father has placed in his own authority; 8 but ye will receive power, the Holy Spirit having come upon you, and ye shall be my witnesses both in Jerusalem, and in all Judaea and Samaria, and to the end of the earth. 9 And having said these things he was taken up, they beholding him, and a cloud received him out of their sight. 10 And as they were gazing into heaven, as he was going, behold, also two men stood by them in white clothing, 11 who also said, Men of Galilee, why do ye stand looking into heaven? This Jesus who has been taken up from you into heaven, shall thus come in the manner in which ye have beheld him going into heaven.

12 Then they returned to Jerusalem from the mount called the mount of Olives, which is near Jerusalem, a sabbath-day's journey off. 13 And when they were come into the city, they went up to the upper chamber, where were staying both Peter, and John, and James, and Andrew, Philip and Thomas, Bartholomew and Matthew, James son of Alphaeus, and Simon the zealot, and Jude the brother of James. 14 These gave themselves all with one accord to continual prayer, with several women, and Mary the mother of Jesus, and with his brethren.

15 And in those days Peter, standing up in the midst of the brethren, said, (the crowd of names who were together was about a hundred and twenty,) 16 Brethren, it was necessary that the scripture should have been fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit spoke before, by the mouth of David, concerning Judas, who became guide to those who took Jesus; 17 for he was numbered amongst us, and had received a part in this service. 18 (This man then indeed got a field with the reward of iniquity, and, having fallen down headlong, burst in the midst, and all his bowels gushed out. 19 And it was known to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that that field was called in their own dialect Aceldama; that is, field of blood.) 20 For it is written in the book of Psalms, Let his homestead become desolate, and let there be no dweller in it; and, Let another take his overseership. 21 It is necessary therefore, that of the men who have assembled with us all the time in which the Lord Jesus came in and went out among us, 22 beginning from the baptism of John until the day in which he was taken up from us, one of these should be a witness with us of his resurrection. 23 And they appointed two, Joseph, who was called Barsabas, who had been surnamed Justus, and Matthias. 24 And they prayed, and said, Thou Lord, knower of the hearts of all, shew which one of these two thou hast chosen, 25 to receive the lot of this service and apostleship, from which Judas transgressing fell to go to his own place. 26 And they gave lots on them, and the lot fell on Matthias, and he was numbered with the eleven apostles.

Acts 2

1 And when the day of Pentecost was now accomplishing, they were all together in one place. 2 And there came suddenly a sound out of heaven as of a violent impetuous blowing, and filled all the house where they were sitting. 3 And there appeared to them parted tongues, as of fire, and it sat upon each one of them. 4 And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and began to speak with other tongues as the Spirit gave to them to speak forth.

5 Now there were dwelling at Jerusalem Jews, pious men, from every nation of those under heaven. 6 But the rumour of this having spread, the multitude came together and were confounded, because each one heard them speaking in his own dialect. 7 And all were amazed and wondered, saying, Behold, are not all these who are speaking Galilaeans? 8 and how do we hear them each in our own dialect in which we have been born, 9 Parthians, and Medes, and Elamites, and those who inhabit Mesopotamia, and Judaea, and Cappadocia, Pontus and Asia, 10 both Phrygia and Pamphylia, Egypt, and the parts of Libya which adjoin Cyrene, and the Romans sojourning here, both Jews and proselytes, 11 Cretans and Arabians, we hear them speaking in our own tongues the great things of God? 12 And they were all amazed and in perplexity, saying one to another, What would this mean? 13 But others mocking said, They are full of new wine.

14 But Peter, standing up with the eleven, lifted up his voice and spoke forth to them, Men of Judaea, and all ye inhabitants of Jerusalem, let this be known to you, and give heed to my words: 15 for these are not full of wine, as ye suppose, for it is the third hour of the day; 16 but this is that which was spoken through the prophet Joel, 17 And it shall be in the last days, saith God, that I will pour out of my Spirit upon all flesh; and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, and your young men shall see visions, and your elders shall dream with dreams; 18 yea, even upon my bondmen and upon my bondwomen in those days will I pour out of my Spirit, and they shall prophesy. 19 And I will give wonders in the heaven above and signs on the earth below, blood, and fire, and vapour of smoke: 20 the sun shall be changed to darkness and the moon to blood, before the great and gloriously appearing day of the Lord come. 21 And it shall be that whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. 22 Men of Israel, hear these words: Jesus the Nazaraean, a man borne witness to by God to you by works of power and wonders and signs, which God wrought by him in your midst, as yourselves know 23 --him, given up by the determinate counsel and foreknowledge of God, ye, by the hand of lawless men, have crucified and slain. 24 Whom God has raised up, having loosed the pains of death, inasmuch as it was not possible that he should be held by its power; 25 for David says as to him, I foresaw the Lord continually before me, because he is at my right hand that I may not be moved. 26 Therefore has my heart rejoiced and my tongue exulted; yea more, my flesh also shall dwell in hope, 27 for thou wilt not leave my soul in hades, nor wilt thou give thy gracious one to see corruption. 28 Thou hast made known to me the paths of life, thou wilt fill me with joy with thy countenance. 29 Brethren, let it be allowed to speak with freedom to you concerning the patriarch David, that he has both died and been buried, and his monument is amongst us unto this day. 30 Being therefore a prophet, and knowing that God had sworn to him with an oath, of the fruit of his loins to set upon his throne; 31 he, seeing it before, spoke concerning the resurrection of the Christ, that neither has he been left in hades nor his flesh seen corruption. 32 This Jesus has God raised up, whereof all we are witnesses. 33 Having therefore been exalted by the right hand of God, and having received of the Father the promise of the Holy Spirit, he has poured out this which ye behold and hear. 34 For David has not ascended into the heavens, but he says himself, The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit at my right hand 35 until I have put thine enemies to be the footstool of thy feet. 36 Let the whole house of Israel therefore know assuredly that God has made him, this Jesus whom ye have crucified, both Lord and Christ.

37 And having heard it they were pricked in heart, and said to Peter and the other apostles, What shall we do, brethren? 38 And Peter said to them, Repent, and be baptised, each one of you, in the name of Jesus Christ, for remission of sins, and ye will receive the gift of the Holy Spirit. 39 For to you is the promise and to your children, and to all who are afar off, as many as the Lord our God may call. 40 And with many other words he testified and exhorted them, saying, Be saved from this perverse generation. 41 Those then who had accepted his word were baptised; and there were added in that day about three thousand souls.

42 And they persevered in the teaching and fellowship of the apostles, in breaking of bread and prayers. 43 And fear was upon every soul, and many wonders and signs took place through the apostles' means. 44 And all that believed were together, and had all things common, 45 and sold their possessions and substance, and distributed them to all, according as any one might have need. 46 And every day, being constantly in the temple with one accord, and breaking bread in the house, they received their food with gladness and simplicity of heart, 47 praising God, and having favour with all the people; and the Lord added to the assembly daily those that were to be saved.

Acts 3

1 And Peter and John went up together into the temple at the hour of prayer, which is the ninth hour; 2 and a certain man who was lame from his mother's womb was being carried, whom they placed every day at the gate of the temple called Beautiful, to ask alms of those who were going into the temple; 3 who, seeing Peter and John about to enter into the temple, asked to receive alms. 4 And Peter, looking stedfastly upon him with John, said, Look on us. 5 And he gave heed to them, expecting to receive something from them. 6 But Peter said, Silver and gold I have not; but what I have, this give I to thee: In the name of Jesus Christ the Nazaraean rise up and walk. 7 And having taken hold of him by the right hand he raised him up, and immediately his feet and ankle bones were made strong. 8 And leaping up he stood and walked, and entered with them into the temple, walking, and leaping, and praising God. 9 And all the people saw him walking and praising God; 10 and they recognised him, that it was he who sat for alms at the Beautiful gate of the temple; and they were filled with wonder and amazement at what had happened to him. 11 And as he held Peter and John, all the people ran together to them in the portico which is called Solomon's, greatly wondering.

12 And Peter, seeing it, answered the people, Men of Israel, why are ye astonished at this? or why do ye gaze on us as if we had by our own power or piety made him to walk? 13 The God of Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, the God of our fathers, has glorified his servant Jesus, whom ye delivered up, and denied him in the presence of Pilate, when he had judged that he should be let go. 14 But ye denied the holy and righteous one, and asked that a man that was a murderer should be granted to you; 15 but the originator of life ye slew, whom God raised from among the dead, whereof we are witnesses. 16 And, by faith in his name, his name has made this man strong whom ye behold and know; and the faith which is by him has given him this complete soundness in the presence of you all. 17 And now, brethren, I know that ye did it in ignorance, as also your rulers; 18 but God has thus fulfilled what he had announced beforehand by the mouth of all the prophets, that his Christ should suffer. 19 Repent therefore and be converted, for the blotting out of your sins, so that times of refreshing may come from the presence of the Lord, 20 and he may send Jesus Christ, who was foreordained for you, 21 whom heaven indeed must receive till the times of the restoring of all things, of which God has spoken by the mouth of his holy prophets since time began. 22 Moses indeed said, A prophet shall the Lord your God raise up to you out of your brethren like me: him shall ye hear in everything whatsoever he shall say to you. 23 And it shall be that whatsoever soul shall not hear that prophet shall be destroyed from among the people. 24 And indeed all the prophets from Samuel and those in succession after him, as many as have spoken, have announced also these days. 25 Ye are the sons of the prophets and of the covenant which God appointed to our fathers, saying to Abraham, And in thy seed shall all the families of the earth be blessed. 26 To you first God, having raised up his servant, has sent him, blessing you in turning each one of you from your wickedness.